Hello and welcome to Section 7 Mongo D-B mongoose and rest.
AP eyes in this section you're going to be building your very own rest API similar to the weather API
we used when we were building the weather app although instead of managing weather information you're
going to create an API that manages to do application which means we're going to need ways to create
delete complete and otherwise manage our data.
Now in order to actually store this data we could use the file system but that's a really bad idea for
most applications.
It's great when you're working with simple command line interfaces but for a real API like the one we're
going to build we want to use a real database and we're going to be using Mongo D-B to get that done.
Mongo D-B is a really popular No s ul database.
We'll talk exactly about what all of that means later.
But for now all you need to know is that it's going to let us persist user information as well as to
do information.
We're also going to be looking at Mongoose which is a library that makes it really easy to work with
Mongo D-B.
But before we add on libraries and obscure things even further let's just stick to the fundamentals.
We're going to get started by installing Mongo and we'll spend a few videos going through exactly what
Mongo is and why it's become so popular.
Let's go ahead and dive in.
Installing the database software