You know how to insert delete and fetch the documents out of Mongo D.B and this one you're going to
learn how to update documents in your Mongo IDB collections and to kick things off.
As usual we're going to duplicate the last script we wrote and we'll update it for the video.
I'm going to duplicate the delete file.
Renaming it to mango D.B hyphen update dot SJS and this is where we'll write our update statements.
I'm also going to delete all of these statements we wrote that deleted data.
Now that we have this in place we can explore the one method we'll be looking at in this video this
one is called Find one end update.
It's kind of similar to find one and delete it lets us update an item and get the new document back.
So if I update it to do set incompleted equal to true I will get that document and back in the response.
Now in order to get started we're going to be updating one of the items that we have inside of our to
do's collection.
If I gave you the documents we currently have to the goal here is going to be to update the second item
in the one where text equals eat lunch.
We're going to try to set the completed value to true which would be a pretty common action if I check
off a to do item we want to toggle that completed a boolean value back inside of Adam.
We're going to kick things off by accessing the appropriate collection.
That'll be DVD collection.
The collection name is uppercase t to do's and the method we'll be using is find one and update.
Now find one and update is going to take the most arguments we've used so far.
So let's go ahead and look up the documentation for it.
So you can have this for future reference.
Over inside of Chrome I can close my get hub tab.
We currently have the cursor tab open.
This is where we have the count method defined.
If we scroll down below the cursor tab we have our other tabs.
The one we're looking for is collection now inside of the collection section.
We have our type DAPs and our methods we're looking at methods here.
So if I scroll down we should be able to find find one and update and click it.
Now find one an update takes quite a few arguments.
The first one is the filter.
This lets us target the document we want to update.
Maybe we have the text or most likely we have the ID of the document.
Next up is the actual updates.
We want to make.
We don't want to update the ID we just want to filter by id the updates.
In this case are going to be updating that completed boolean.
Then we have some options which are defined below.
We'll use just one of them and we have our callback.
We're going to leave off the callback as we've been doing so far in favor of promises.
As you can see down below returns or promise if no callback has passed in and that's exactly what we
expect.
Let's go ahead and start filling out the appropriate arguments for a find one and update.
Kicking things off with that filter.
What I'm going to do is filter Abidi over inside of Roboam Mango I can grab the idea of this document
I'm going to edit it and copy the ID to the clipboard.
Now over inside an atom we can start querying the first object at the filter.
We're only looking for documents where the ID Eagles a new object id with the value that we copied to
the clipboard.
And this is all we need for the filter argument.
Now next up is going to be the actual updates.
We want to apply and this is not exactly straightforward.
What we have to do here is learn about the Mongo D-B update operators.
We can do a complete list of these operators and exactly what they are by googling Mongo D-B update
operators when I do this we're looking for the mango D-B dot com documentation.
Now this documentation is specific to Mongo D-B which means it's going to work with all of the drivers
in this case that is going to work with our node J.S. driver.
And if we scroll down below we can look at all of the update operators we have access to.
The most important and the one we're going to get started with is the set operator this.
Let's set a field a value inside of an update which is exactly what we want to do.
There's other operators like increment and this one money sign and see let you increment a field's value
like the H field in our users collection.
All of these are super useful.
We're going to get started with set though in order to use one of these operators what we need to do
is type it out set and then set it equal to an object and in this object.
These are the things that we're actually going to be setting.
For example we want a set completed equal to true.
If we tried to put completed equal to true at the root of this object like this it would not work as
expected.
We have to use these update operators which means we need this.
And now that we have our updates in place using the set update operator we can go ahead and provide
our third and final argument.
If you head over to the documentation for find one an update we can take a look at the options real
quick.
The one we care about is return original return original is defaulted to true which means that it returns
the original document not the updated one and we don't want that when we update a document.
We want to get back that updated document.
So what we're going to do is set return original to false.
That's going to happen in our third and final argument.
This one is also going to be an object return original setting equal to Wells.
Now with this in place we are done we can tack on and then call to do something with the results right
here and get my result back and I can simply print it to the screen and we can take a look at exactly
what comes back.
Excellent.
And now let's go ahead and run this from the terminal.
I'm going to save my file over inside of the terminal.
We're going to be running node.
The file is in the playground folder and we just called it Mongo D-B hyphen update dot and jazz.
I'm going to run the script and what do we get back we get back at the value prop just like we did when
we used to find one and delete.
And this has our document with the completed value set to true which is the brand new value we just
set.
And this is fantastic.
If we head over to Roble Mongo we can confirm that the value was indeed updated.
Here's the old document where the value is false.
I'm going to open up a new view for dues.
And what do we get.
We had lunch with a completed value of true.
Now that we have this in place we know how to insert delete update and read documents from our Mongo
D-B collections to wrap this video up.
I want to give you a quick challenge over inside of the users collection.
You should have a document.
It should have some name it's probably not.
It's probably something that you set when I want you to do is update this name to your name.
Now if it's already your name that's fine you can change it to something else.
I also want you to use that eye and see the increment operator that we talked about to increment this
by one.
Now I'm not going to tell you exactly how increment works but I want you to do is head over to the docks.
Click on the operator and then you can scroll down to see the examples there's examples for each operator.
It's going to become really useful to you to learn how to read documentation.
Now documentation for libraries is not always going to be the same.
Everyone does it a little differently but once you learn how to read the docs for one library it gets
a lot easier to read the docs for others.
And I can only teach so much in this course.
The real goal of this course is to get you writing your own code doing your own research and looking
up your own documentation.
So your goal once again is to update this document setting the name to something other than what it's
currently set to and incrementing the age by one.
Take a moment to knock this out.
Test it.
Make sure it works.
And when you're done you can go ahead and click play and I'll show you how I would have done it.
Hopefully that went well.
To kick things off I'm going to grab the idea of the document right here.
This is the document I want to update I'll copy it to the clipboard.
Now we can focus on writing that statement over inside of atom.
First up we'll update the names since we already know how to do that.
Inside the atom I'm going to go ahead and duplicate the statement I have here I'll copy and paste it
and then I'm going to go back and grab the idea again since I just removed it from a clipboard.
Awesome.
And now back inside of out and we can start swapping things out.
First up we're going to swap out the old ID for the new one and we're going to change what we pass to
set instead of updating completed.
We want to update name.
I'm going to set name equal to something other than Gen.
I'm going to go ahead and use my name.
Andrew now we are going to keep returning original set to false.
We want to get the new document back.
Not the original.
Now the other thing we needed to do was increment that age.
This was going to be done via the increment operator which you should have explored using the documentation
over inside of chrome.
If you clicked on Anke that's going to bring you to that part of the documentation and if you scroll
down you should be able to see an example right here we have an example of what it looks like to increment
we set ink just like we set set.
Then inside of the object we specify the things we want to increment and the degree to which we want
to increment them.
It could be negative 2 or in our case it would be positive 1 over inside out and we can implement this
right here.
I'll set.
Ink equal to an object and on there will increment the age by 1.
And with this in place we are now done.
Before I do run this file I am going to comment out to the other call to find one an update just leaving
the new one.
I also need to swap out the collection.
We're no longer updating the to do's collection we're updating that users collection and now we are
good to go.
We're setting name equal to Andrew and we're incrementing the age by 1 which means that we would expect
the age in Roboam Mongo to be 26 instead of twenty five.
Let's go ahead and run this by restarting the script over inside of the terminal.
Then we can see our new document where the name is indeed Andrew and the age is indeed 26 and this is
fantastic.
Now you know how to use the increment operator.
You can also go off and learn all of the other operators you have available to you inside of your update
calls.
I can double check that everything did work as expected over inside of Roboam Mongo.
I'm going to go ahead and refresh the users collection.
And what do we have.
We have our updated document right here.
Let's wrap this video up by committing our changes over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to run get status so we can view all of the changes to the repository here we just have one
unchecked File.
Our Mongo D-B update script.
I'm going to use a get and to add that to the next commit and then I'll use get commit to actually make
the commit.
I am going to provide that an argument for a message so we can specify a message and update script.
Excellent.
And now we can run the commit command and push it up to get hubs so our code is backed up on our get
hub repository with updating in place so we don't have all of the basic crud operations down crud standing
for creating reading updating and deleting.
Up next we're going to talk about something called mongoose which we'll be using for the to do API.
It's coming up soon so stay tuned.
We'll see you next time.