In the last several videos you learn how to use the Mongo D-B native driver and that let you create
and it update and delete documents from here on out.
We're also going to be using something called mongoose mongoose which is an O R M standing for object
relational mapping is a fantastic NPM library.
It makes it really easy to structure your data.
For example in this app we're going to have to do's and users to do needs certain things it needs certain
properties of certain types maybe we want to add some custom validation for them for the user for example
we need to validate their password.
All of this is a lot easier with mongoose in place.
Is it possible that mongoose.
Yes it is.
You can do everything.
Mongoose can do with a mango divi native driver but instead of writing all that boilerplate code yourself
most people prefer to use mongoose to get the job done.
Let's go ahead and start integrating it into our node code.