In this video you're finally going to move out of the playground folder and we're going to start playing
with mongoose.
We'll be connecting to our Mongo DB database creating a model talking about exactly what a model is.
And finally we'll be saving some data to the database using mongoose.
Now we're not going to need any of the files we currently have open from the playground directory so
we can go ahead and close them.
We're also going to wipe the to do app a database using robo Mongo.
The data inside of here is going to be a little different than the data we'll be using going forward
and it's best to start with a clean slate.
Now there is no need to create the database after you drop it because if you remember Mongo D-B is going
to automatically create the database once you start writing data to it.
With this in place we can now explore a mongoose and the first thing I always like to do is check out
the Web site.
You can check the website out by going to mongoose and G-S dot com.
Here you can find examples.
Guides a full list of plugins a ton of great resources.
The read the docs resource is the one I use the most.
It includes tutorial like guides that have examples as well as documentation covering every single feature
of the library.
It really is a fantastic resource if you ever want to learn about something or use a feature we don't
cover in the course.
I highly recommend coming here taking the examples copying and pasting some code playing around with
it and figuring out how it works.
Now obviously about this course for a reason.
We're going to be covering most of the essential mongoose features right now.
The first thing we need to do before we can actually use mongoose in our project is install it over
in the terminal.
I'm going to install it using NPM.
I am I being short for NPM install the module name itself is called mongoose and will be installing
the most recent version available at the time of the filming.
That's going to be version four point five point nine.
And we are going to tack on these same flags since we will need mongoose for both production and testing
purposes.
Now once we run this it's going to go off and do its thing.
We can move into atom and start creating the files we're going to need to run our application.
First up let's make a directory in the root of the project.
This directory is going to be called server and everything related to our server is going to get stored
in here.
The first file We're going to create is going to be called server.
Yes this is going to be the root of our application.
When you want to start up our node you're going to run this file.
This file will get everything ready to go.
The first thing we need to do inside of server dot J.S. is load in a mongoose.
We're going to make a variable called mongoose which I always seem to spell incorrectly and we're going
to require it from the mongoose library.
Awesome.
Now that we have the Mango's variable in place we need to go ahead and connect to the database because
we can't start writing data to the database until mongoose knows how to connect and the process of connecting
is going to be pretty similar to what we did inside of our Mongo DB scripts.
For example the connect script here we called Mongo client connect passing a u r l but we're going to
do for Mongoose is called mongoose dot connect passing in the exact same way you are out.
Mongo D-B is the protocol Colan forward slash forward slash we're going to be connecting to our local
host a database on port 2 7 0 1 7.
Next up is going to be our forward slash followed by the database name and we'll continue to use the
to do app database which we used over here in the script.
Now this is where the two functions differ.
The Mongo client connect method takes a callback and that is when we have access to the database.
Mongoose is a lot more complex.
This is good because it means our code can be a lot simpler.
Mongooses maintaining this connection over time.
So imagine down here.
I tried to save something save New something.
Now obviously by the time this statement runs mongoose connect is not going to have had time to make
a database request to connect.
That's going to take a few milliseconds at least.
This statement is going to run almost right away behind the scenes.
Mongooses is going to be waiting for that connection before it ever actually tries to make the query.
This is one of the great advantages of mongoose.
We don't have to micromanage the order things happen in mongoose takes care of that for us.
Now there is one more thing I want to configure just above Mangu stock connect.
We've been using promises in this course and we're going to continue to use them.
Mangu supports callbacks by default but callbacks really aren't how I like to program.
I prefer promises as they're a lot simpler to chain manage and scale right here.
We're going to tell mounds use which promise library we want to use.
Now if you're not familiar with the history of promises it didn't used to always be something built
into javascript promises originally came from libraries like Bluebird.
It was an idea developer had they created a library.
People start using it.
So much so that they added it to the language right here.
We need to tell mongoose that we want to use the built in promis library as opposed to some third party
one we're going to set mongoose ADOT promise equal to global dot promise.
And this is something we're only going to have to do once these two lines we're just going to put in
server dot apps.
We don't want to add them anywhere else.
And with this in place Mongoose is now configured.
We've connected to our database and we've set it up to use promises which is exactly what we want.
The next thing we're going to do is create a model.
Now as we talked about inside of Mongo D-B your collections can store anything I could have a collection
with a document that has an age property and that's it.
I could have a different document in the same collection with a property name.
That's it.
These two documents are different but they're both in the same collection.
Mongoose likes to keep things a little more organized than that.
Well we're going to do is create a model for everything we want to store in this example we'll be creating
a to do model.
Now what to do is going to have certain attributes that's going to have a text attribute we know that's
a string.
It's going to have a completed attribute we know that's a boolean.
These are things we can define but we're going to do is create a mongoose model so mongoose knows how
to store our data right here.
Let's make a variable called uppercase t to do.
And we're going to set that equal to mongoose dot model model is the method we're going to use to create
a new model.
It takes two arguments the first one is the string name I'm going to match the variable name on the
left uppercase t to do.
And the second argument is going to be an object and this object is going to define the various properties
for a model.
For example the to do model is going to have a Text property so we can set that up right here and then
we can set text equal to an object and we can configure exactly what text is.
We can do the same thing for a completed.
We're going to have a completed property and we're going to want to specify certain things maybe it's
required maybe we have custom validators maybe we want to set that type.
And we're also going to add one final one completed at this is going to let us know when a to do was
completed.
Now a created out property might sound useful but if you remember the Mongo db object id that already
has and he created at timestamped built in.
So there's no reason to add that here.
Complete it out.
On the other hand is going to add value.
It lets you know exactly when you completed a to do from here we can start specifying the details about
each attribute and there is a ton of different options available inside of the mongoose documentation.
For now though we're going to keep things really really simple just specifying the type for each text.
For example we can set any type equal to a string.
It's always going to be a string that wouldn't make sense if it was a Boolean or a number.
Down below we can set a type for completed.
Completed needs to be a boolean.
There's no way around that.
So we're going to set type equal to uppercase B boolean.
The last one we have is completed at.
Now this is going to be a regular old Unix time stamp which means it's just a number so we can set the
type for completed at equal to number.
Excellent.
With this in place we now have a working mongoose model.
It's a model of how to do that has a few properties text completed and completed at.
Now in order to illustrate exactly how we create instances of this we're going to go ahead and just
add one to do.
We're not going to worry about fetching data updating data or deleting data although that is stuff that
Mancuso supports we'll be worrying about that in the next video as we start building out the individual
routes for our API.
For now we're going to go over just a very quick example of creating a brand new to do.
I'm going to make a variable called new to do although you could call it anything you like.
The name here is not important what is important though is that you run the to do function which is
right here.
This is what comes back from mongoose top model as a constructor function.
We want to add the new keyword in front of it because we're creating a new instance of to do.
Now the to do constructor function it does take an argument.
It's going to be an object where we can specify some of these properties.
Maybe we know that we want tax to equal something like cooked dinner right here.
We can specify that text equals a string cook dinner.
Excellent.
And we haven't required any of our attributes so we could just stop here.
We have a Text property that is good enough.
Let's go ahead and explore how to save this to the database.
Creating a new instance alone does not actually update the Mongo D-B a database.
What we need to do is call a method on new to do.
That's going to be new to do dot save new to do that save is going to be responsible for actually saving
this to the bango IDB a database and save returns or promise which means right here we can tack on a
then call and we can add a few callbacks for when the data either get saved or when an error occurs
because it can't save for some reason maybe the connection failed or maybe the model is not valid.
Either way for now we'll just print a little string console dialog unable to save to do up above in
the success callback.
We're actually going to get that to do right here.
I can call the argument doc and I can print it to the screen cancel the dialog.
I'll print a little message first saved to do and the second argument will be the actual document.
And now that we have this in place we are done.
We've configured mongoose connecting to the Mongo DB database.
We've created a model specifying the attributes we want to do's to have.
We created a new to do.
And finally we saved it to the database.
I'm going to add a semi-colon at the very end and we're going to run the script from the terminal.
I'm going to kick things off by clearing the terminal output and we're running node the file we're running
is in that server directory and it's called Server dot.
And yes when I run the file what do we get.
We get saved to do.
Meaning that things went well.
We have an object right here with an ID property as expected.
The text property which we specified and this underscore underscore the property underscore underscore
the is version and it comes from mongoose.
We'll talk about it later.
But essentially it keeps track of the various model changes over time.
For now it's not important it can be ignored.
If we open up Rogel mango we're going to see the exact same data.
I'm going to Right-Click the connection and refresh it.
Here we have our to do app inside of the to do app database we have our dues collection.
Notice that mongoose automatically lower cased and pluralized to do I'm going to view the documents
and what do we have we have our one document with a text equal to cook dinner.
Exactly what we created over inside of Adam.
Now seems like a pretty good time for a challenge.
We have one to do.
Created using our mongoose model what I want you to do is make a second one filling out all three values.
That means you're going to make a new to do with a text value a completed boolean.
Go ahead and set that to true and a completed at time stamp which you can set to any number you like.
And then I want you to go ahead and save it print it to the screen if it saves successfully printing
error.
If it saves poorly then finally run it.
Make sure it shows up in Rodel Mongo and the data looks correct.
If it does you're done.
That's your challenge so take a moment pause the video.
Create a new to do and when you're done click play.
Hopefully you were able to get that done without too much trouble.
The first thing I would have done is made a new variable down below.
I'm going to make a variable called other to do setting it equal to a new instance of the to do model.
From here we can pass in our one argument which is going to be the object and we can specify all of
the values.
I can set text equal to whatever I like.
Feed the cat.
I can set the completed value equal to true which I wanted you to do and I can set completed at equal
to any number.
Anything lower than zero like negative 1 is going to go backwards from 1970 which is where zero is anything
positive is going to be where at.
And we'll talk about timestamps more later.
It For now I'm going to go with something like 123 which would basically be two minutes into the year.
Nineteen seventy.
With this in place we now just need to save.
I'm going to call other to do dot save and this is what's actually going to write to the Mongo DB database.
I am going to tack on and then call back because I do want to do something once the save is complete.
If the save worked we're going to get our doc and I'm going to print it to the screen.
I'm going to use that pretty print system we talked about earlier.
Jason docstring a phi passing in the actual object undefined and to excellent.
You didn't need to do that.
You could have printed it in any way you like.
Next up I'm going to print a little message if things go poorly Council a dialogue.
Unable to say it and I'll pass along that error object.
So if someone's reading the logs they can see exactly why the call failed.
With this in place we can now comment out that first to do this is going to prevent another one from
being created and we can rerun the script running our brand new to do.
Creation calls right here inside of the terminal I'm going to shut down the old connection and start
up a new one.
This is going to create a brand new to do and we have it right here.
TEXT equals feed the cat.
Complete it is the boolean true.
Notice there's no quotes around it and completed as is the number one at 23.
Once again no quotes.
I can also go into robo Mongo to confirm.
I'm going to re fetch the to do's collection.
And now we have to do's on the right hand side of the values you also notice the type.
Here we have 32 for completed at end of the the property the completed property is a Boolean text is
a string and the ID is an object id type.
There is a lot of useful information hidden inside of robo Mongo.
If you want something they most likely have it built in that is it for this one.
We now know how to use mongoose to make a connection.
Create a model and finally save that model to the database.
Stay tuned I will see you soon.