In this video you're going to learn how to improve your mongoose models.
This is going to let you add things like validation.
You can make certain properties required and you can set up smart defaults so if something like complete
it is not provided you can have a default value that gets set.
All of this functionality is built into mongoose.
We just have to learn how to use it and to illustrate why we'd want to set this stuff up.
Let's scroll to the bottom of our server file and remove all of the properties on the new.
Do we create then we're going to save the file and move into the terminal running the script that's
going to be node in the server directory and the file is called server.
Yes.
When we run it what do we get.
We get our new to do but it only has the version and Id properties all of the properties we specified
in the model tax completed and completed.
They're nowhere to be found.
That's a pretty big problem.
We should not be adding to dues to the database if they don't have a Text property and things like completed
should have smart defaults.
No one is going to create a to do item if they already completed it so completed should default to false.
Now in order to get started we're going to pull up two pages in the mongoose documentation just so you
know where this stuff lives.
If you ever want to dive deeper in the future.
First up we're going to look up the validators.
I'm going to google mongoose validators and this is going to show us all of the default validation properties
we have built in.
For example we can set something as required.
So if it's not provided it's going to throw an error when we try to save that model.
We can also set up validators for things like numbers and strings giving a min max value or a min length
max length value for a string.
The other page we're going to look at is the schemas page to get to this.
We're going to google mongoose schemas.
This is the first one the guide dot h t m l file and on this page you're going to see something slightly
different from what we've been doing so far.
Right here.
They call new schema setting up all of their properties.
This is not something we've done yet but we will in the future.
For now you can consider this object the schema object identical to the one we have over an atom that
we pass in as the second argument to our mongoose model.
Call to kick things off.
Let's customize how mongoose treats are taxed property.
Currently we tell mongoose that we want it to be a string but we don't have any validators.
One of the first things we can do for the Text property is set required equal to true.
When you set required equal to true the value must exist.
So if I were to try to save this to do it would fail and we can prove this we can save the file head
over to the terminal shut things down or restart it.
And what do we get.
We get unreadable error message.
We'll dive into this in a second.
But for now all you need to know is that we're getting a validation error to do validation failed and
that is fantastic.
Now aside from just making sure the Text property exists we can also set up some custom validators for
strings.
For example we have a min length validator and this is fantastic.
You shouldn't be able to create it to do whose text is an empty string like this one.
We can set min length equal to the minimum length which we're going to set as one in this case now even
if we do provide a text property down below let's say we get taxed equal to an empty string it's still
going to fail.
It is indeed there but it does not pass this validator or the min length must be 1.
I can save the server file restart things over in the terminal and we still get a failure.
Now aside from required and min length there are a couple other utilities that are around in the docs.
One good example is something called trim trim is fantastic for strings essentially trim trim off any
white space in the beginning or end of your value.
If I set trim equal to true it's going to remove any leading or trailing whitespace.
So if I try to create a to do whose text property is just a bunch of spaces it's still going to fail
the term property is going to remove all of the leading and trailing spaces leaving an empty string.
And if I rerun things we still get a failure in the text field is invalid.
Now if we do provide a valid value things are going to work as expected.
Right in the middle of all of these spaces I'm going to provide a REAL to do a value edit this video
when we try to save this to do what's going to happen is first up these spaces in the beginning and
the end of the string.
Those are going to get trimmed and then it's going to validate that this string has a minimum length
of 1 which it does.
And finally it will save the to do to the database.
I'm going to go ahead and save server japes restart our script and this time around we get our to do
it this video shows up as the text property.
Those A leading and trailing spaces have been removed.
And this is fantastic.
Using just three properties we were able to configure our text property setting up some validation.
Now we can do similar stuff for completed for completed.
We're not going to require it because the completed value is most likely going to default to false.
So what we can do instead is set the default property giving this completed field the default value
now completed as we talked about earlier in the video should default to false.
There is no reason to create it to do if it's already done.
We can do the same thing for completed as if a to do starts off not completed and completed and is not
going to exist completed is only going to exist when that to do has been completed it's going to be
that time stamp.
So what I'm going to do is set default equal to no.
Awesome.
Now with this in place we have a pretty good schema for our to do.
We're going to validate that the text is set up properly by the user and we are going to set up these
values by ourself since we can just use defaults.
With this in place I can now rerun our server file and here we get a better default to do we have the
text of the user provided it's been validated and trimmed down below.
We have completed set to false and it completed and set to NULL.
And this is fantastic.
We now have a foolproof schema that has good defaults and validation.
Now if you've been playing around with the various types you might have noticed that if you set a type
equal to something other than the type you specified in certain cases it does still work.
For example down below if I try to set text equal to an object I'm going to get an error that's going
to say hey you tried to use a string but that object showed up instead.
But if I try to set text equal to something like a number I'm going to go with 23.
This is going to work.
That's because Mongoose is going to cast your number in to a string essentially wrapping it in quotes.
The same thing is going to be true with a boolean.
If I pass in a boolean like this the resulting string is going to be the one I have right here.
I'm going to go ahead and save the file after setting text equal to true and run the script when I do
it.
What do I get.
I get taxed equal to true right here.
Notice it is indeed wrapped in quotes.
It's important to be aware that typecasting does exist inside of mongoose.
It can easily trip you up and cause some unexpected errors.
For now though I am going to set text back equal to a proper string now it's time for a challenge where
you are going to be responsible for creating a brand new mongoose model.
Down below I'll leave a few comments describing what I'd like to do.
First up you're going to make a new user model and eventually we're going to use this for authentication.
It's going to store stuff like an e-mail a password and the to do's are going to be associated with
the user.
So when I create one only I can edit it.
Now that's all going to happen later.
For now we're going to keep things really simple on the user.
The only property you need to set up is the email property we'll set up others like password later.
But it's going to be done a little differently since it needs to be secure so for now we'll just stick
with e-mail.
I do want you to require it.
I also want you to Trinite.
So if someone adds spaces before after those spaces go away.
Last but not least.
Go ahead and set the type equal to a string set type and set min length of one.
Now obviously you'll be able to pass in a string that's not an e-mail.
We'll explore custom validation a little later.
This is going to let us validate that the email is an e-mail.
But for now this is going to get us on the right track.
Once you have your mongoose model created I want you to go ahead and try to create a new user create
one without the email property and then make one with one making sure that when you run the script the
data shows up as expected over in Roboam Mongo.
And this data should show up in the new users collection.
Take a moment to create the model save a user and check it out in the database.
Pause the video and when you're done go ahead and click play.
And I hope that wasn't too much trouble the first thing I'm going to do is make a variable to store
this new model a variable called uppercase U user and I'm going to set that equal to mongoose dot model
which is how we can make our new user model.
The first argument as you know needs to be the string model name.
I'm going to use the exact same name as I specified over in the variable although it could be different
I just like to keep things using this pattern where the variable equals the model name.
Next up as the second argument we can specify the object where we can figure all the properties a user
should have.
Now as I mentioned we'll be adding others later.
But for now adding support for an email property will be good enough and there's a few things I want
to do on this e-mail.
First up I want to set the type.
An email is always going to be a string so we can set that type equal to string.
Next up we're going to require it.
You can't make a user without an e-mail.
So all set required equal to true after required.
We're going to go ahead and trim that e-mail if someone adds spaces before or after it it's clearly
a mistake.
So we'll go ahead and remove those for the user.
Making your application just a little more user friendly.
Last but not least what we want to do is set up a min length.
We'll be setting up customer validation later but for now a min length of one is going to get the trick
done.
Now I am going to go ahead and create a new instance of this user and save it before I run the script.
Though I will be commenting out are new to do I actually have to do is commented out now so I'm going
to go ahead and remove the first one leaving the second one.
There's no need to have two examples of the same thing.
And now down below we can pick a new instance of this a user model.
I'm going to make a variable called user and set it equal to new user passing in any values we want
to set on that user.
Now I'm going to run it with nothing at first just to make sure the validation is working.
Down below I can now call user dot save.
Save returns I promise.
So I can tack on a and then call back I'm going to add a success case for this one an air handler the
air handler will get that air argument and the success case will get the duck if things go well I'll
print a message using console dialogue.
Use or saved followed by the doc.
No need to format it for this example and I'll do the same thing down below.
Council dot log.
Unable to save user followed by the error object.
Now since we're creating a user with no properties we would expect the error to print.
I'm going to save server datcha Yes restart the file and what do we get.
We get our error.
It's a validation error path.
Email is required mongooses letting us know that we do indeed have an error.
The email does need to exist since we set required equal to true.
I'm going to go ahead and put a value in here.
Sending email to my email Andrew at example dot com and I'll put a few spaces afterwards this time around.
Things should go as expected and trim should be trimming the end of that email removing all the spaces
and that's exactly what we get.
The user was indeed saved which is great and the email has been properly formatted.
Now obviously I could have put a string in like 1 to 3 and it would have worked because we don't have
custom validation set up just yet.
But we have a pretty good starting point.
We have the user model and we have our email Propp set up and ready to go.
With this in place we are now going to start creating that API in the next video.
You're going to install a tool called post man which is going to help us test our TTP requests.
Then right after that one which will be a quick one we're going to create our very first route for our
to do rest API