This video you're going to learn how to use post ma'am.
Postman isn't a central tool if you're building a rest API.
I have never worked with a team or on a project where post man was not heavily used by every developer
involved.
Postman lets you create HTP requests and fire them off.
That makes it really easy to test that everything you're writing is working as expected.
Now obviously we will also be writing automated tests but using postman lets you play around with data
and see how things work as you move through your API.
It really is a fantastic tool to grab it.
We're going to head over to the browser and go to get post man and dot com.
And here we can grab their chrome application.
Now if you're not using Chrome you are going to need to install it although you don't have to use the
Chrome browser.
All you have to do is install Chrome to install the app.
Open up postman and you never have to use Chrome again.
If you already use Chrome great.
Go ahead and install that.
If you are on a Mac they just introduced a Mac app.
It is a great alternative.
It has all the same features it's just bundled differently instead of opening Chrome to open postman.
You can just open the app from Spotlight like I can here.
Hey what's going on.
It's and you're from the future with a quick interruption.
If you go over to the post man Web site you're going to notice there's no longer a chrome app download
option.
That's because Google Chrome is deprecating the entire idea of a chrome application.
So that whole ecosystem is going away.
But that's perfectly fine because post man has released applications for all operating systems.
So whether you're on Mac whether you're on Windows or Linux you can find the native application for
your operating system.
It's the exact same app it's just specific to your OS.
So go ahead and grab the one for your system.
Then we can just go ahead and continue on as usual.
All right let's jump back in to the regular video.
Now I'm going to be using the chrome application since that's most likely what you'll be using if you're
not on a Mac to install it.
All you have to do is install the chrome app from the Chrome store click add to Chrome and it should
bring you over to the page where you can open up the application.
Now to open up chrome apps you have to go to this kind of weird you are Alex chrome colon forward slash
forwards slash apps here.
You can view all of your apps and we can just open up postman by clicking it.
Now as I mentioned post man lets you make HTP requests so we're going to go ahead and make a few to
play around with the user interface.
You do not need to make an account and you do not need to sign up for a paid plan that paid plans are
targeted towards teams of developers who need advanced features.
We are just making basic requests on our machine.
We don't need cloud storage or anything like that.
I'm going to skip account creation and we go right to the application here.
We can set up our request.
This is what happens in the panel right here and down below in the whitespace will be able to view the
result.
Let's go ahead and make a request to Google in the you are Albar I'm going to type HTP call.
Forward slash.
Google dot com.
We can click send it to send off that request.
Make sure you have get chosen as your HTP method.
When I fire off the request it comes back and all of the data that comes back is shown below.
We have things like the status code.
We have a 200 here meaning things went great.
We have the time it took about a quarter of a second.
We have headers.
These are coming back from Google we have cookies.
There is none in this case and we have our body data the body for google.com is an H TNL Web site for
the most part the bodies that will be sending and getting in post man are going to be Jason since we're
building out that rest a P.I. so to illustrate how Jason data works we're going to make a request to
the geocoding you are out that we used earlier in the course.
If you remember we were able to pass in a location and we got some Jason back describing things like
the latitude and longitude and the formatted address.
Now this should still be in your Krown history if you deleted your history.
You can go ahead and go to Google API is right here this is the you are I'll I'll be using you can simply
copy it or you can grab any Jason API.
You are out.
I'm going to grab this one.
Copy it to the clipboard.
Head back into post man and swap out the L with the you are at I just copied.
Now I can go ahead and fire off the request.
And what do we get.
We get our Jason and data down below.
And this is fantastic.
We're able to see exactly what comes back when we make this request and this is how we're going to be
using postman will use postman to make requests to add to do's delete to do's get all of our to do's
log in.
All of that stuff is going to happen right in here.
Remember API.
They don't necessarily have a front end.
Maybe it's an Android app maybe it's an iPhone app or a web app.
Maybe it's a nother server so post man give us a way to interact with our API making sure it works as
expected.
Here we have all of the Jason data that comes back in the raw view which is underbody.
We have the raw data response.
Essentially it's just an prettified.
There is no formatting there is no colorization.
Also have a preview.
The preview is pretty useless for Jason when it comes to Jason data.
I always stick with the pretty tab which should be the default.
Now that we have post man installed and we know a little bit about how to use it we're going to move
on to the next video where we actually create our first request and we'll be firing off a post man request
to hit that you are all going to create.
This is going to let us make new to do's.
Right from post man or any other application whether it's a web app a mobile app or another server.
That's all coming up next.
So just make sure you have postman installed if you were able to do everything in this video you are
ready to continue on.
Stay tuned.
I will see you next time.