In this video you're going to create your HTP post route for adding new to do's.
Before we dive into that we're going to take a quick second to refactor everything we have in server
because it doesn't really belong here.
We have database configuration stuff which should live somewhere else and we have our models which should
also live in separate files.
The only thing we want in server G-S is our express route handlers to get started inside of the server
directory we're going to make a new folder called D-B and inside of the DB folder we'll make a file
where all of this mongoose configuration happens.
I'm going to call that file mongoose dot Yes.
And don't we need to do is take our mongoose configuration code right here cut it out and move it over
into mongoose.
Jay Yes.
Now we do need to export something.
What we're going to export is the mongoose variable.
So essentially when someone requires this file they're going to have mongoose configured and they're
going to get it back.
They're going to get back the mongoose variable that comes from the library right here.
I'm going to set module exports equal to an object and that object will set mongoose equal to mongoose.
Now as we know in Essex this can be simplified if you have a property and a variable with the same name
and you can shorten it and we can take things a step further and put it all on one line.
Excellent.
And now we have the mongoose configuration in a separate file and that file can be required right here.
I'm going to pull off the mongoose property using E.S. 6 destructuring.
Essentially we're creating a local variable called mongoose equal to the mongoose property on the object
and that object is going to be the return result from requiring the file we just created that's in the
DV directory and it's called mongoose dot JSM we can leave off that extension.
Now that mongoose lives in its own place let's do the same thing for to do.
And user this is going to happen in a new folder in server called models inside of models.
We're going to create two files one for each model.
I'm going to make a new file called to do.
Yes.
And a new file inside of models called user Dot.
And we can take the models from here and simply copy and paste them in to their appropriate files.
Once the model is copied we can remove it from server.
Yes I'm going to do the same thing with user copying it into user J S and removing it from here.
Now I'm also going to remove everything we have so far.
All of these examples aren't necessary any more.
We can simply leave our mongoose imports statement up at the top.
Now inside of these model files there are a few things we need to do.
First up we call mongoose model.
So we still need to load in mongoose.
Now we don't have to load in the mongoose J.S. file we created it we can load in the plain old library.
Let's make a variable call that variable.
Mongoose and we're going to require Monkees and the last thing we need to do is export the model otherwise
we can't use it in files that require this one.
I'm going to set module exports equal to an object and we'll set the deed to do property equal to that
to do variable.
This is exactly what we did over in mongoose.
Jay Yes and we're going to do the exact same thing in a user.
Yes.
Inside of user J s up at the top.
We'll create a variable called the mongoose acquiring and mongoose and at the bottom will export the
user model module DOD exports setting an equal to an object where a user equals user.
Awesome.
And now all three of our files have been formatted.
We have three new files and our one old one.
The last thing I have to do is load in to do end user.
Let's make a variable using destructuring called to do setting an equal to require models forward slash
to do and we can do the exact same thing for user using ESX destructuring we're going to pull off that
user variable.
And we're getting it from the object that comes back from a call to require requiring models of board
slash user.
Excellent.
With this in place we are now ready to get going.
We have the exact same set up only it's been refactored and this is going to make it a lot easier to
test update and manage the server just as file is just going to be responsible for our routes and to
get started we're going to need to install Express.
We've already done that in the past.
So over in the terminal all we need to do is run p.m.-I followed by the module name which is express
will be using the most recent version for point fourteen point zero and we're also going to be installing
a second module and we can actually type that right after the first one there's no need to run NPM installed
twice.
This one is called The Body hyphen parser a body parser is going to let us send Jason to the server.
The server can then take that Jason and do something with it.
Body parser essentially parses the body.
It takes that string body and turns it into a javascript object.
Now body parser with an R on the end.
We're going to be installing the version 1 pt. 1 5 point to the most recent version.
I'm also going to provide the save flag which is going to add both express and body parser to the dependencies
section of packaged Jason.
Now I can go ahead and fire off this request.
Installing both modules and over inside of server.
Yes we can start configuring our app.
First up we have to load in those two modules we just installed as I mentioned to like to keep a space
between local imports and library imports right here.
I'm going to use a variable called Express to store the Express library require Express and we're going
to do the same thing for body parts for a variable called Body parser setting and equal to the return
result from requiring a body hyphen parser.
Now that we have this in place we can set up a very basic application like we did earlier in the course
we're going to make a variable called app.
This is going to store our express application.
I'm going to set this equal to a call to express nothing new here.
And we're also going to call app dot listen listening on a port.
Now we will be deploying this to Heroku eventually.
For now though we're going to have a local port Port 3000 and we'll provide a callback function that's
going to fire once the app is up and all we're going to do is use console log to print started on port
three thousand.
Excellent.
Now that we have this in place we have a very basic server.
All we have to do is start configuring our routes.
And as I promised the one we're going to be focusing on in this video is the post route.
This is going to let us create new to do's now inside of your rest API.
There's the basic crud operations crud being create read update and delete when you want to create a
resource.
You use the post HTP method and you send that resource as the body.
This means that when we want to make a new to do it we're going to send a Jasen object over to the server.
It's going to have a text property and the server is going to get that text property create the new
model and send the complete model with the id the completed property and completed at back to the client
to set up a route.
We need to call app dot post passing in the two arguments we've used for every single express route.
R U R L and R callback function that gets called with the request and response objects.
Now that you are L4 of ISAPI is really important and there is a lot of talk about the proper structure
for resources.
What I like to do is use a forward slash to do's.
This is for resource creation and this is a pretty standard set up forward slash to do.
As for creating a new to do later on when we want to read to do's we'll use the get method and we will
get from a forward slash to do's to get all to Doo's or forward slash to Doo's some crazy number to
get individual to do by its ID.
This is a very common pattern it's the one we're going to be using here.
For now though we can focus on getting body data that got sent from the client to do this.
We have to use that body parser module.
As I said body parser is going to take your Jason and convert it into an object attaching it onto this
request object.
Right here we're going to configure the middleware using app use which we used earlier inside of our
express section as we know app use takes the middle where if we're writing custom middleware it will
be a function if we're using third party middleware we usually just access something off of the library.
In this case it's going to be body parser dot Jason getting called as a function of the return value
from this Jason method is a function and that is the middleware that we need to give to express.
With this in place we can now send Jason to our express application.
What I'd like to do inside of the post callback is simply Consul a log in the value of request dot body
where the body gets store to buy body parser.
With this in place we can now start up a server and test things out inside a postman over in the terminal.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output and then I'll run the app node server server.
Dhananjay Yes the server is up on port 3000 which means now we can head into post man now inside of
post man we're not going to be making a get request like we did in the previous video and this time
what we're going to be doing is making a post request which means we need to change the HTP method to
post and type the you are Allen right here.
That's going to be localhost Kallen 3000 for the port forward slash dues.
This is that you are all that we want to send our data to.
Now in order to send some data to the application we have to go to this body tab.
We're trying to send Jason data.
So we're going to go to Raw and select Jason from the dropdown list on the right hand side.
Now we have our Hetter set.
You can see there's one letter showing up right here.
This is the Content-Type header letting the server know that Jason is getting sent all of this is done
automatically with postman inside of here.
The only piece of information I'm going to attach to my Jason is a text property.
This is from post man.
Now that we have this in place we can click send to fire off our request.
We're never going to get a response because we haven't responded to it inside of server.
Yes but if I head over to the terminal right here you see we have our data.
This is the data we created inside a post man it's now showing up in our node application which is fantastic.
We are one step closer to actually creating that to do the only thing left to do inside of the post
handler is actually create that to do using the information that comes from the user.
Let's make a variable called to do to do the thing we've done previously creating an instance of a mongoose
model.
We're going to set it equal to new to do passing in our object and passing in the values we want to
set.
In this case we just want to set text.
We're going to set text to request dot body which is the object we have here.
And then we're going to access that text property like this.
Next up we're going to call to do dot save.
This is going to actually save the model to the database.
And we are going to be providing a callback for a success case and for the error case awesome.
Now if things go well we're going to be sending back the actual to do which is going to show up right
here.
I'm going to get the document and right here inside of the callback function I'm going to use response
dot send to send the doc back.
This is going to give the user really important information things like the ID and the completed and
completed at properties which were not set by the user.
If things go poorly and we get an error that's fine too.
All we're going to do is use response send to send that error back.
Now we'll be modifying how we send errors back a little later.
For now this code is going to work just great.
We can also set an HTP status if you remember HTP statuses but you give someone some information about
how their request.
When did it go well did it go poorly all that sort of thing.
You can get a list of all the HTP statuses available to you by going to HTP statuses dot com.
Here you can view all of the statuses that you can set.
The one that set by default by Express is the 200.
This is if things went OK what we're going to be using for an error is a 400 a 400 means there was some
bad input which is going to be the case if the model can't be saved maybe the user didn't provide a
text property or maybe the text string was empty.
Either way we want to send a 400 back and that's going to happen right before we call send.
All we're going to do is call status passing in the status of 400.
With this in place we are now ready to test out our post to do's request over inside of postman.
I'm going to restart the server over inside of the terminal and you could start this up with node mine
if you like for the moment I'll be manually restarting it.
We're now up on localhost three thousand and over inside of postman we can make the exact same request
we made earlier.
I'm going to send it off.
And what do we get we get at 200.
This is fantastic it's the default status which means things went great down below the Jason response's
exactly what we expected.
We have our tax that we set.
We have the I.D. which was generated we have completed that which is set to null the default and we
have completed set to false default.
This is brilliant.
We can also test what happens when we try to create it to do it without the proper information.
For example maybe I set a text property equal to an empty string.
If I send this along we now get a 400 bad request down below.
We have a bunch of validation code saying that the to do validation failed.
Then we can go into the errors object to get the specific error.
Here we see the text field failed and the message is Path text is required.
All of this information can help someone fix their request and make a proper one.
Now if I head over into robo Mongo I'm going to refresh the collection for Dewes look at the last one
and it is indeed the one we created and Postman the text equal to.
This is from postman.
With this in place we now have our very first HTP and point set up for the to do rest API.
Now I haven't talked exactly about what rest is we're going to talk about that later.
For now we're going to focus on creating these endpoints.
The rest of version will come up a little later when we start adding authentication.
With this in place I want to give you a challenge your challenge is going to be to fire off a couple
more to do requests.
Try to set some text for at least one more to do make sure it shows up in the database as expected if
it does great.
You are done.
Take a moment to add a few to do's.
Pause the video and when you're done click play
that one should have been pretty easy over inside of post man.
We can add a few more to do's.
I'm going to add some right here.
Charge My Phone.
I don't think I've ever needed to be reminded of that one.
And we'll add take a break for lunch because it's about 12:30 and I'm starting to get pretty hungry.
Down below we see the charge my phone to do was created with a unique ID.
I'm going to send off this one.
And we see that we take a break for lunch to do was created over inside of robo mango we can give our
to do's collection a final refresh.
I'm going to expand to those last three items and they are indeed the three items we created in post
man and now that we have some meaningful work done in our project.
Let's go ahead and commit our changes.
As you can see over and atom the server directory is green meaning that it hasn't been added to get
and the package.
Jason File is orange which means that it's been modified even though it is tracking it over in the terminal.
We can shut down the server and I always like to run and get status to do a sanity check here.
Everything does look as expected.
I can then use get added to add everything followed by one more sanity check.
Here we have our four new files in the server folder as well as our package.
Does Jason File.
Now it's time to make that commit.
I'm going to create a quick commit.
I'm using the AM flag which usually adds modified files since I already used add.
I can simply use the AMA flag like we've been doing in the course and the message for this one would
be something like add post to Doo's route and refactor monkeys.
Excellent.
With the commit in place we can now wrap things up by pushing it up to get Haab making sure it's backed
up and making sure it's available for anyone else collaborating on the project.
Remember creating a committee alone does not get it up on get a job.
You've got to push that with another command.
With that in place it's now time to move on to the next video where you will be testing the route you
just created.
Stay tuned I will see you then