In this video you're going to learn how to set up the test suite for the to do API similar to what we
did in the test section and we'll be writing to test cases for forward slash to do is we're going to
verify that when we send the correct data as the body we get a 200 back with the completed doc including
the ID and if we send bad data what we expect back is a 400 with the error object.
Now before we can do any of this we do have to install all of those modules we installed in the test
section.
Expect for assertions Moka for the entire test suite.
Super tests to test our express routes and node man gnomon is going to let us create that test watch
script we had so we can automatically restart the test suite.
Now I know you have gnomon installed globally but since we are using it inside of a package Jason script
it's a great idea to install it locally as well.
We're going to run NPM II with expect version one point twenty point to the most recent.
Next up is going to be Moka the most recent version it's 3 0 2.
After that is known to man version 1 10 2 and last but not least is super test app version 2.0.
Point zero.
With this in place all we have to do is tack on that C dev flag.
We do want to save these but not as regular dependencies there for testing purposes only.
So we're going to save them as dev dependencies.
Now we can go ahead and run this command and once it's done we'll be able to start setting up the test
files inside of atom over inside of atom inside of my package database and file.
I now have it my dev dependencies list it out.
Now my output for this command might look a little different than yours.
NPM is caching some of my modules that I've installed recently.
So as you can see here it's just grabbing the local copy.
They did indeed get installed though and I can prove that by opening up the node modules directory would
this emplace we're now going to create a folder inside a server where we can store all of our test files
and this folder is going to be called tests.
And the only file We're going to worry about creating for this video is a test file for server.
Yes I'm going to make a new file in tests called Server dot test Dot.
Yes this is the extension we used in the previous section it's the extension will be using for test
files in this section as well inside of the server test file.
We can now kick things off by requiring a lot of those modules were going to require the super test
module and expect Moka and gnomon do not need to be required.
That's not how they're used.
Konst expect we'll get equal to require expect and we'll do the exact same thing for Super Test Konst
request equals require super test.
Excellent.
Now that we have these in place we do need to load in some of our local files we need to load in server.
So we have access to the Express app we need that for super test.
And we also want to load in our to do model as you'll see a little later we're going to be querying
the database and having access to this model is going to be necessary.
Now the model already exports something but server dot J s currently exports nothing.
We can fix this by adding module that exports it to the very bottom sending an equal to an object on
that object.
All we're going to do is set the app property equal to the app variable using the E.S. 6 object syntax.
With this in place we are now ready to load those two files in First up let's go ahead and create a
local variable called app and we're going to be using E.S. 60 structuring to pull it off of the return
result from requiring the server file here.
We're going to start by getting the relative path then we're going to go back one directory from tests
into server then the filename is simply server without the extension.
And we can do the exact same thing for the to do model as well.
We're going to make a constant call to do we're using as 60 structuring to pull that off of the export
and the file is from the relative path backup directory.
Then we have to go into the models directory.
And finally the file name is called to do.
And now that we have all of this loaded and we are ready to create our describe a block and add our
test cases.
I'm going to use describe to group all of the routes I'm going to have multiple test cases for some
routes and it's nice to add a describe block so you can quickly glance at the test output in the terminal
the describe block for posts to Dewes will simply be called Post forward slash to Dewes.
Then we can add our arrow function and inside of here we can start laying out our test cases.
The first task is going to verify that when we send the appropriate data everything goes as expected.
It should create a new to do.
Excellent.
Now we can add our callback function.
This function is going to take the done argument because this is going to be an asynchronous test.
You have to specify done otherwise this test is not going to work as expected in here.
What we're going to do is create a variable called text.
This is the only set of data we really need.
We just need a string and we're going to use that string throughout.
Go ahead and give this any value you like.
I'm going to use test to do text perfect.
Now it's time to start making that request via super test which we've done in the past.
Now we only made get requests previously but post requests are just as easy.
We're going to call her quest passing in the app.
We want to make the request on.
Next up we're going to call datt post which sets up a post request.
We're going to go to a forward slash to do's and the new thing is actually sending in data in order
to send data along with the request as the body.
We have to call send and we're going to pass in an object.
This object is going to get converted to Jason by super test so there's no need for us to worry about
that.
Just another great reason to use the super test library in here.
We're going to set text equal to the text variable above and we can use the E.S. 6 syntax like this
to get that done.
Now that we've sent the request we can start making assertions about the request.
First up the status I'm going to expect that the status equals 200 which should be the case when we
send across valid data.
After this we can go ahead and make an assertion about the body that comes back.
We want to make sure the body is an object and it has the text property equal to the one we specified
up above that's exactly what it should be doing when it sends the body back right here over inside of
server dot test.
Yes we can get that done by creating a custom expect assertion.
If you remember our custom expect calls do get passed the response and we can use that response inside
of the function.
We're going to expect that the response body has a text property and that text property equals using
to be the text string defined above.
If that's the case great then this will pass.
If not that's fine too.
We're just going to throw an error and the test will fail.
Now the next thing we need to do is call and to wrap things up but we're not quite done yet.
What we want to do is actually check what got stored in the Mongo DB collection.
And this is why we loaded in the model up above instead of passing done in to end like we did previously.
We're going to pass in a function.
This function will get called with an error if any and there are spots this callback function is going
to allow us to do a few things.
First up let's handle any errors that might have occurred up above.
This would be if the status wasn't 200 or if the body does not have a text property equal to the text
we sent in.
All we have to do here is check if an error exists if an error does exist.
All we're going to do is pass it into done.
This is going to wrap up the test printing the error to the screen.
So the test will indeed fail.
I'm also going to return this result.
Now returning it doesn't do anything special.
All it does is it stops the function execution.
So anything we have down below is not going to run down below.
We're going to make a request to the database fetching all the dues and verifying that are one to do
was indeed added to do that.
We have to call to do dot find now to do that fine is really similar to the Mongo D-B native find method
we used we can call it with no arguments to fetch everything in that collection.
In this case we'll be fetching all of that to Dewes.
Next up we can attach a then call back.
We're going to get this function called with all the do's and we can make some assertions about that.
In this case we're going to assert that that to do we created does exist right here.
We'll get started by expecting to Doo's ADOT length to equal to be the number one because we've added
one to do item we're going to make one more assertion.
We're going to expect that that one and only item has a text property equal using to be the text variable.
We have up above if both of these pass them we can be pretty sure that everything worked as expected.
The status code is correct if the response is correct and the database looks correct as well.
Now it's time to call.
Done wrapping up the test case.
Now we're not done quite yet.
If either of these fail the test is still going to pass but we have to do is tack on a catch call catch
is going to get any errors that might occur inside of a callback then we're going to be able to take
that error argument and using aero function.
We're going to be able to pass it into done just like this.
Notice here I'm using the Stayman syntax as opposed to the arrow function expression syntax.
With this in place our test case is now good to go.
We have a great test case and all we need to do is set up the scripts in package.
Jason to actually run it before we run the test.
We're gonna set out the scripts just like we had in the test section.
We're going to have to test which just runs the tests and we're going to have a second one test watch
which runs the test script through gnomon.
This means that any time we change our app the tests will be run right here we'll be running Moka and
the only other argument we need to provide is the globbing pattern for the test files.
We're going to fetch everything in the server directory and it could be in a subdirectory which it will
be later.
So we use two stars that could have any file name as long as it ends with the dot test.
J.S. extension now for test watch all we're going to do is run node man.
We're going to be using the X E.S. flag to specify a custom command to run inside of a single quotes
the command we're going to run.
NPM test the test script on it's own is useful and test watch simply reruns the test script every time
something changes.
Now there is still a major flaw we need to fix before we can move on.
As you notice inside of the server test file we make a really big assumption.
We assume that there's nothing already in the database.
We assume this because we expect the dues to be a length of one after adding one.
Which means that we assumed it started at zero.
Now this assumption is not going to be correct if I were to run the test suite right now it would fail.
I already have to do's in the database.
Well we're going to do is add a testing lifecycle method.
This one is called before each before each is going to let us run some code before every single test
case.
We're going to use before each to set up the database in a way that's useful for now all we're going
to do is make sure the database is empty right here.
We're going to pass in a function that function is going to get called with a Done argument.
Just like our individual test cases are.
This function is going to run before every test case and it's only going to move on to the test case
once we called done which means we can do something asynchronous inside of here.
What I'm going to do is call to do dot remove which is similar to the Mongo D-B native method.
All we need to do is pass in an empty object.
This is going to wipe all of our dues and then we can tack on and then call back and inside of the then
call back.
We're going to call done just like this.
Now we can also shorten this using the expression syntax perfect with this in place.
Our database is going to be empty before every request and now our assumption is correct we're assuming
we start with 0 to do's and we will indeed start with 0 to do's since we just deleted everything.
I'm going to go ahead and move into the terminal.
Clear the terminal output.
And now we can start running in the test suite using NPM run test hyphen watch.
This is going to start up gnomon which will start up the test suite and right here we get 1 test passing
should create a new to do.
And this is fantastic.
We can verify that everything is working as expected by tweaking some values.
I can add on one here just to prove that it actually is doing what it says it's doing.
Here you can see that we're getting an error because the two are not equal the same thing holds true
with our status.
If I change the status to something else like 201 the test suite is going to rerun and it is going to
fail.
Last but not least down below if I change this to three it's going to fail because we're always wiping
the database so the only correct value here would be 1.
Now that we have this in place we can add our second test case.
This is going to be the test case that verifies that a to do does not get created when we send bad data
to get started with this one.
We will be using it to create a brand new test case the text for this one could be something like should
not create to do with invalid body data now we can pass in our callback with the dawn argument and start
making our super test request this time around there is no need to make a text variable since we're
not going to be passing text in what we're going to be doing is passing in nothing at all.
Now this is going to be your challenge for the video.
What I'd like you to do is make a request just like we do above.
You're going to make a post request the same you are.
But instead you're going to send send as an empty object and this empty object is going to cause the
test to fail because we won't be able to save the model then you're going to expect we get a 400 which
would be the case we send a 400 back right here.
You don't need to make any assumptions about the body that comes back.
Last but not least you are going to use the same format we have here where we pass a callback to and
we check for any errors and then we make some assumptions about the database.
The assumption you're going to make is that the length of the to do's is zero.
Since this code does not create it to do no to Doo's should be there before each is going to run before
every test case.
So the to do that gets created here is going to get deleted before this case runs.
So go ahead and set that up make the request verify that the length is zero.
You don't need to have this assertion since this assertion asserts something about the array and the
array is going to be empty.
You can also leave this off since we're not going to make any assertions about the body.
When you're done save the test file.
Make sure both of your tests pass and when you're done go ahead and click play.
How'd you do that one.
Was a little open ended but hopefully you were able to get it done without too much trouble.
The first thing I'm going to do is call Everquest passing in our app we want to make another post request
so called post again and you are also going to be the same.
Now at this point we are going to be calling send but we're not going to be passing invalid data.
The whole point of this test case is to see what happens when we pass in invalid data.
What should happen is we get a 400.
So I'm going to expect that a 400 is what comes back from the server.
Now we don't need to make any assertions about the body so we can go ahead and move on to dot and where
we're going to pass an our function that gets called with the error if any and the response just like
this.
Just like we do up above.
The first thing we want to do is handle any potential errors.
If there is an error we're going to return.
Which stops the function execution and we're going to call done passing in and that error.
So the test properly fails and now we can fetch from the database and make some assertions about the
length of the to do's collection.
I'm going to use to do find to fetch every single to do inside of the collection.
Then I'll check on it then call back so I can do something with that data.
In this case I'll get the tattoos and I'm going to assert something about its length.
We're going to expect that to Doo's da length equals to be the number 0.
There should be no to do's in the database before this test case runs.
And since we're sending in bad data this test case should not create any to do.
Now we can call done and we can also tack on our catch callback which we're going to need to do.
Just like we did above.
I meant to put a little space here and we can call catch.
I'm going to call catch taking that error argument and passing it in to done.
And now we are done.
I can save the file.
This is going to restart gnomon it's going to restart our test suite and what we should see is our two
test cases.
Both of them passing over in the terminal we get just that we have two test cases for post to do's and
both are indeed passing.
And this is fantastic.
Now it took a little while to set up the basic test suite in this video but in the future as we add
more routes.
Testing is going to be much easier.
We're not going to have to set up the infrastructure up above.
We're not going to need to create the test scripts or install new modules.
This one took a little longer but the future videos will not.
The last thing to do is make a commit.
We added some meaningful code so we're going to want to save that work.
If I run get status you can see we have a few changed files as well as some on Tracht ones so I will
use GET add to add all of those to the next commit.
Now I can use get commit with the M flag to actually make the commit and a good commit message for this
one would be test post to Doo's route.
Excellent.
I'm going to make the commit.
And lastly I'll be pushing this up to get it using get push.
Now you can use get push for this particular case.
I need to go ahead and use get push force which is going to overwrite everything on get Hobb.
This is only something I need to do in this specific situation.
You should just be running get Pusch.
Now once you run that your code should get pushed up to get help and you are done.
We have two test cases for our row and it's time to move on to add a new route.
The extra hour is going to be a get request to fetch all dues.
I'm super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.