With our test suite in place it's now time to create our second route and we get to do's route which
will be responsible for returning all of your to do's and this would be useful for any to do application.
The first screen you're probably going to show a user is a list of all of their to do's and this is
the route you would use to get that information.
It's going to be a GET request.
So I'm going to use app ADOT get to register the route handler and the URL itself is going to match
the you are else we have above.
It's going to be get a forward slash to do's because we want to get all of that to do.
Later on when we get an individual to do the u r l will look something like this.
But for now we're going to match it with the post you are out.
Next up we can add our call back.
This is going to give us our request and response objects and inside of here we can get started.
All we need to do is get all of the dues in the collection and we actually already did that in the test
file inside of server test.
Yes.
We used to do find it to fetch all of the dues we're going to use that same technique right here to
do and find we're not passing in a query.
We want to return everything later on when we add authentication.
You'll get back just to do as you created.
But for now without authentication you're going to get everything in the to do's collection back.
Next up we're going to attach a then call this then call is going to take two functions and the success
Case function when the promise gets resolved and a function that gets fired when the promise gets rejected.
Now the success case will get called with all of the dues and all we're going to do is send that information
back using response Dot said we could pass in the array like this but this is not the best way to get
the job done.
When you pass back an array you're kind of locking yourself down if you want to add on another property
whether it's a custom status code or some other data.
You can't because you have an array.
The better solution would be to create an object and on that object specify to do's sending an equal
to the to use array.
Using ESX this would let you add other properties later on.
For example I could add some sort of custom status code setting an equal to whatever I like by using
an object as opposed to sending an array back.
We're opening ourselves up to a more flexible future.
With this in place our success case is good to go.
The only thing we need to do to wrap this one up is handle errors and the error handler is going to
look exactly like the one we have above response dot status.
We're going to be sending back a 400 and we'll be sending back the error object that got passed in to
the function.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and start up our server and test things out over inside
of postman.
I'm going to fire up the server using node server server data as an inside of post man.
We can get started by creating some to do's.
Currently our application and the tasks for the application use the same database to before each call
we were on in the last video unfortunately wiped everything which means we have no data to fetch.
The first thing I'm going to do in post man is try to fetch the data.
We should get back an empty array which should still work.
The U R L is going to be a localhost 3000.
Forward slash to do's.
And it is indeed going to be a GET request.
I can click send.
This is going to fire off the request and right here we get our data back.
We have an object.
We have our dues property and we have our empty array which is expected.
Now as you've noticed manually configuring a route every single time you want to use it gets pretty
tedious.
And we're going to be using a lot of the same routes over and over again with post man and we can actually
create a collection of routes so we can refire requests without having to manually enter all this information
over on the right hand side.
I can click the drop down arrow next to save and click save as.
Here I can give my request a little bit of detail.
I'm going to change the request name to get forward slash to do's and this is the naming convention.
I like to use the HTP method followed by the R-AL we can leave the description blank for now.
And the Double-O we can create a new collection since we don't have any.
The post man Ecko collection is an example collection post man gives you to explore this feature.
We're going to make one called to do app now any time we want to run that command all we do is we go
to collections we click get to do's we click send and the request fires.
Let's go ahead and set up a post request to create it to do.
And then we'll run that we'll save it and we'll rerun get to make sure it returns the newly created
to do to create the post request.
If you remember we do have to change the method to post and then you are Al will be the same local host
three thousand four slashed to dues.
Now in order for this request to succeed we also have to pass along a body.
This one is going to be a raw.
Jason abody right here we can specify the data we'd like to send.
In this case the only data property we're going to send is text and I'll set this to something to do
from postman.
Now we can go ahead and fire this off.
And below we get our newly created to do with a 200 status code which means everything went well.
We can save this to our collection so we can easily rerun this one later on in a change the request
name to post forward slash to Doo's following that same syntax then down below I can select an existing
collection need to do app collection and save it.
Now I can simply click the request use command enter or click the send button to fire off the request
and down below I get my dues array and everything looks great.
I can always click post out a second one.
I can tweak it if I like adding the number two then I can use command return to fire that one off I
can rerun the get request and I have my two Dewes in the database with this employees are get request
is now complete.
We also set up our collection and post man making it really easy to fire off any of these HTP requests
much faster.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap this video up by making a commit over in the terminal.
I'm going to shut the server down and run get status and this time around you see we just have one file
and it is modified which means instead of using GET add we can simply use get commit with the flag.
The flag adds all modified files to the next commit.
It does not work for new untracked files but modified files are perfectly fine.
And then I can tack on the flag to specify my commit message a good one for this will be ad get to do's
route.
Excellent last up.
We're going to push it up to get help.
And now we are done.
I will see you in the next video where we write test cases for get to do.
It's coming up next.
So stay tuned and we'll see you then.