With are get to do is route now in place.
It is time to add a test case for it and a missing semicolon which I left off right here.
That's not going to cause the program to crash but it is a good idea.
Now before we can actually write the test case we have to deal with a different problem.
The first thing we do inside of our test file is delete all the to do's and this happens before every
single test.
Now they get to Doo's route pretty much lives off the fact that there is to do it can return it will
handle not to do it but for our test case we do want some data in that database in order to add this
data.
Well we're going to do is modify before each adding some seed data.
This means that our database is still going to be predictable.
It's always going to look exactly the same when it starts but it will have some items in it.
Now in order to do that the first thing we're going to do is make up an array of dummy to do's.
Now these to do is only need the text properties since everything else is going to get populated by
mongoose right here.
I can create a constant call that to do setting an equal to an array.
And we're going to have an array of objects where each object has a text property.
For example this one could have a text of first test to do that I can add on a second object as the
second item in the array with a text property equal to second test to do.
Excellent.
Now before we can actually write the test case we do have to modify before each using a brand new mongoose
method called insert many which takes an array like the one we have here and it inserts all of those
documents into the collection.
This means that we are going to need to tweak the code real quick instead of having a simple arrow function
that calls done.
I'm going to tack on some curly braces and inside of the callback function we're going to call to do
dot insert many and we're going to call insert many with the array we defined above.
This is going to insert all of that to do as in the array are two to do's and then we can do something
like calling.
Done.
I'm going to return the response.
This is going to a lot of chain callbacks and then I can tack on then and I can use a really simple
expression based arrow function.
All I'm going to do right here is call done using that expression syntax.
Now let's go ahead and run the test suite and I'll warn you the other tests are going to have problems
because of the numbers that they assert are now going to be incorrect over in the terminal I'm the start
of the test suite NPM run test watch.
And once that test suite gets started I'm going to move back into Adam and you can see as promised both
of the test cases failed.
We expected three to be one and we expected two to be zero.
Everything is now off by two to fix this.
We're going to use two different techniques for the first test.
What we're going to do is only find Dewes where the text equals the text we have above.
This means that the resulting length is still going to be won and the first item should still have a
Text property equal to the text above.
For the second test we're going to leave the fine call the way it is.
Instead we're going to make sure that the length of the database is to there should only be two documents
in the dues collection because that's all we added up above.
And this was testing a failure so a third one should not have been added.
With this in place you can see are two test cases are now passing.
So we're ready to move on adding a new.
Describe a block down below right here.
I'm going to add a describe block.
We're going to describe the get to Doo's route passing in our aero function and then we can add our
single test case.
It should it get all to do.
Now in this case all to do's refers to the two to do as we just added up above.
I'm going to pass in an Aero function with the Done argument and we are good to go.
All we have to do is start the super test request.
I'm going to request something on the Express application.
It's going to be a GET request.
So we'll call and get passing in the U R L forward slash to do is with this in place we're not ready
to make our assertions we're not sending any data in the request body but we are going to make some
assertions about what comes back.
We're going to expect that a 200 comes back and we're also going to create a custom assertion expecting
something about the body here will provide our callback function with the response and we're going to
expect that response dot body dot to do's has a length of two to be two.
Now that we had this in place oh we have to do is tack on an end call like we did in the previous section
and past done in as the argument.
There is no need to provide a function to end like we do up above because we're not doing anything a
synchronous with this in place.
We are now good to go.
We can save the server test file.
This is going to rerun the test suite using node mount and we should see our new test and it should
be passing.
If it is we're done and right here we get just that we have our section for post to dues both of those
tests are passing and we have our section for get to choose and the one test is indeed passing.
Now if I change the status to 201 the test is going to fail because that's not the status that came
back.
If I change the length to three it's going to fail because we only added two Dewes in as the seed data.
Now that we're done.
Let's go ahead and make a commit saving this code.
I'm going to shut down the test watch script run and get status and right here we have two modified
files which means I can use get commit with the flag and the flag.
Remember the a flag adds modified files to the next commit a good message for this commit is going to
be add tests for get forward slash to do's.
I'm going to make the commit.
Push it up to get a job.
And we are done with this in place we are ready to move on adding a brand new route that is coming up
next I am super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then