In this video you're going to learn a few alternative ways that you can use mongoose to query your data.
Now inside of the server test file we already looked at one way to do dot find.
We're going to look at two more and then we're also going to explore how to validate object IDs in order
to do all of this we are going to make a new file in the playground folder.
I'm going to call this one mongoose hyphen queries.
Jay Yes and the first thing we need to do is load in the mongoose file here and we need to do file here.
I'm going to use 60 structuring like we've used for all files where this happens and then we can require
in the local file using the relative path we need to go up a directory out of playground into server
into D-B.
And finally the file name we're looking for is called mongoose.
We can do the same thing for to do.
We're going to make that constant to do from the require return results and the file here is going to
follow the same path.
We need to go back a directory and into server but instead of going into D-B we'll go into models then
we'll get the file to do.
Now before we can actually do any querying we are going to grab an idea for one of our existing to do's
over in Rabo Mongo in the to do app database.
I'm going to explore all of our documents and I'll just grab the first one.
All right click to edit it.
Then I can grab the ID excluding the quotes parentheses and the object id identifier with this ID in
the Clipboard back inside of Adam.
I can make a variable called ID and set it equal to the idea just copied inside a single quotes.
And now we have an idea and we can use this for all of our queries.
Now I understand you've already used to do fine before but we are going to talk about a few other things.
So for the moment we will be starting with that to do not find.
It lets you query as many to do's as you like.
You can pass no arguments to get all your to do it back or you can query by anything right here.
We're going to query by ID now.
Mongoose is fantastic.
It doesn't require you to pass in object IDs.
It can actually do that for you.
In this case what we have is perfectly valid.
We pass in a string as the value Mongoose is going to take that string it's going to convert it to an
object id and then it's going to run the query.
This means we don't need to manually convert our string into an object ID.
Now after we make the query we can attach a a then call back.
We're going to get all of our to do's will name that argument right here and we can go ahead and print
them to the screen console dialog.
To Duse.
And the second argument will be the actual do's array.
Nothing new here aside from the fact that you can indeed pass in an ID as a string.
The next method we're going to look at is one called to do dot find one now to do not find one is very
similar to find the only difference is that it returns 1 document at most.
And that means it simply grabs the first one that matches the queery you have now in our case we're
querying by a unique ID.
So it's only going to find a one matching item.
But if there were other results for example if we queried all to do with completed false the first doc
would be the only one that returns even though there's two that match the query.
What we can do to call Find one is identical to what we did with find and to prove it.
I'm actually going to copy the code I'm not even going to rewrite it.
All we need to do is change a few things instead of to do's.
We get to do.
We're just going to get a single document not an array of documents.
That means I can print a to do string followed by I need to do variable with this in place.
We now have enough examples where it makes sense to run the file and see exactly what happens over inside
of the terminal.
I'm going to kick things off by running this file and I'll run it through gnomon gnomon playground forward
slash mongoose queries Dhananjay as when I run the file what do we get.
We get our to use array our array of one document and we get our to do object.
If you know you're just trying to fetch one individual item I recommend using find one over find you
get back the document as opposed to an array.
This also makes it a lot easier when the ID of the to do you're looking for doesn't exist.
Instead of getting an empty array as the result you'll get null back and you can work with that doing
whatever you like.
Maybe that means you return a 404 or maybe you want to do something else if the ID is not found.
The last method we're going to look at is to do
dot find by ID now find by ID is fantastic if you are just looking for a document by its identifier.
There is no way to query by anything else other than the ID and all you do is you pass in the ID as
the argument.
You dont have to make a query object and you dont have to set an underscore ID Propp with this in place.
We can now do the exact same thing we did with find one I'm going to prove that by taking the then call
pasting it right here and just changing this from to do two to do by de.
Now if I save the file gnomon is going to rerun and what do we get.
We get the exact same result for both.
If you want to find one document by something other than ID I'd recommend using find one if you want
to find one documented by ID.
I always recommend using find by ID.
Now all of this and more is available on the docks.
So if you want to dive into anything I discussed here you can always go to mongoose J.S. dot com.
Click on the Read the docs link and over on the left hand side.
They have a couple links.
The one that we're looking for is the one on queries right here.
You can learn more about how to query your docs but we pretty much covered everything this page talks
about.
Now the next thing I want to talk about is what happens when the ID isn't correct and this is going
to be the case because remember our API is going to be getting this idea from the user which means that
if the ID isn't correct we don't want our code to fail.
We want to elegantly handle these errors to prove this.
I'm going to go ahead and tweak the idea a little bit.
IDS do have specific protocols.
So what I want you to do for this example is find a number in your ID.
I'm going to go with the first character because it happens to be a number and just increment it by
one.
I'm going to go from five to six.
Now we have a valid ID but the ID is not going to be in the database because I tweaked it and obviously
the other to do in the database does not match this ID.
Now with this in place you can see as we restart the server we get an empty array for the Find call
and we get null for both find one and find a by ID when your ID does not match anything in the database.
An error is not going to get thrown.
It's still going to fire the success case.
It's just going to fire it either with an empty array or with NULL which means when we want to handle
that case where the ID doesn't exist in the database all we have to do is add an if statement right
here.
I can add an if statement if there is no to do.
We're going to do something and that something is going to be to use return which prevents the rest
of the function from executing and we'll print a little message console log Id not found us.
Now if I save the file and the last call should look a little different right here instead of getting
to do with no we get ID not found.
And this is perfect.
Now we know how to query using Find one and find by ID.
And we also know how to handle situations where the ID you're querying for doesn't actually exist inside
of the collection.
I'm going to set the ID back to its original value changing the 6 to 5 and if I saved the file No-Man's
going to restart.
And we're going to get our document back.
Now the last thing I want to talk about is how to validate an object ID.
What we've done so far is we've created a valid object ID.
It's just of a value that is not in the collection.
But if we were to do something like tack on to ones we would actually have an invalid ID which is going
to cause errors in the program.
Now you might think why would this ever happen.
But it could happen because the user is the one specifying the ID double L.
We're going to add a catch call on to find Abidi.
We're going to get that error and simply printed to the screen using console dot lock.
Now to illustrate this we don't need all three queries in order to clean up the terminal output.
I'm going to go ahead and comment out find and find one with this emplace are invalid ID.
And the catch callback we can save the file.
And over in the terminal we should get a really long error message.
Here we go.
We have an error message cast error cast to object id failed for the following value.
This is warning you that your object id doesn't not just exist in the collection it's actually completely
invalid now running in this with a catch method.
It does let us handle the error.
We could do something here like tell the user hey the ID that you sent through is invalid.
But there's also another way to get it done that I prefer.
What we're going to do is load in the object id off of the Mongo D-B native driver and that's something
we did before right here in Mongo DB connect.
We loaded it in object ID inside of mongoose queries we're going to do the same thing.
I'm going to make a constant called object ID.
And we're going to get it from the Mongo DB library.
Now on object idea we have a lot of utility methods we've looked at how we can create new object IDs.
But one thing we also have access to is a method called object ID.
Dot is a valid is valid takes the value.
In this case it's our string right here and it returns true if it's valid and false.
If it's not valid which means we can add if conditions to validate the ID before we ever run the query
in order to do this we're going to add an if statement and we're going to check if the value is not
valid.
I'm going to flip it using exclamation mark and then we can call object ID is valid by flipping it.
We've essentially created a method that tests whether an object ID is not about the value.
I'm going to pass in is just going to be the string up above.
And now we can add some code to run when the ID is not valid.
Consul
dialog Id not about.
Now if I go ahead and save the file we should get our id not an invalid message.
And then after that we should get our error message printing to the terminal because we do still have
our catch call and this query is still going to run.
Over here we get just that Id not valid prints to the screen.
But now we know how to validate IDs and that's going to come in handy in the next video.
With this in place it's now time for a challenge before I set up the challenge and comment out the ID
and our is valid call.
And down below I'll comment out fine by ID.
I'm going to leave them here and you can use them as a reference for what to do in the challenge.
Your challenge is going to be to query the users collection.
That means that you're going to want to go ahead and move into Roboam mango and grab an ID from your
users collection.
Here I have just one document if you have 0 documents for whatever reason you can always right click
insert a document and all you have to do is specify the email.
Now in order to make that query over inside an atom you are going to need to load in the user mongoose
model because currently we only have that to do on a required down below.
I want you to use user ADOT find by ID to query the ID that you picked over in Roble Mongo then you're
going to go ahead and handle the three cases.
There's going to be the case where the query works like we have here but there is no user in that case
you're going to print something like user not found.
You're also going to handle the case where the user was found.
I want you to go ahead and print the user to the screen.
And finally you're going to handle any errors that might have occurred.
You can simply print the error object to the screen.
For that there's no need to use is valid for this one.
All you have to do is fill out the find by id call when you're done.
Go ahead and test it.
Save the file make sure that the user shows up.
Then tweak the ID making sure your other cases work as well.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play and you do.
Hopefully you are able to get that done using the find by id method.
Now the first thing I'm going to do is import the user file.
I'm going to make a constant.
I'm going to grab the user variable off of the return result from a choir and we're going to follow
the same path we have here.
We have to go out of the playground directory into the server model's directory.
And finally the file name is user now that we have user imported we can query it down below.
Before I write the query I am going to fetch an ID over in Roboam mango.
I have one right here.
I can edit the document highlight it copy it and move back into Atam inside of Adam.
I'm going to set up my user find by id call all I have to do is pass in the ID I have that in the Clipboard
I'm going to wrap it in quotes.
Excellent.
Next up the callbacks.
I'm going to attach a then call back passing in two functions.
The first one is when the promise gets resolved and the second one is when the promise gets rejected
for rejections.
Oh we're going to do is print that error.
Object to the screen which means we can use console dialog.
Now if things go well there are still a few exceptions we want to make sure that the user actually does
exist.
The query is still going to pass if the ID doesn't match anything found inside of the collection.
If there is no user we are going to stop function execution using return.
Then we're going to go ahead and print using console dot log unable to find user.
Now the last case we need to handle is if things actually go well which means that the query was indeed
valid and the I.D. was found inside of the user's collection right here.
I'm going to console log using our pretty printing technique the user variable.
Jason docstring a by passing in our three arguments user undefined and the number two with this in place.
I can now go ahead and save the file and open up the terminal since it's currently hidden.
And what do we get.
We get our user showing up in the terminal.
This is fantastic if you're seeing this you successfully completed the challenge.
Now I can also test that my other cases are working as expected.
I'm going to change this.
6 at the end of my ID to a 7 save the file.
And when it restarts I get unable to find user which is expected.
Next up I'm going to change it back to basics but I am going to tack on a few ones or any other characters
in this case I'll use two ones and two a characters.
This time we do get our error.
We're unable to cast that value to an object.
I d.
Well let's undo the change to the ID and now we're done.
I'm going to wrap this video up by committing our changes.
I'm going to shut down gnomon run and get status.
And we have one new file I can use and get add to add it to the next commit and then I can use it get
commit to make the commit message for this one is add queries playground file.
Awesome.
With this in place I'm going to push it up to get help.
And we are done.
I will see you next time where you will be responsible for creating an entire API request.
This one is going to be a challenge.
I am super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.