This video was for OS X and Linux users if you are on Windows I have created a separate video is the
next one and that is your installation video.
If you're still watching I am going to assume that you're on either Linux or OSX the commands we go
through in this video will not work otherwise.
The first thing we're going to do is download and set up Mongo DB Mongo D-B is going to be the database
we use we'll be using a third party service to host our database when we eventually deploy it to Heroku.
But on our local machine we're going to need to download Mongo D-B so we can start up a database server.
This is going to let us connect to it via our node applications to read and write data in order to grab
the database.
We're going to head over to a Mangu IDB dot com.
Then we can go to the download page and we can download the appropriate version.
If you scroll down you do want to select the community server and this is the one we'll be using.
And then there are options for different operating systems whether it's Windows Linux OS X or Solaris
I'm on OS X.
I'm going to use this download.
If you're on Linux click Linux then go to the version dropdown and select the appropriate version.
For example if you're on a boot to fourteen point zero 4 you can download the one right here.
Then you'd simply click the download button and follow along.
I'm on OSX so I'm going to download that installer right here.
The installer is a little big it's about 80 megabytes.
It's not actually an installer it's the executables to start up the database server.
So take a moment to pause the video wait for your Mongo download to finish and when it's done you go
ahead and click play my download is complete so I can go ahead and open it up which is going to extract
the directory.
Creating a brand new folder in my downloads directory if you're on Linux you might need to manually
extract the contents of that archive in to the downloads directory.
Now this folder contains a bin folder and in there we have all of the executables that we need in order
to do things like connect to the database and start a database server before we go ahead and run any
of them.
What we're going to do is rename this directory to a mongo and then I'm going to take it and move it
into my user directory which I have a shortcut to right here.
I'm going to go ahead and drag it there and now in the user directory I have the Mongo folder.
We're also going to create a brand new directory alongside of Mongo called Mongo hyphen data.
This is going to store the actual data inside of the database.
So when we insert a new record into the to do's table for example that is going to live right here.
Once you have the mango folder moved into the user directory and you have the new Mongo data folder
you are ready to actually run the database server from the terminal.
I'm going to go into the terminal and navigate into that brand new Mongo folder that is in the user
directory where I currently am so I can CD into Mongo.
Then I'm going to CD into the bin directory by attacking it on right there from here.
We have a bunch of executables that we could run.
We have things like bison dump Mongo dump what we're going to focus on in this video is to Mongo D which
is going to start up the database server and Mongo which is going to let us connect it to the server
and run some commands.
Kind of like when we type Noad we can run some javascript commands right here in the terminal when we
type Mongo will be able to run some Mongo commands to insert Thach or do anything we like with the data.
First up though at startup the database server.
I'm going to use a dot forward slash to run a file in the current directory.
The one we're going to run is called Mongo D and we do need to provide one argument.
The DBI path argument it divi path is going to get set equal to the path of the Directory we just created
the Mongo data directory.
I'm going to use the taled up to navigate to the user directory then forward slash Mongo hyphen data
just like this.
When I run this command it's going to start up the server.
This is going to create an active connection that we can connect to to start manipulating our data.
The last line you see when you run that command should be waiting for connections on port 2 7 0 1 7.
If you see this then your server is up and running.
Next up let's open up a new tab.
I'm going to open up a tab which starts in the exact same directory and this time around instead of
running Mongo D.
We're going to run the Mongo file when we run Monga we open up a console it connects to the database
server we just started and from here we can start running some commands.
These commands are just going to be to test that things are working as expected will be going over all
of this in detail in this section.
For now though we can access D-B dot to do's.
Then we're going to call ADOT insert to create a brand new to do record.
I'm going to go ahead and call it like a function.
Go ahead and do the same and inside of insert.
We're going to pass in our document.
This is going to be the Mongo DB document we want to create.
For now we're going to keep things really simple on our object.
We're going to specify one attribute text sending an equal to after that call in a string inside of
quotes.
Go ahead and type anything you want to do.
I'm going to say film new node.
Of course with your command looking just like this you can go ahead and hit enter and what you should
get back is a right result within an inserted which is short for a number inserted a value set to 1.
This means that one new record was created and that is fantastic.
Now we've inserted a record.
Let's go ahead and fetch the record just to make sure everything worked as expected.
DB daat to Dewes.
Now instead of calling insert we're going to call find and we're going to call fine without any arguments.
We want to return every single item in the to do's collection.
When I run this what do we get we get one object looking thing back.
We have our text set to the text that we provided and we have an underscore id property.
This is the unique identifier for each record and we'll talk about that later.
As long as you're seeing the TX property coming back to what you said then you are good to go.
We can go ahead and shut down the Mongo command know we are still going to leave the Mongo command running
because there's one more thing I want to install.
It's called robo mango and it's a graphic user interface for managing your Mongo database.
This is going to be really useful as you start playing around with mango.
You'll be able to view the exact data saved in the database.
You can manipulate it and do all sorts of stuff over in the Finder.
We have our Mongo data directory and you can see there's a ton of stuff in here.
This means that our data was successfully saved all of the data is sitting in and this Mongo data directory
to download and install robo Monga which is available for Linux Windows and Mac.
We're going to head over to robo Mongo and dot org and grab the installer for our operating system.
We can click download and download at the most recent version.
Now it should automatically detect your OS.
Go ahead and download the installer for either Linux or Mac.
The Mac one is really simple it's one of those installers where you take the icon and you drag it into
the applications folder for Linux.
You're going to need to extract the archive and run the program in the bin directory that is going to
start up robo Manjo on your Linux distribution.
In the case of OSX I'm just going to quickly take the icon drag it over to applications and then we
can play around with the program itself.
Perfect.
Now I'm going to go ahead and open it up inside of the finder.
And when you first open up robo Mongo you might get a warning like this on OSX since it's a program
that we downloaded and it's not from an identified OSX developer.
This is fine.
Most programs you download from the web are not going to be official since they did not come from the
App Store.
You can right click click open and then click open again to run that program.
When you first open it you're going to see some screens like this.
We have a little screen in the background and we have a list of connections and currently that list
is empty.
What we need to do is create a connection for our local Mongo DB database so we can connect to it and
manipulate that data.
Right here we have create.
I'm going to go ahead and click that.
And the only thing we're going to need to update is the name.
I'm going to give it a more descriptive name like local Mongo database the address local host and the
port 2 7 0 1 7 are correct.
There's no need to change those.
I'm going to click save and then I'm going to double click the database to connect to it now.
Over inside of the tiny window we have our database we are connected to it and we can do all sorts of
things to manage it.
We can go ahead and open up the test database and in there we should see one collection.
If we open up that we have our dues collection and from here we can go ahead and right click the collection
click view documents and we should get our one to do item.
The one that we created over inside of the Mongo con..
I can expand it to view the text property film New Noad course shows up right here if you're seeing
this.
Then you are done in this video you downloaded and ran and the Mongo D-B a database server.
This means we have a local database server we can connect to from our node application which is coming
up really soon.
We also installed robo Mongo robo Mongo lets us connected to our local database so we can view and manipulate
data.
This comes in handy when you're debugging data managing data or doing anything else with your Mongo
database will be using it throughout the course and you'll start to see why it's valuable.
Just a little bit later.
For now though you are all set up you are ready to continue on and start building the to do API.
I'll see you next time.
But remember the next video is for Windows users so go ahead and skip a video and then we'll get started