In this video you are going to create an API route for fetching an individual to do.
Now most of this video is going to be a challenge but there is one thing I want to show you before we
get started.
And that is how to fetch a variable that's passed in via the you are out.
Now as I mentioned the structure for this you are out is going to be a GET request to forward slash
to dues.
Then we're going to dive into the dues fetching an individual item where the idea gets passed like this.
This means that we need to make this part of the you are dynamic.
I want to be able to fetch that value wherever a user happens to pass in and use it to make the query
the query that we set up in mongoose queries like this one to fetch the do by ID.
Now in order to get that done let's go ahead and call and get passing in.
If you are out the first part we already know forward slash to Doo's forward slash.
But now what we need is a u r l parameter u r l parameters.
Follow this pattern.
It's a colon followed by a name.
Now I could call this to do ID or anything else but we're going to call it for this section is colon
ID.
This is going to create an ID variable.
It's going to be on the request object.
The one will set up in just a moment and we'll be able to access that variable.
That means when someone makes this request and this callback will fire the one we're going to specify
now and we'll be able to query by that ID they pass and now we are still going to get the request and
response object.
The only difference is we're now going to be using something off of a request.
This one is request dot Puranas request pro-ams is going to be an object it's going to have key value
pairs where the key is the R parameter like ID and the value is whatever value was actually put here
in order to demonstrate this.
I am going to simply call response send sending back the request harams object.
This is going to let us test out this route inside of postman and see exactly how it works over inside
of the terminal I can start up our server.
I'm going to use node on server forward slash server just to start things up.
Now the servers on localhost three thousand and we can make a get request to this.
You are out over inside of post man.
I'm going to do just that.
We have the get method that you are Al is a local host and it's still on port three thousand.
Forward slash to Doo's forward slash.
And then we can type whatever we like.
For example one two three.
Now when I send this off when we get back is that request Paramo object and right here you can see it
has an ID property set to 1 2 3.
That means we are able to access the value here using request Dopp harams dot ID and that is exactly
what you're going to need to do for the challenge.
Over inside of Adam I'll start things off by creating that variable a VAR Id set equal to request dot
harams dot ID with this in place you now know everything you need in order to complete the challenge
which is going to be to finish filling out this route.
First up youre going to validate the idea using that object ID is a valid method that we explored over
in the mongooses queries file up above I'll leave a little comment here.
Validate ID using is Vout.
Now if it's not valid what you're going to do is stop the function execution and you're going to respond
with a 4.
0 4 because the ID passed in is not valid there's no way it's ever going to be in the collection.
We're going to respond with a or for letting the user know that the to do was not found.
And you can send back an empty body which means you can just call send without passing in any value.
It would be similar to this statement with no error here and you would also change this from a 400 to
a 404.
Now after that you're going to start querying the database.
And this is going to happen using find by ID.
I want you to take this idea and query that to do collection looking for a matching document.
And there's two ways this could go.
There's the success case and there is the error case.
If we get an error that one is pretty self-explanatory all we're going to do is send back a 400 letting
the user know that the request was not valid.
And we're also going to go ahead and send back nothing.
We're not going to be sending back that error argument because the error that prints for this error
message it could contain private information.
Now we're going to be beefing out our air handling later currently.
As you can see we have the function duplicated in quite a few places that will get moved into one location
later.
But for now you can respond with a 400 and send empty body back.
This brings us to the success case.
Now if there is a to do if to do you're going to go ahead and send it back if there is no to do it no
to do this means the call did succeed.
But the idea was not found in the collection.
All you're going to do is go ahead and send back a 4 or 4 with an empty body.
Now both of these statements are going to look really similar.
You're sending back a 404 or letting the user know that the ID they passed in does not match any ID
of a document in the to do's collection.
Now you know how to do all of this.
You can use anything you need to get this done.
That means you can use the mongoose queries file.
You can use the mongoose Jay ask.com and documentation.
You can use stack overflow Google or anything else.
It's not about memorizing exactly how to get stuff done.
It's about working through those problems on your own.
Eventually you will memorize a lot of these techniques as they come up again and again.
But for now your goal is to just get it working when you're done.
Go ahead and fire off this request.
Over in the postman application that means you're going to want to grab an ID that is valid from robo
Mongo and paste it right here.
You can also test what happens with IDs that are valid but don't exist in the database and IDs that
are invalid like one two three which is not a valid object id or this place you are ready to start the
challenge.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Fill this out.
Test it.
Make sure it works.
And when you're done go ahead and click play.
How'd you do on this one.
This was by far the biggest challenge I've given you but that's the goal.
The goal is to start giving you more work to do on your own because that's where the real learning happens.
Now the first thing I'm going to do is fill out the code for these comments right here.
We're going to validate the idea and we're going to send back a 404.
If it's not valid now up at the very top of the file I do not have object id imported.
I'm going to have to go ahead and do that just below body parser.
I can create a variable object id uppercase I uppercase D and set that equal to the return result from
require.
And we're requiring the Mongo NDB library now that we have object idea in place we can go ahead and
use it down below.
Right here we'll write an IF statement if object id dot is valid.
Now obviously we only want to run this code if it's not valid it's going to flip the return result using
an exclamation mark and then I'm going to pass the ID in.
Now we have an IF condition that's only going to pass if the ID the one that got passed in as a D u
r l parameter was not valid in that case.
We're going to use return to prevent function execution.
Then I'm going to go ahead and respond using response dot status setting an equal to a 4 0 4 and I'm
going to call send with no arguments so I can send back an empty body.
And there we go.
Our first thing is complete with this in place we can now go ahead and move down below creating the
query.
At this point we actually do have something we can test we can pass in invalid IDs and make sure we
get that 404 back over inside of the terminal.
I ran the application using no demands.
It automatically restarted in post man.
I can rerun this request and right here we get our 404 which is fantastic.
This is not a valid object ID.
The condition failed and the 404 was indeed returned.
Next up we're going to make that query to do a dot find by ID here.
We're going to pass in the ID which we have in the ID variable.
And then we're going to attach our success and error handlers then passing in our success call back.
This is going to get called potentially with the individual to do document and I am going to call catch
as well getting the error and we can do the air handler first if there is an error.
We're going to keep things really simple response dot status setting an equal to a 400 then we're going
to go ahead and call send leaving out the error object intentionally with this in place.
The only thing left to do is fill out the success handler.
Now the first thing we need to do is make sure that it to do is actually found this query if successful
might not always result in an actual document being returned.
Right here I'm going to use an IF statement to check if there is no to do if there is no to do we want
to respond with a 404 just like we did up above.
We're going to return to stop the function execution response dot status.
The status here will be 404 and we will be using send to respond with no data.
Perfect.
Now that we have this case in place the last case is the happy path the success case when everything
goes as planned.
The idea is valid and we find a document in the dues collection that has an I.D. matching the I.D. passed
in in that case.
All we're going to do is respond using response and send sending back that to do.
Now you could have sent it in like this.
This will indeed work.
But what I want to do is tweak it just a little bit instead of sending back to do as the body.
I'm going to send back an object where the two do is attached as the to do property using the six object
definition which is identical to this.
This gives me a little flexibility down the line.
I could always add other properties onto the response like custom status codes or anything else.
It's similar to the technique we used up above for get to Dewes right here instead of responding with
the array.
We responded with an object that has to do is property and that is the array.
Now that we have this in place we are done and we can test things out.
I'm going to save the file remove all of our comments at a semi-colon where needed.
And we're going to grab an I.D. from Roboam Mongo over inside of robo Mongo.
I can grab an ID for one of my to do.
I'm going to go with the second one.
I'll edit the document and copy it to the clipboard.
Now over in post man we can go ahead and make the request.
Setting the ID equal to the ID value we just copied.
I'm going to send it off and what do we get.
We get our object where we have it to do property.
And on that to do property we have all of the properties for the document ID text completed at and completed.
Now the last case I want to test is what happens when we request a to do with a valid object id but
one that just happens to not exist.
I'm going to do this by taking the last number in my ID and replacing it from 9 to zero if I send this
off.
We get our 404 which is fantastic.
This is exactly what I expect to happen when I make a request for it to do the object ID is valid.
It's just not in the collection now that we've made this request we can actually save this inside of
our to do app collection.
So later down the line it's a lot easier to fire off this one I'm going to save it using Save As we
can leave the description empty and we can change the name to get forward slash to Dewes forward slash
colon ID.
And I am going to add it to our existing collection.
Need to do app collection.
Now we have three routes.
The only thing left to do for this route is to add some test cases and that's going to be the topic
of the next video to wrap this one up.
Let's commit our changes and push them up to get up.
I'm going to shut down the server and run and get status.
Here we see we have our modified file.
This means I can run and get commit with the a flag and the flag and then I'm going to provide a my
commit message.
Now if you're using a flag and the flag you can actually use a shortcut the AM flag which does the exact
same thing.
It's going out all of our modified files to the commit.
It's also going to give us a place to add a message a good message for this one would be ADD get to
do's ID.
Excellent.
With this in place I'm going to make the commit.
Push it up to get help.
And we are done.
I will see you next time where we are going to go ahead and write test cases for this route.
It's going to be mostly a challenge like this one was.
So get ready for it.
Stay tuned.
I will see you them