In this video we're going to create three test cases for this route.
The one that fetches an individual to do Item one is going to make sure that when we pass in an invalid
object id we get a for a for another one is going to verify that when we pass in a valid object id but
it doesn't match a doc.
We get a 404 back.
And lastly we'll write a test case that makes sure when we pass in an object ID that does match a doc
that Doc actually comes back in the response body we're going to write the test case for the valid call
together.
Then you'll be writing these two test cases on your own that will be the challenge for this video over
inside of server test.
Yes we can get started down at the very bottom by adding a describe block right here.
I'm going to call the scrub and this describe block will be named get forward slash to Doo's a forward
slash colon ID and we can at our aero function as the callback function inside of our describe call
back.
We can now set up the test case that we're going to create together.
It should return to do doc.
This is going to be the test that makes sure when we pass in a valid ID that does match a doc the Doc
comes back.
It's going to be an asynchronous test so we will be specifying the Done argument right here.
Now in order to run this test case we're going to need the ID of a to do that is actually inside of
the collection.
And if you remember we do add two to dues to the collection but unfortunately we don't have the IDs
here.
The Ids are auto generated behind the scenes in order to fix this.
What we're going to do is add the id property underscore ID.
This means we'll be able to access the ID in our test case and everything will work as expected.
Now in order to do this we do have to load an object id off of Mongo D-B which we've done before.
I'm going to make a constant using E-S six the destructuring.
I'm going to grab object id off of the return result from requiring Mongo D.
B.
Now right here inside of the array we can add an id property for both of our to Dewes new object ID
with a comma.
This is for the first to do and a down below we can add an ID for the second to to do as well.
New Object I.
D.
Excellent.
Now that we have ideas and we can access those IDs by accessing them off the to do's array we're ready
to write the test case down below inside of this test case.
We're going to get started by creating our super test request.
We're going to request something from the app express application.
It is going to be a get request.
That is the you are Alwar testing and the actual You are L is going to be a forward slash to Doo's forward
slash ID where the ID equals one of these IDs up above.
I'm going to go ahead and use the ID of the first to do down below.
We can fix this by changing our string to a template string so we can inject the ID forward slash to
Doo's forward slash and then we're going to add our syntax for injecting a value into the template string.
In this case we're accessing something from the Duzer.
We want to grab the first item this is the first to do and we're looking for it's underscore ideal property.
Now this is an object idea we need to convert this into a string because that is what we're going to
pass in as the you are able to convert an object ID to a string.
We can use the two hex string method.
There we go.
Now we've generated the proper ID and we can start making some assertions about what should happen when
this request gets fired.
First up the HTP status code that should be a 200.
So I can call expect right here passing in 200.
Next up we do want to verify that the body that comes back matches the body up above.
Most notably that the text property equals the text property we set.
I'm going to create a custom expect call right here to get that done.
We'll pass in our function that gets called with the response object.
And now we can make an assertion using the expect library.
I'm going to expect that the response body has to do property which we set up right here when we use
the 6 object's syntax.
And that to do property has a text property that equals using to be the text property of our first to
do.
That's going to be to Doo's grabbing the first one the zero indexed to do.
And we're going to grab its text property with this in place.
All of our assertions are done.
We can call and passing in done which is going to wrap up the test case.
Now we can go ahead and run this test over inside of the terminal by running NPM run test hyphen watch.
This is going to kick off our test suite and we should have our new section with our test case that
is passing.
Right here we get should return to do dock and that is passing which is fantastic.
Now it's time for you to write two test cases on your own.
I'll give you the calls.
So we're on the same page there but you are going to be responsible for filling out the actual test
function.
Should return a 404 if you do not found this is going to be an sink test so will specify the done argument
and your job inside of here is going to be to make a request using a real object I.D. and you're going
to college to hex string method.
That means you're going to call the method we have here and you're going to call new object ID to make
a new one.
It is going to be a valid ID but it won't be found in the collection.
So we should get a 404 back.
Now the only expectation you need to set up is the status code.
Make sure make sure you get a 404 back.
Now the second test you're going to write is going to verify that when we have an invalid ID we get
back a 404.
It should return 404 for non object IDs.
This is also going to be an async test.
So we'll specify done right here for this one you're going to pass in a u r l something like this.
Forward slash to Doo's forward slash One two three.
This is indeed a valid.
You are out.
But when we try to convert one to three to an object ID it's going to fail that should trigger the code
right here and we should get a 404 back once again and the only expectation you need to set up for this
test is that when you make the request to the you R-AL of 404 is the status code.
Take a moment to knock out both of these test cases making sure they work as expected when you actually
have the calls set up.
If all of your test cases are passing over in the terminal when you're done then you are ready to move
on.
Take a moment to knock this out pause the video and when you're done click play.
All right.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble getting these calls set up for the first one.
I'm going to go ahead and get that hex string by creating a variable.
Now you didn't need to create a variable you could have done it slightly differently.
I'm going to make a variable called hex ID sending an equal to a new object ID.
Now on this object id we do want to call that two hex string method which we used above.
This takes our object id and gives us a string and we can specify that string as part of the U r l.
Now it's fine if you did this inside of the call.
Kind of like we do up here.
Either way works as long as the test case passes right here.
We're going to call request passing in our app.
Next up we are going to make a get request.
So I'll call that get method and we can set up r u r l.
This one is going to be forward slash to Doo's forward slash and we're going to inject in our template
string that Hex ID value.
Now the only expectation we need to set up is that a 404 comes back.
We're expecting a 4.
0 4 we can wrap this test case up by calling and passing in our Done function.
Now we can save the file on this test case should rerun the last test is still going to fail but that's
fine.
And over here you can see we get exactly that should return to Dudack passes should return 4 or 4 if
to do not found passes in the last test to write is what happens when we have an invalid object ID.
I'm going to call Everquest passing an app and then I'm going to go ahead and call get setting up the
R L.
We don't need to use template strings here since we're just going to be passing in a plain straight
forward slash to Doo's forward slash.
One two three ABC indeed.
An invalid object id the object ID.
As we talked about have a very specific structure and this does not pass that criteria to find out more
about object IDs.
You can always go back to the object id video in the beginning of this section right here.
We're going to start setting up our assertions by calling expect and expecting a 404 comes back and
we can wrap this test up by calling the end method and passing in done with this in place our test suite
forget to use by ID is complete.
Over in the terminal it just reran and all of the test cases passed.
And this is fantastic.
We don't have a complete test suite set up for the route which means we are done.
And if the data comes back incorrectly for example if the body data has an extra character appended
like the character one the test cases are going to fail everything is working really really well.
The last thing left to do is commit our changes over inside of the terminal I'm going to shut down and
node man and run it get status here the only changes we have are changes to the server test file which
is a modified file get is already tracking it which means I can use get commit with the AM flag or the
combined am flag providing a message add test cases for get to Dewes by ID.
I'm going to make the commit and push it up to get up in the next video we're going to switch things
up a little bit instead of continuing on adding new routes which we will do a little later.
We are going to deploy our application to Heroku using a real world Mongo DB database.
That means all the calls we're making in post man we can make.
But to a real server and anybody can make those calls not just people on our local machine because the
RL will no longer be a local host that is coming up next I am super excited to show you how to set up
Heroku with Mongo D-B.
Stay tuned.
We'll see you then