In this video you're going to deploy the to do API to Heroku.
So anybody with a u r l can access these routes adding and fetching to do items.
Now before we can push it to Heroku there are quite a few things we need to change small little tweaks
to get it ready for the Heroku servers one of the bigger tweaks is going to be to set up a real Mongo
D-B database because currently we use a local host database and this is not going to be available.
Once we get our app on Heroku to kick things off we're going to move into the server file and set up
the app to use the environment port variable that Heroku is going to set which we did in the previous
section where we deployed to Heroku.
If you remember what we did is we created a variable called port and we set that equal to process dot
E and V dot uppercase port.
This is the variable that may or may not be set.
It's going to be set.
If the app is running on Heroku it won't be set if it's running locally.
We can use our or syntax to set up a value if port is not defined.
This is going to be used on local host and we're going to stick with port three thousand if the process
in the port variable is there we're going to use it.
If it's not we'll use 3000 now we need to swap out 3000 down below with the port which means our call
to listen is going to have port passed in.
And our string below is going to get switched to a template string.
So we can inject the actual port right here I'll use started up at port then I'm going to inject the
actual port variable in to the template string.
All right.
The port is set up and now we can move into the packaged up Jason File.
There's two things you need to tweak in here.
First up we need to tell Heroku how to start the project.
This is done via the start script the start script is the command that Heroku is going to run to start
the application.
In our case it's going to be node and then we're going to go into the server directory and we're going
to run the server.
J.S. file.
I have a com at the end and we are good to go with the start script.
The next thing we need to do is tell Heroku which version of node we want to use the default version
currently is a VIF 5 a version of node and that's going to cause some problems because we take advantage
of a lot of six features in this project and those are available in the six of node in order to figure
out exactly what version of node you're using you can run node at the from the terminal here.
I'm using six point two point two.
If you're using a different V-6 version that is perfectly fine.
Over inside of package out Jason we're going to tell Heroku to use the same version we're using here.
This gets done by setting up an engine's property engines lets us specify various versions for things
that Heroku lets us configure one of these is node the property name will be node and the value is going
to be the version of node to use Six Point to Point two.
Awesome.
Now our package Jason File is ready for Heroku Heroku knows how to start the app and it knows exactly
which version of node we want to use.
So we won't get any weird errors when we deployed with packages out Jason out of the way the last thing
we need to do is set up a database and we're going to do this with a Heroku ad on
know if you go to her Roker's Web site and click on any of your apps we haven't created one for this
one so click on an app from the previous section.
I'm going to go ahead and click on one of mine.
You're going to see a little dashboard where you can do quite a few things right here.
You can see there's an installed add ons section but what we really want is to configure our add ons
when you configure your add ons you're able to add all sorts of really cool tools that come built into
Heroku.
Now not all of these are free but most of them have a good free plan.
You can see we have various database related items down below we have data storage utilities we have
monitoring tools a lot of really cool stuff but we're going to be using as an add on called End lab.
This is a mango DBI database service.
It has a great free plan and it's going to let us integrate Mongo D-B with our Heroku application.
Now you don't actually need to do anything from the Web site we're going to do everything from the terminal.
I just want to make you aware of exactly where this lives.
Down below you can see they do have a free sandbox plan and they have plans that go all the way up to
$5000 a month.
We're going to be sticking with the zero dollar plan though everything in this course is free.
In order to get set up over inside of the terminal we're going to create a new Heroku app because currently
we don't have one Heroku create is the command to get that done.
Once the application has been created we need to tell the app that we want to use and lab which is short
for Mongo lab.
In order to add this add on we're going to run the following command Heroku add ons Colan create Now
the add on is Mongo lab and after the colon we're going to specify the plan we want to use.
We're going to use that sandbox plan which is free when we run this command.
It's going to configure and lab with our Heroku application and we are good to go.
Now if you run the Heroku config command you can actually get a list of all the configuration variables
for your Heroku application.
Right now we just have one.
It's a mongo DB.
You are I this is the database you are l that M lab gave us.
This is the one we need to connect to it's the only one available for our app.
Now this Mongo DB You are variable.
This is actually on process dot envy.
When the app runs on Heroku which means we can use a similar technique to what we did right here inside
of our mongoose J.S. file inside of mongoose.
J.S. Right here in our call to connect.
We can check if process dot NV dot uppercase Mongo D-B underscore.
You are I exists.
If it does we're going to use it if it doesn't after our or statement we are going to use the local
host you are Al.
And this is going to make sure that our Heroku app connects to the actual database because connecting
to local host will fail causing the app to crash.
With this in place we are now ready to get things going over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to run a get status to check our changed files.
We have three.
Everything looks good.
I can run yet commit with a flag.
This is going to let us specify our commit message set up app for Heroku.
I'm going to make the commit and push it up to get help.
Now we need to push our application to Heroku.
I'm going to do that using get push Heroku master.
Remember when you create a Heroku application it automatically adds that Heroku remote.
And here we're putting it to the master branch the master branch is the only branch Heroku is actually
going to do anything with the application is getting pushed up it should be ready in just a few seconds.
Once it's done we can open up the you are l on the browser and see exactly what we get.
Now another command I want to talk about for just a moment is a command called Heroku logs Heroku logs
shows you the server logs for your application.
If anything goes wrong you can usually get an error message inside of here.
So if you have a problem deploying in this section and you're going to ask a question on you to me please
run the Heroku Lockes command.
Copy the output and paste it into your question and this will let me answer your question right away.
Now as you can see we have our started up at port 4 1 9 0 6 message printing at the bottom which is
great.
Your port is going to be different as long as you have this message.
Everything should be good to go.
I am going to run Heroku open or copy that you are all up above.
You can see it right here.
This is going to open up the application in my browser.
I'm going to choose to copy the you are l.
I'll move into chrome and I can visit it now visiting the root of the app should do nothing because
we haven't set up a route you are Al but if we go to forward's slashed to Dewes we should get our to.
Jason coming back here you can see we have an empty array which is expected because we haven't added
any to do items.
So let's go ahead and do that.
What I want to do is grab this you r l and head over to post man inside of post man we're going to make
a few calls.
I'm going to create a post to Doo's request.
All I need to do is take the you are all here and swap it out with the one I just copied and then I
can send off the request because the body data is already configured.
I'm going to send that off and down below what do we get.
We get our to do item and this is not coming from our local machine.
This is coming from our Heroku application that is talking to our Mongo lab Mongo DB database.
Now all the other commands should also work.
I'm going to go to get to Doo's paste in the U R L and we should be able to get all of our to do items.
I'm also going to check what happens when I try to fetch an individual to do right here.
I'll copy the ID added on to the U R L and send off that request.
And what do I get.
I get the individual to do item so no matter which call we use.
Everything is working as expected and this is fantastic.
Our application is now running on Heroku with a real production database and that is it for this one.
Now we're up on her Roku in the next video.
I'm going to show you a few tweaks and tricks we can use inside of post man to make switching between
our local environment and our Heroku environment.
Much much easier.
That's coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then.