Before we get back to creating our express routes we're going to take a quick moment to explore a feature
of post man that's going to make it a lot easier to switch between your local environment and the Heroku
application.
This is called post man environments.
Now in order to illustrate this I am going to start up my local server by running node server server
J.S. and over inside of post.
We're going to start making a few requests now if you remember in the last video we made a request to
our Heroku application I clicked send on the get to Doo's you Arel and I get the two do's back as expected.
The problem is that over here the actual items saved in the collection and they all use that localhost
you are Owl and there's no good way to switch between the two.
To fix this issue we're going to create environments one for our local machine and one for Heroku.
And this is going to let us create a variable as the are Owl and we can change that variable by flicking
a switch over here in the environments dropdown to illustrate exactly how this is going to work.
I am going to be copying the Heroku you are all right now and then I'm going to head over to the know
environment dropdown and click manage environments.
Here we currently have none but we can go ahead and add it to the first environment.
I'm going to call to do app local.
This is going to be the local to do application and we can set up a set of key value pairs.
Now the only key We're going to set is you are all we're going to set a local host you are all for the
to do app local environment and we'll set the Heroku you are Al for the to do app Heroku environment
which will create in just a socket right here local host Colan three thousand.
We're leaving off path's because that is going to depend on the individual route.
I'm going to go ahead and add in that environment then we can create a second one.
This one will be called to do app Heroku and we're going to set the U R L key once again this time though
we're setting it equal to the value I copy to the clipboard.
This is the Heroku application you are out.
I'm going to add that now we have our two environments and I can close that window manager.
I'm going to close all of my tabs and I'm not going to make any changes by saving then I'm going to
go to get to do's.
Now currently get to deuse automatically fetches from localhost.
But we're going to do is replace the U R L everything before the slash with the following syntax which
will look similar if you're familiar with any templating engines.
Curly braces followed by the variable name u r l followed by two closing braces.
This is going to inject the u r l right here meaning that the get to Duzer Quest is now dynamic.
We can change which endpoint requests from localhost or Heroku based on the environment.
I'm going to save this request and fire it off.
And you'll notice when you try to fire this request we get an error.
It's trying to make a request to a u r l that starts with the curly braces.
This is the uncoated character you R-AL the closing curly braces and to Dewes That's because the U R
L variable is currently not defined.
We need to switch to an environment over in the environments list we now have to do app Heroku and to
do app local.
If I click to do app local and send that request off what do I get.
I get my two items in the local database.
If I switch over to to do app Heroku this is going to make a request to the Heroku application it's
going to be updating this you R-AL and when I fire it off we get a different set of data this time around.
All we have is our 1 to do item and the one that's available on the Heroku application.
With this in place get to Dewes can now easily be used to fetch local host or Heroku items and we can
do the same thing with our post to request right here I'm going to replace the R L with the curly braces
and inside of those curly braces will have the U R L variable.
Now I can go ahead and save this request fire it off and it's going to make a new to do on the Heroku
application.
If I switch to the local environment we can fire that off and now we have a new do on the local environment.
The last request to change is going to be the get to do is by ID request.
We're going to take that localhost three thousand.
Once again then we're going to go ahead and replace it with.
You are out.
Just like this.
And now we are done we can save the request and we can go ahead and fire it off.
Now this one has a second variable.
This is the actual to do ID.
You could add this as a variable as well.
For now though since it's going to change as we add and delete to Dewes I'm going to simply grab one
from the local database move into the get to Doo's requests swap it out here and send it off and we
get to do back.
If I make it a to do object id that doesn't exist by changing one of the numbers to 6.
We get a 404 everything is still working as expected and it's also going to work on the Heroku environment.
I'm going to fetch all the dues on the Heroku environment grab one of the Ids.
Move to the get to do by ID request swap out the ID send it off and we get that to do item.
Hopefully you're starting to see why these postman environments are so convenient you can easily switch
between two environments changing exactly what happens to the request.
Now in this case we happened to only have one variable you are Al you could add others and we will a
little bit later.
For now though that is it.
We have a way to swap between the two environments inside of postman.
Now that we have this in place we're going to move back into the Adam editor and we're going to start
adding new routes.
There's two more to go in the next video.
You're going to learn how to delete to do's by ID.
That's coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then