In this video we're going to explore how to remove documents from our Mongo DB collections using a mongoose.
Then you're going to be responsible for filling out the delete route which will let someone delete it
to do by the ID to get started we are going to duplicate that mongoose queries file.
Calling the new file mongoose hyphen remove.
In here we can remove everything below our initial imports.
I'm going to highlight everything in the file including the uncommented code below.
Remove it and we end up with a file that looks like this mongoose gives us three methods for deleting
our records.
The first one lets you delete multiple records.
This one is to do dot remove and to do not remove works kind of like to do dot find you pass in a query
and that query matches multiple records removing all of them.
If it matches none none will get removed.
Now the difference between to do find and to do remove.
Other than the fact that remove removes the docs is that you can't pass in an empty argument and expect
all the documents to get removed.
If you want to remove everything from your collection you need to run it like this.
If we run this we're going to have everything get removed.
I'm going to tack then on right here.
We're going to get back our results and we can print that result to the screen using console dialog
result just like this.
Now we can run the mongoose remove file which is going to remove all of that to do's from our database
node playground forward slash mongoose hyphen remove dot J Yes.
Now when we run the Remove method.
Once again we get back a results object.
A lot of this stuff is not useful to us but at the very top there is a result property we can see that
the removal did work.
We got a one back as opposed to a zero.
And we have the number of records that were removed.
In this case the number of records happens to be three.
Now there are two other ways to remove documents and these are going to be much more useful for us.
In this video the first one is going to be to do dot find one and remove.
Now find one and remove is going to work.
Kind of like find one it's going to match that very first document only it's going to remove it.
Now this will also return the document so you can do something with the removed data.
Now the data will be removed from the database but you will get the object back so you can print it
to the screen or send it back to the user.
This is unlike the Remove method in the Remove method.
We do not get the docs back that got removed we just get a number saying how many were removed was find
one and removed.
We do get that information back.
Now another method is to do not find a by id and remove find by id and remove works just like find by
ID you pass on the ideas the argument and it removes it.
Now both of these are going to return the doc and that is exactly what we want.
There is no need to run both of them we can just run one to do not find by id and remove.
This is going to let us remove it to do by ID some ID like this and we're going to be able to attach
a then method providing our callback in the callback is going to get the doc back.
You could call it Doc or in this case we can call it to do since it is a to do item.
Now that we have this in place we just need to create it to do since we deleted all of them and put
the ID in right here over inside of Roble Mongo.
I can right click that to Doo's collection and insert a document.
We're just going to set a text property and I'll set that text property equal to something to do and
we can save that record.
I'm going to make sure that when I click view documents we do get our one document and it's sitting
right here.
Now obviously it is missing some of the properties since I created an Roble non-goal but that is fine
for our purposes.
I'm now going to edit that document and grab the ID and this is the ID we can add into our playground
file to make sure the document gets removed over inside an atom.
Right here will pass in our string.
This is the string ID and inside of our then the callback.
We're going to use console dialog to print that to do to the con..
I am going to comment out this call to remove up above because otherwise it would remove the document
we're trying to remove right here with this in place I can now save the file head into the terminal
and rerun the script.
I'm going to shut it down.
Started up again.
And what do we get.
We get our documents sitting right here which is fantastic and if I had into Roboam I'll go and try
to fetch the documents into Dewes.
We're going to get an error that there are no documents we have one but we deleted it.
Now inside of atom we can also play around with find one and remove find one and remove works exactly
the same as find by idea and remove only it takes that query object.
This would be to do not find one and remove we would pass in the query object like this.
Pasting in our ID and we could attach our event callback which would get called with the document just
like this.
Both of these work very similarly.
The big difference is whether or not you need to query by more than just the ID.
Now that you know how to use find by id and remove we're going to go into the server file and start
filling out the actual route.
This is going to be the route that lets us delete or to do.
I'll do the setup for the route for you but you're going to be responsible for filling out everything
inside of the callback function to create a delete route.
We're going to use app dot delete
then we're going to provide you R-AL which will look identical to the one we have for getting an individual
to do by ID forward slash to reduce a forward slash colon ID.
This will be the ideal we could access inside of the callback function.
The callback function will get the same request and response arguments and inside of here I'll leave
some comments to guide you in the right direction.
But you're going to be responsible for filling every single thing out.
First up get the ID right here you're going to pull off the ID just like we do up above.
And we're going to do that because the next thing you're going to do is validate the ID.
If it's not valid not valid return a 4.
0 4 if it's not valid you're going to send a four or four back just like we do above.
Next up you're going to remove to do by deed.
And this is going to require you to use that function we just discussed over inside of the mongoose
room move file you're going to remove it by id and there's two ways that could go.
We could have a success or we could have an error if we do get an error.
You can respond in the usual ways sending back a 400 with an empty body.
Now if it's a success we're going to need to make sure that had to do was actually deleted by checking
that the doc came back if no doc send 404.
So the person knows that the I.D. could not be found and it could not be removed.
If Doc send doc back with a two hundred.
Now the reason we need to check if the doc exists is because this function fine by id and remove is
still going to have its success case called even if no to do gets deleted.
I can prove this by rerunning the file after having deleted the item with that ID.
I'm going to comment out find one and remove head into the terminal and rerun the script.
And what do we get.
We get Knol as the value of to do.
That means you want to set up an if statement like we do here to do something specific.
If no item was actually deleted with this in place you are ready to go.
You know how to do all of this.
Most of it is done in the route up above and everything specific to removing an item was done over in
this playground file.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock this out once you have it filled out.
You're going to go in the postman.
You're going to create a couple new items because currently we have none.
Then you can try to make a dillweed request seeing exactly what happens when you provide a valid ID
or you provide an invalid ID.
Make sure everything works as expected when you're done.
Go ahead and click play.
Hopefully you are able to get that done and you were able to successfully delete the to do you created
inside of Postman.
If so that is fantastic.
Now we're going to go through one by one.
The first thing we need to do is grab the idea off of the request object.
I'm going to make a variable called ID sending an equal to request Rams.
This is where all of our you are all parameters are stored and then we get it by value.
We have IDs set up right here.
So we would get the ID property.
I'm going to remove the comment and down below we can validate the ID.
If object id ADOT is valid.
Now we're checking if this ID is valid and if it is valid Well we don't really want to do anything.
All we care about is if it's not valid.
So I'm going to flip the boolean value and inside of here we can now run some code when the ID is not
valid.
That code is going to send back a 4 0 4.
I'm going to use return to preventing the rest of the function from being executed.
Then we're going to go ahead and respond.
Setting the status response status equal to a 4 0 4 and we'll call send to initiate the response with
no body data.
Now that the object ID is valid we can move on down below actually removing it right here.
We're going to kick things off by calling to do the dot find a by id and remove now find by id and remove
as you know takes just a one argument.
The actual ID to remove it we can call then passing in our success callback which as we know will get
called with the individual to do the document.
Now inside of the success case we still have to make sure to do is actually deleted.
If there was no to do we are going to send a 4 0 4 back if there was no to do we are going to respond
using return and setting the status using response status to a 404 and calling send to initiate the
response.
Now if this if statement doesn't run it means it to do.
It was actually deleted.
In that case we want to respond with a 200 letting the user know that everything went well and we're
going to send it to do argument back response and not send passing in to do the only thing left to do
for this to do challenge is to call catch.
We're going to catch so we can do something with any potential errors.
All we're going to do is respond using response dot status sending an equal to a 400 and we'll go ahead
and call send with no arguments sending back an empty response.
With this in place we are now good to go.
We have everything set up just like we wanted to which means we can remove the comments from down below.
And you'll notice that the method we have it down below looks really similar to the one we have up above
and this is going to be the case for a lot of our routes that manage an individual to do item.
We're always going to want to get that idea.
We're always going to want to validate that the object id is indeed a real object ID.
And down below inside of our success and error cases similar things are also going to happen.
We want to make sure that a doc was actually deleted if it wasn't we'll send back that 404.
And with this in place we cannot verify that this route works.
Now we can save the file and start up the server in the terminal I'll use clear to clear the terminal
output and then we can run node server forward slash server.
J.S. once the server is up we can move into post man and start firing off a couple of requests.
First up I'm going to create a few to do's.
I'll send this off and then I'll change the text and send it off again.
I'll change the body text to some other to do item sending that off.
And now we should have to do is if I go to get to do's and fetch them what do we get.
We get our two to do's.
Now I am going to need one of these ideas this is going to be the to do that we delete.
So what I will do is copy this to the clipboard and then we can go ahead and create our new route.
This new route is going to use the delete method so we're going to switch from get to delete then and
we can go ahead and provide the you are out using the environment variable you RL that we created in
the last video.
Their route is forward slash to Doo's forward slash ID.
I'm going to paste the ID in here.
Now I can go ahead and run the request when I run it.
What do we get we get a 200.
Everything went well and down here we have the document that we deleted.
If I go back to get to do's and rerun it now we only have one document and the item that we passed in
as the id to delete did indeed get deleted.
I'm going to save this request to our collection so we can fire it off without having to manually enter
all of that information.
Let's save as delete in uppercase followed by the route forwards slash to Doo's forward slash colon
ID.
We are going to save this to an existing collection.
The to do app collection now we have this route sitting right here.
We can always go ahead and access it whenever we need.
Now from here we're going to go ahead and fire the request again.
This is going to try to delete a to do whose ID is valid but doesn't match one in the collection and
we get a 404 back.
Now if I make this idea invalid by deleting a bunch of characters and I send that off we also get a
404 because the idea is invalid which is fantastic.
With this in place we can now make a commit over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to shut the server down run and get status.
And you can see we have two files we have a new file the mongoose playground file and we have our modified
server file.
I'm going to use get add a dot to add all of those to the next commit and we'll use it get commit with
the flag to make the commit add delete to Doo's by ID route.
I'm going to make the commit and push it up to get hub.
We can also go ahead and deploy our application using get push Heroku master.
Now we'll be able to delete our two Doo's inside of the Heroku application with this in place we are
now done.
I will see you next time where we're going to write some test cases for the route we just set up.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.