In this video you're going to write some test cases that verify our delete route works as expected.
Now before we get into that what we're going to do is make one quick change to the delete route to make
it match our other routes our other routes return an object.
And on that object the response body we have it to do property and we did the same thing for the to
do's call right here on the response body.
We have the DO's property that stores the array for the delete request.
We never did that.
What I'm going to do is send back an object as the response body where the two do.
Property equals the to do that got deleted.
Although we'll just use that.
Yes.
Six syntax to send that back with this in place we can go ahead and write some test cases that verify
the delete route.
Works as expected and this is going to happen at the very bottom of our server test file.
I'm going to create a new described block for the delete forward slash to do is forward slash colon
ID.
Right right here we'll provide our arrow function and we can go ahead and call it three times the first
test case.
It should remove a.
To do this is going to be test case number one.
It's going to verify that when we pass in an ID that does exist inside of the dues collection the item
gets removed.
Next up it should return 4 or 4.
If you do not found if we try to delete the to do but nothing was actually deleted we're going to send
the 404 back.
So the user knows that the call probably didn't work as expected.
Yes the call didn't necessarily fail but you never deleted the item you wanted to delete.
So we are going to consider that a failure.
And that's what we did when we sent the 404 back.
And the last test we're going to write it should return 404 if object id is invalid and this test is
going to verify that when we have an invalid object id do get a 404 back which is the expected response
status code.
Now these two tests will thaw a little bit later.
We're going to go ahead and focus on this one because this is where we're going to need to do a few
complex things.
Not only are we going to need to send off the request after the request comes back.
We're going to want to assert some things about it and we're gonna want to query the database making
sure that to do was actually removed from the to do this collection.
The first thing I'm going to do is figure out which to do I want to leave.
We have two options up above.
I'm going to go ahead and delete the second to do item though that choice is irrelevant you could easily
just do this with the first one down below.
We'll create a hex ID variable like we did for our previous test case.
We're going to set that equal to the second item from the to do is right.
Then we're going to go ahead and grab its id property calling the two hacks sharing method.
Now that we have the hex ID for the second to do item we can start worrying about making the request
right here.
I'm going to call request passing in the app.
We want to make the request too.
Then we can call Delete which is going to trigger a delete HTP request the following you are l is going
to have some variables injected into it so I will use template strings.
Its forward slash to Doo's forward slash followed by the ID.
I'm going to inject the hex ID variable.
Now that we have our delete method all set up we can move on to start making our expectations.
We're going to expect that we get a 200 back we should get at 200 because this idea is going to exist
in the database.
Next up we can assert that the data comes back as the response body.
I'm going to make a custom expect call passing in our function where we have the response argument sent
in and we're going to do is assert that the ID is the ID right here.
We're going to expect that the response body property has to do Propp Where are the underscore ID property
equals the hex ID to be hex.
I d.
If this is the case then we can verify the call pretty much worked as expected.
Now the last thing we need to do is query the database and make sure the item was actually removed.
I'm going to call end passing in a callback so we can do a few asynchronous things before we wrap up
the test case.
And if you remember gets called with an error and the response if there is an error we're gonna need
to handle that because otherwise there's no need to query the database.
If error were going to return to prevent the function execution done passing in that error so the error
gets rendered by moka.
Now we can go ahead and make the query and this is actually going to be your challenge for the video.
What I want you to do is query database using find by ID you're going to try to find the to do item
that has this ID.
Now when you try to find that ID it should fail you should get nothing back.
You're going to create that to do variable in your then call and make sure it does not exist.
You can make sure something doesn't exist using the to not exist assertion that would look something
like this we're expecting no to not exist although instead of null you'll pass in the to do argument
which is going to be in your success handler.
Now this usually would contain the to do item but since we've just deleted it it should not exist.
And this is going to get all of that done.
Now if there is an error you're going to do the exact same thing we did up above in our test case for
a post to Dewes right here we simply add a catch clause passing the error through to done.
Now that you know what to do it's your job to get it done.
What I'd like you to do is fill this out fill out the query.
Make sure to handle the errors.
Make sure to call it done.
Then you can go ahead and run the test suite verifying that this test case passes.
These two are going to fail.
So for the moment I'm just going to comment them out they're going to fail because we have a done argument
specified but we never call it.
So the test will time out after two seconds.
Take a moment to knock this out run the test suite make sure it works as expected and when you're done
click play.
I hope you are able to get that done.
The first thing to do is call to Dewes dot excuse me to do dot find by id passing in that Hex ID.
This is the item that should have gotten deleted.
Now we can call then passing in our callback.
It is going to get called with the doc the to do.
Variable and all we're going to do is verify that it does not exist.
We just deleted it so fine by ID should return.
No for the doc.
We're going to expect that the to do variable does not exist.
Using the to not exist method available on that expect a library.
Now we do need to call done to wrap up the test case from here we can go ahead and call catch.
I'm going to call catch grabbing that error argument and passing it through to done.
There's no need to provide curly braces here we just have one statement so we can use the shortcut which
is available in yes 6 for error functions with our actual query in place we can remove the comments
that outlined what was supposed to happen and we can run the test case over inside of the terminal.
We can now run the test suite to verify that everything we set up worked as expected.
Over here I'm going to use NPM run test HIF and watch to start up our test suite with gnomon and when
it runs we see that we have our one test under the delete describe a block and it is passing.
Should remove to do passed without any errors.
Now that we have one test case in place we can fill out the two other ones.
These test cases are going to be basically identical to the test cases we have above.
For the get to do by id route there is no shame in copying and pasting code when you one know exactly
what the code does.
We know what it does because we wrote it and two we actually do need it.
We can't reuse it.
We need to tweak it just a little bit so it does make sense to copy.
I'm going to copy this.
This is for the should return for a for if to do not found test and we're going to paste that into the
exact same test for the delete route and don't we have to do is change get to delete save the file.
This is going to rerun the test suite and now we have two tests under delete.
They are both passing.
You can see our last test still fails so we can go ahead and do the same thing.
I'm going to copy the code right here which verifies that non-object IDs cause a 404.
I'm going to paste it in here.
Changing the get method call to delete.
If I save the file it's going to rerun the test suite and this time around all nine of test cases are
passing.
With this in place we now have delete to Doo's tested.
Let's go ahead and wrap this one up by making a commit over inside of the terminal.
Over here.
I'm going to run and get status to see what changes I got going on.
Everything looks good.
We made one small change to the server file and we added our tests to the server test file.
I can use get commit with a M flag to make a commit and a good message for this one would be test the
delete to Dewes by id route.
I'm going to take that commit and push it up to get a job and there's no need to deploy to Heroku since
we haven't created anything visually different.
We did tweak the server code just a little bit but we'll worry about that a little bit later.
For now everything is good.
We can move on to the next video where you are going to create the final route for managing to do's.
This is going to be a route that lets you update to do.
I'm excited to get to it so stay tuned.
I will see you next time