The delete route is now set up and tested it's time to start on the final route for managing our to
do resources.
This is going to be the route that lets you update to do item whether you want to change the tax to
something else or whether you want to toggle it as completed.
Now this is going to be the most complex route.
We write everything so far has been relatively straightforward.
We're going to need to do a few extra things to get this updating route to work as expected.
The first thing I want to do before we go ahead and create the route down below is install that low
dash library we used in one of the previous sections for this course.
If you remember low Dasch provides a few really great utility functions and will be taking advantage
of a couple of those inside of our update route right here.
I'm going to use NPM II with the Save flag to install it.
The module name itself is called EHLO dash low dash and we'll be using the most recent version at four
point fifteen point zero.
Now once this is installed we can require it up top and then we can go ahead and add our route.
At the very top of the file we can make a constant will use underscore as the name for the variable
that stores the low dash library.
Then we'll go ahead and require it requiring low dash.
Now I've used regular variables here instead of constants for my other imports.
I can go ahead and switch these to constants as well.
Perfect.
Now that we have this in place we are ready to move to the bottom of the file and start adding the new
route.
This route is going to use the HTP patch method patch is what you use when you want to update a resource.
Now remember none of this is really set in stone.
I could have a delete route that creates new to do's and I could have a post route that deletes to Dewes
but these are just the general guidelines and best practices for API development right here.
We're going to set up a patch route by calling up patch.
This is what is going to allow us to update to do items.
Now that you are going to be the exact same you are Al as it has been when we're managing an individual
to do item forward slash to Doo's forward slash colon ID.
Then we can set up our callback with our request and response arguments inside of the callback.
One of the first things that we're going to need to do is grab that Id just like we do for all our other
routes.
I'm going to make a variable called Id set equal to request dot harams dot ID.
Now on the next line we're going to go ahead and create a variable called a body.
And this is the reason I loaded in low dash.
The body of the request body that's where the updates are going to be stored if I want to set a to do
text to something else.
I would make a patch request.
I would set the text property equal to whatever I want the to do text to be.
The problem here is that someone can send any property along.
They can send along properties that are on the to do items.
Or they could send along properties we don't want them to update for example completed at completed
at is going to be a property that gets updated but it's not going to be updated by the user.
It's going to be updated by us when the user updates the completed property completed and is going to
be generated by the program which means we do not want a user to be able to update it in order to pull
off just the properties we want users to update.
We're going to be using the pick method underscore dot pick pick is fantastic.
It takes an object.
We're going to pass and request dot body then it takes an array of properties that you want to pull
off if they exist.
For example if the text property exists we want to pull that off of a request body adding it to body.
This is something that users should be able to update and we'll do the same thing for completed.
These are the only two properties a user is going to be able to update.
We don't need users updating ideas or adding any other properties that aren't specified in the mongoose
model.
Now that we have this in place we can get started down the usual path kicking things off by validating
our ID.
There is no need to rewrite this code since we've written it before and we know what it does.
We can simply copy and paste it right there.
And now we can go ahead and move on to the slightly complex part of Patch which is going to be checking
the completed value and using that value to set completed at.
If a user is setting a to do do's completed property to True we want to set completed that to a time
stamp.
If they're setting it to false we want to clear that time stamp because that to do won't be completed.
Right here we're going to add an if statement checking if the completed property is a boolean and it's
on body.
We're going to use the underscore dot is Boolean utility method to get that done.
We want to check if body dot completed is a boolean.
If it is a boolean and that boolean is true body completed then we're going to go ahead and run some
code.
This code is going to run if it's a boolean and it's true.
Else we're going to run some code if it's not a boolean or it's not true.
If it is a boolean and it is true we're going to set body and Dot completed at everything we set on
body is eventually going to be updated in the model.
Now we don't want the user to update everything.
So we've picked off certain ones from the request body but right here we can make some modifications
of our own.
We're going to set this equal to the current time stamp.
We're going to create a new date which we've done before but instead of calling to string which is the
method we used in the previous section we'll be using a method called get time and get time returns
a javascript time stamp.
This is the number of milliseconds since midnight on January 1st of the year 1970.
It's just a regular number values greater than zero are milliseconds from that moment forward values
less than zero are in the past.
So if I had a number of minus a thousand it would be 1000 milliseconds before that Unix APIC which is
the name for that date that January 1st at midnight on Nineteen seventy.
Now that we have that in place we can go ahead and fill out the else clause inside of the else clause.
If it is not a billion or it's not true we're going to go ahead and set body completed equal to false.
And we're also going to clear completed at body dot completed at is going to get set equal to.
When you want to remove a value from the database you can simply set it to not.
Now we're going to go ahead and follow a usual pattern.
We're going to be making a query to actually update the database the query that we're going to be making
is going to be really similar to the one we made in our Mongo db update file inside of here.
We used a method called Find one an update.
It took a query the update object and a set of options were going to be using a method called Find a
by id and update which takes a really similar set of arguments right here and server.
We will call to do dot find by id and update the first argument for fine by id and update is going to
be the idea itself.
Since we're using a find by id method we can simply pass in the ID as opposed to passing in a query.
Now we can go ahead and set the values on our object which is the second argument.
Remember you can't just set key value pairs.
You have to use those Mongo DB operators things like increment or in our case set.
Now set as we explored takes a set of key value pairs.
And these are going to get set in this case.
We've already generated the object I have highlighted here.
We just happen to generate it appear and it happens to be called a body.
So I will set the dollar signs set operator equal to the body variable.
Now we can go ahead and move on to the final options.
These are just some options that let you tweak how the function works.
If you remember in Mago D-B update we set return original to false.
This means we get the new object back the updated one.
We're going to use a similar option with a different name it's called new.
It has similar functionality.
It just has a different name because that's what the mongoose developers chose with the query in place
though we are done.
We can tack on and then call back and catch call back and add our success and error code.
If things go well we're going to get our to do dock back if things don't go well.
We are going to get an error argument and we can go ahead and send back a 400 response status 400 dot
send now inside of here we are going to need to check if the to do object exists.
If it doesn't if there is no to do then we're going to go ahead and respond with a floor for return
response dot status 4 0 4 dot send if it need to do does exist.
That means we were able to find it and it was updated so we can simply send it back response dot send.
And we're going to send it back as the to do property where to do equals the to do variable using the
Yes 6 syntax.
With this in place we are now done.
It's not too bad but it was a little more complex than any of the routes we've done before.
So I want to walk you through it step by step.
Let's take just a quick moment to recap what we did and why we did it.
First up the first unusual thing we did is we created this body variable.
This has a subset of the things the user passed to us.
We don't want the user to be able to update anything they choose.
Next up we update the completed property based off of the completed property.
And finally we make our call to find by id and update with these three steps we are able to successfully
update our dues when we make the patch call.
Now to test this out I'm going to save the server file and start up the server over in the terminal.
I'll use clear to clear the terminal output and we can run NPM start to start up the app.
The app is up and running on port 3000 so over inside a postman we can make some requests to see exactly
how this works.
I'm going to switch to the to do app local environment and make a get to Doo's request so we can get
a real ID for one of our to do items and you can see we have some old data from our tests right here.
I'm going to grab the second one with a text equal to second test to do and then I'm going to go ahead
and create a new request changing the method from get to patch.
Right here we're going to provide our YOU R-AL.
It will be the curly braces you Arel with closing curly braces then we'll have Thorens slash to Doo's
forward slash the ID we copied never remember that Patrick Quest is all about updating the data.
So we have to provide that data as the request body.
I'm going to go to body raw.
Jason in order to do just that right here.
Let's go ahead and make some updates to the to do.
I'm going to set completed equal to true.
And if you look in the get to do tab you can see that that to do as a completed value of false.
So it should change and the completed property should get added with the request set up.
I'm going to go ahead and send it off and down below what do we get.
We get our to do completed is set to True and the completed act is set to the time stamp.
Now I can also go ahead and tweak this change and completed true to completed false to send off the
request.
This now sets completed equal to false and clears completed at last Lastly we could go ahead and do
something like setting the text I'm going to send it back to true and add a second property text setting
that equal to updates from postman I can fire off this request and down below we get our to do looking
just as we had expected to look.
We have our text update.
We also have our completed update and the time stamp showing up in the completed at field.
With this in place we don't have the ability to get delete update and create to do items.
Those are the four main crud actions.
The next thing we're going to do is write some tests that verify patch works as expected so we can automatically
run them and catch any regressions in our code.
For now that is it we're going to go ahead and in the terminal make a commit and push our changes we'll
push them up to Heroku and test that out as well get status reveals that we have just those two changed
files which means we can use a get commit with ATHM flag to make the commit a good message for this
one ad patch forward slash to Doo's forward slash colon ID.
I'm going to make the commit and push it up to get hub.
And once it's on get hub we can push it up to Heroku using get push Heroku master.
Remember the master branch is the only branch Heroku has access to.
We're not going to be using branching in this course but in case you already know branching and running
into any issues you do need to push to the Heroku M. branch to have your app redeploy.
Like I said that is not an issue if you're using all the commands as I use them in the videos.
Now that the app is deployed we can go ahead and open it up.
We're going to open it up by making requests inside a postman.
I'm going to switch to the to do app Heroku environment then I'm going to go ahead and inside of get
to Doo's fire off the request.
These are all the to do is available on Heroku.
I'm going to grab this first one I'm going to go over to the Patrick Quest swapped out the ID and we
can keep the same body.
I'm going to set completed equal to true and text equal to updates from postman when I send that off.
What do we get back.
We get back the updated to do completed looks great complete it looks great and text looks great as
well.
Now I'm going to go ahead and add this to my collection the patch call is going to come in handy down
the line.
So I will save it as giving it the name we have used for all of ours.
The GTP method followed by that you are Al.
I am going to save it to our existing collection to do app perfect.
With this in place we are done.
We have our patch route working and it's time to move on to the next video where we will test this code.
Stay tuned.
We'll see you then.