In this video we well I guess more appropriately you are going to be writing to test cases that verify
Passhe works as expected.
We're going to take one to do that's not completed and make it complete and we'll take a second one
that is complete and make it in complete.
Now in order to do that we are going to need to tweak the seed data we have on our server test file
the data are right here is to do items.
Neither of them have the completed property specified which means it's going to default to false for
the second item.
We're going to go ahead and set.
We're going to set completed equal to true.
And we're also going to set completed at equal to whatever value we want.
You can choose any number at all.
I'm going to go ahead and use 3 3 3 and now we have 2 to do's that are going to let us toggle both ways
to get started down below.
I will help you create the describe it block.
So we're on the same page there but you will be responsible for filling out the actual test cases.
This video is basically going to be a challenge because we've done a lot of this stuff before.
First up they describe a black We're going to describe this group of tests.
We'll use the method followed by that you are allowed to do just that.
Then we can go ahead and add our function and in here we can define our two test cases.
The first test is going to take our first to do and set its text equal to something else and we'll change
to complete it from false to true.
It should update the to do we can provide our function with the Done argument right here and I'll leave
some comments inside in just a moment to give you an idea as to how I'd like you to accomplish this.
The second test is going to be for titling that second to do where the completed value is already equal
to true.
Right here it should clear completed at when to do is not completed.
Perfect this test case is going to make sure that when we go ahead and remove the completed status setting
an equal to false completed at gets cleared know for the first test case what you're going to do is
grab the idea of the first item grab ID of first item and then you're going to make our patch request.
You're going to provide the proper You are all with the idea inside of it and you're going to use send
to send some data along as the request body for this one.
I want you to update the text set it equal to whatever you like and you're going to set completed equal
to true.
Now once you send that off you'll be ready to make your assertions and you're going to make one assertion
using the basic system assert that you get a 200 back and you're going to make one custom assertion
the custom assertion is going to verify that the response body has a text property equal to the text
you sent in text is changed.
You're going to verify that completed is true and you're also going to verify that completed at is a
number and you can use the to be a method available inside of expect to get that done.
Now for the second test we're going to do something similar but we're just going to go in the other
direction.
We're going to grab this should be GRABBE not grad grab ID of second to do item.
You're going to update the text to something different and you're going to set completed to false then
you can make your assertions.
Once again we will be expecting a 200 for this one and we will be expecting that the response body now
represents those changes text is changed to whatever you happen to pick.
I also want you to check that completed is now false.
And to check that completed at
is null and you can use the to not exist method available on expect to make that assertion.
This is what you need to do to complete the test suite.
Once you're done and wanting to run NPM test and make sure both test cases pass.
If they do you're good to go if they don't go ahead and tweak things around.
Feel free to use any code we wrote in any of the projects to get this challenge done.
That goes with every other challenge as well.
You can also use Google or stack overflow.
That is not cheating it's called being resourceful.
And that's what real developers do every single day.
So take a moment knock this out make sure that the proper data comes back based on the data you send
in and when you're done you can go ahead and click play you do.
I know this one was a little open ended but hopefully you were able to get both test cases set up.
Let's fill out the first test case first and I'll kick things off by grabbing the proper ID.
Let's make a variable called hex ID setting it equal to the first to do's underscore ID property and
we're going to call two hex string to get the string back.
We can pass in to the U r l.
Next up I'm going to go ahead and create some dummy text.
This will be the new updated text.
Let's make a variable called text and set it equal to whatever you like.
This should be the new text.
Now we can go ahead and actually make our request using request to our express application.
We will be using the patch method.
Hopefully you were able to figure that out on your own if you weren't maybe you use the documentation
for super test since I did not explicitly tell you how to make that patch call.
Next up we are going to be using a template string as are u r l forward slash to Doo's forward slash.
Then we're going to inject the hex.
I d.
Now before we can make our assertions we do need to send some data along as well.
So I'll call send passing in the data.
This is going to be the things we want to change for this test.
We did want to set completed equal to true.
I'm going to set completed equal to true and we do want to update the text source at the text equal
to the text variable up above.
And I can always leave off this part using yes 6.
Now that we have send in place we can start making our assertions.
The first one is easy.
We're just expecting at 200.
I'm going to expect a two hundred to be the return status code.
And before we add our customer assertion we can call and passing in done.
Now the last thing we need to do is make those assertions about the data coming back right here.
I'm going to call expect passing in a function this function as we know by now gets called with the
response and we can make our custom assertions.
We're going to make an assertion about text completed and completed at first up the text.
We're expecting that the response dot body dot to do dot text property equals using to be the text variable.
We defined up above.
If this is equal to the data that came back then we're going to go next up.
Let's make some assertions about that completed property.
We're going to expect that the response body to do has a completed property and that it's true using
to be true.
We set it to true right here.
So it should have changed from false to true.
Now the last assertion we're going to make inside of our custom expect call is going to be an assertion
about completed and making sure it's a number we're going to expect response body to do dot completed
at equals a number using to be a.
Inside of quotes the type number with this in place.
Our first test is now complete.
We can go ahead and remove those comments and actually verify it's working by running it over in the
terminal.
Our second test is going to fail.
That's fine as long as the first one passes.
We're good at to continue on.
I'm going to run NPM test.
This is going to fire off the test suite.
We can see our first patch test succeeds.
And this is the one we just filled out and our second one fails.
We're getting a time out after two seconds which is expected because we never call done.
Now that the first ones in place that we can go ahead and fill out the second one.
Now the code for these two tasks is going to be really really similar.
Now since we just wrote this code and we know exactly what it does we can copy and paste it.
I'm not a fan of copying and pasting code I don't understand but I am a fan of being efficient since
I know what this code does.
I can paste it right in here.
And now we can go ahead and make some changes instead of grabbing the hex ID for the first to do item.
We want to grab the hex ID for the second to do item and then the next thing we need to do is update
the data we're sending.
We don't want to set completely equal to true.
We already did that manually up above.
This one we're trying to set to False.
We are also going to update the text so we can leave that in place.
I'm going to go ahead and tweak the text value a little bit adding a couple exclamation marks on the
end.
Next up the assertions we're still expecting a 200 to be the status code that comes back.
That part's great and we are still expecting the text to equal the text for completed.
So we're expecting that to be false and we're not expecting completed to be a number.
It was a number originally but after this update it should have gotten cleared since the to do is no
longer completed.
We can use to not exist to assert that completed at it doesn't exist.
With this in place our test case cases done we can now delete those comments save the file and rerun
things from the terminal.
I'm going to rerun the test suite.
And what do we get.
We get both of our patch tests passing.
Now as you've probably noticed a four patch we didn't write those test cases for invalid object IDs
or object IDs not found.
You could add those but we've done them so many times so far I don't see that as a necessary exercise.
These two test cases though they do validate that our patch method is working as expected especially
when it comes to the slightly more complex logic that patch required to get everything done with this
in place though we are done testing our last route.
We can go ahead and make a commit and move on to the final video of the section which is coming up next
over in the terminal.
I'm going to run and get status here.
I see I have one a modified file on my server test file which looks great.
I can use get commit with the flag to make the commit add tests for Pache forward slash twos forward
slash D.
I'm going to go ahead and make that commit then I'll take a moment to push it up to get help.
And with that in place we are done.
I'll see you in the next video which is the last one for the section where you will learn how to use
a separate test database locally.
So you're not always wiping your data in the development database as you run your tests.
That's coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then