Now that all of our to do routes are set up and tested in this final video we're going to be exploring
how to create a separate test database for our application.
That means when we run the test suite we're not going to be deleting all of the data inside of our to
do app database.
We'll have a separate database alongside of testen to do app that's used for the testing D-B.
Now in order to settle that up we need a way to differentiate between running our app locally and running
our test suite locally.
And that's exactly where we're going to start this whole issue stems from the fact that in our mongoose
J.S. file we either use the Mongo DB are-I environment variable or we use this string.
This string is used for both testing and for development.
And when I say testing I mean when we run our test script and when I say development I mean when we
run our app locally so we can use it inside of tools like post man.
What we really need is a way to set environment variables locally as well.
So we always use the Mongo DB variable and we never had a default string like the one we have here.
And in order to get that done we're going to look at an environment variable that's actually pretty
special.
It's process dot.
Ian the dot node EMV.
And you don't have to write this code.
I'm writing on line 9.
I'm going to be deleting it in just a moment.
This node Ian the environment variable was made popular by the Express library but it now has been adopted
by pretty much any and node hosting company.
For example Heroku sets this value equal to the string production by default.
That means that we're going to have three environments total.
We already have a production environment.
This is what we call our app on Heroku.
We're going to have a development environment when we run our app locally and we'll have a test environment
when we run our app through moka.
This means we'll be able to set up a different value for Mongo DB You are for all three of those creating
a separate test database to kick things off.
We're going to add some code in the server J.S. file up at the very top.
We'll be moving this code out of server JSA a little bit later but for now we're going to tack it on
right here.
Let's make a variable called envy and we're going to set it equal to process dot NVI dot node envy.
Now this variable currently is only set on Heroku.
We don't have this environment variable set locally.
Now environment variables in general are used for much more than just node your machine has probably
close to two dozen environment variables telling the computer all sorts of things where certain programs
exist what versions of libraries you want to use that sort of stuff.
The node EMV variable however is something that we're going to need to configure in side of our package.
Jason File for our development and test environments then just down below we'll be able to add some
if else statements to configure our app depending on the environment.
If we're in development we'll use one database.
If we're in test we'll use a different one.
Now to kick things off inside of package that Jason we are going to need to tweak the test script setting
the node in the environment variable.
Now you can set environment variables by chaining together multiple commands.
The code we're about to write is going to have a fallback for Windows as well.
So you can write the exact same line if you're on OSX Linux or a windows.
This is going to work everywhere including her Roku.
The goal here is to just set node NVI equal to test before we run the test suite.
Now in order to do that we're going to start by using the export command the export command.
This is available in OS X and Linux this is the way to get it done.
Type this even if you're in Windows because when you deployed to Heroku you are going to be using Linux.
We're going to export node NVI setting an equal to test.
Now if you're on Windows This command is going to fail.
Export is going to trigger an error something along the lines of export command not found.
For Windows users we're going to add this or block where we will call set.
Now set is the same as export only it's the Windows version of the command right after it will be providing
the exact same argument node envy equals test after the final test.
We're going to add to ampersands to change these commands together.
So let's go ahead and break down exactly what's going to happen if you're on Linux.
You're going to run this command.
This command is never going to run because the first one did.
Then we're going to change on a second command running moka.
If you're on Windows This command is going to fail which means you will run the second command.
Either way you get the node in the variable set.
Then finally your chain on a call to moka.
With this in place we now have a way to set our node EMV variable right inside a package.
Jason this is a quick cross OS update.
As you can see here we have a modified version of that test script.
The original test script had a problem on the Windows side of things.
It would set the environment variables equal to the string test with a space at the end as opposed to
just the string.
Ts t.
In order to properly set the ENP variable to just ts t and not ts t space we're going to be wrapping
the entire set argument inside of quotes and we're escaping those quotes since we use quotes inside
of our Jason File.
This command is going to work on Linux OSX and Windows.
All right.
That's it.
No I'm actually not going at this for the start script the start script which is for the development
environment will just be the default.
We'll have it set to production on Heroku We'll have it set to test inside of our test script and in
the case of this script we'll just default it inside of servisez ass because we tend to run in this
file without actually going through the start script right here in a server.
J.S. also had a default to development if run production this is going to be set if we're on test this
is going to be set if we're on development this won't be set and development will be used which means
we are ready to add some if statements if the EMV is development we want to do something.
The thing we want to do is set up the Mongo DB you r l else.
If the environment is the test environment in that case we also want to set up some custom database
you R-AL and we would do that right in here.
Now we can go ahead and actually set up our environment variables.
We have two environment variables being used throughout the app both of which are set on her Roku.
So theres no reason to worry about that environment in the production environment.
We have our port environment variable right here and we have our Mongo.
DD You are I variable over inside of server.
Yes if we are in the development environment I'm going to go ahead and set process Dotti and we dot
port equal to 3000.
This means that we can actually remove the default right here.
There's no need to have a default because port is already going to be set.
It will be set on Heroku for production.
It'll be set locally for development and right here we'll set it for our final environment.
The test environment setting in equal to three thousand.
The next thing we're going to do is set a mongo DB.
You are my environment variable for development and test which is the exact same name for the variable
we have on production.
I'm going to remove our default taking the string and cutting it out.
So it's in my clipboard then I can remove all the excess code for setting that default.
And what we're left with is just a reference to the environment variable over inside of server.
Yes we can now set that environment variable for both environments.
Process dot EMV dot Mongo D-B underscore you are.
And we're going to set that equal to the string I just copied.
All right here we are using the to do app database.
Now down below we can set process.
Ian V dot Mongo DB.
You are I equal to the string we just copied.
But instead of setting an equal to the to do app database we're going to set it equal to the to do app
test database.
Now when we run our application in test mode we're going to be using a completely different database.
So it's not going to wipe the database that we're using for development to test that everything is working
as expected.
Right on the second line.
All I'm going to do is log out the environment variable using console that log.
I'm going to print the string in V with a couple of actresses.
So it's easy to spot in the terminal output and then I'll go ahead and pass the EMV variable in as the
second argument.
Now we can go ahead and test that everything is working as expected.
Over inside of the terminal I'm going to start up our app using node server server.
Yes.
And what do we get.
We get an NVI equal to development which is exactly what we expect.
And now we can play around with it in postman over inside a post man.
I'm going to switch to my local environment.
Then I'm going to go ahead and fetch all of my to do's and right here you can see we have some left
over test data.
What I want to do is go ahead and tweak this first one.
So it's different then we'll run our tests and make sure that the tweaked to do still shows up because
when we run the tests we shouldn't be accessing the same database.
So none of this data should get changed.
I'm going to copy the ID for the first item go into my patch call I'm updating the text and the completed
property.
So that's good.
I don't need to change that.
I'm going to go ahead and swap out the ID send off the call and now we have the updated to do with the
text of updates from postman.
Next up I'm going to go into the terminal shut down node server and run our tests using NPM test.
Now when we do this what do we get.
We get our EMV variable set to test right here.
Then it runs through the test suite.
All of our tests pass which is fantastic.
The true test as to whether or not what we set up works is if we start up the server again and we try
to fetch our data from the development database over inside of postman.
I'm going to make that get to do is request one last time and right here are to do data still shows
up as expected even though the test suite did run it didn't matter because it's not wiping this database
anymore.
It's now wiping a brand new database and you can view in robo Mongo if I click the connection and click
refresh.
We now have to do app databases we have to do app and we have to do app test.
This is fantastic.
Everything is set up and we are ready to get rolling.
Now what I do want to do before we go is take all of this code on a server J S and move it somewhere
else.
It doesn't really belong here and it only makes the server file more complex than it needs to be in
the server directory.
I'm going to make a brand new folder called config and in the config folder I'll make a new file called
config dot J.S. and inside of here we can do all of that process environment variable configuration.
I'm going to copy all of the code and replace it to a require call to that file.
It's a relative file so we'll go to a forward slash config forward slash config.
Jay Yes leaving off the extension inside of configfs.
We can now copy the code in and remove the line related to console dot lock.
Let's wrap this video up by committing our changes and deploying to Heroku over inside of the terminal
I'm going to clear the terminal output then we can go ahead and run get status to see what files we
have changed and we have quite a few.
We also have some new files in the server directory.
I'm going to use get added to add all of that to the next commit and not use get status again and to
confirm.
Everything looks good.
Now we're ready for that.
And I can go ahead and do that get commit with the M flag providing our message set up separate test
and development Envy's and I'm also going to deploy it to Heroku so we can verify we haven't broken
anything there.
Get push Heroku master.
Once this is done we'll wrap the video up by heading into postmen and making a get to Doo's request
to our Heroku application.
We're compressing the app and launching it now it looks like everything is going to go over inside of
post man.
I'm going to switch environments from to do app local to to do app parochial and we can fire off this
request now.
Now here we get our to do items coming from the real database.
Which means nothing was broken on the Heroku application and it shouldn't be.
Technically we haven't changed anything in Heroku.
All we're doing is we're running the config file but we don't use the default because it's already set
and it's not going to pass any of these statements because the ENP variable is going to be equal to
the string production.
So as far as Heroku is concerned nothing has changed and it's showing that because the data is still
coming back as expected.
And that is it for this video and that is it for this section in this section.
We learned about Mongo D-B mongoose API eyes post man testing routes all sorts of great features in
the next section we're going to wrap up the application by adding authentication that is all coming
up next.
I am super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you in the next section.