If you're on Windows.
This is the installation video for you if you're on Linux or OS X the last video was for you you can
go ahead and skip this one.
From here on out I am going to assume that you're on Windows.
The goal is to install Mongo D-B on our machines.
This is going to let us create a local Mongo DB database server will be able to connect to that server
with no ass and we'll be able to read and write data to the database.
This is going to be fantastic for the to do API which is going to be responsible for reading and writing
Various to do related information to get started.
We're going to grab the Mongo DB installer by going over to Mongo D-B dot com here we can click that
big green download button and there are quite a few options on this page.
We're using the community server and we are on Windows.
If you go to the version dropdown none of these versions are going to look right for you.
The top one is what you want Windows Server 0 8 are to 64 bit and later with SSL support.
I'm going to go ahead and start that download.
It is slightly big.
Just a tad over 100 megabytes.
So take a moment to start the download pause the video and when your download is done you can go ahead
and click play my installer just finished.
I'm going to go ahead and start it up.
It's one of those basic installers where you click next to a few times and you agree to a license agreement.
Go ahead and click the custom option for a second although we will be following through with the complete
option.
If you click Custom it's going to show you where on your machine it's going to install.
And this is important here.
You can see it's on my C-Drive Program Files Mongo db server then the 3.2 directory.
This is going to be important because we're going to need to navigate into this directory in order to
start up the Mongo DB server.
I am going to go back though and I will be using the complete option which installs everything we need.
Now we can go ahead and actually start to install process.
Usually you have to click yes verifying that you want to install the software I'm going to go ahead
and do that and then we are done.
Now once it's installed we're going to navigate into the command prompt and boot up a server.
The first thing we need to do is navigate into that program files directory.
I'm in the command prompt.
I recommend you use the command prompt and not get bash get bash is not going to work for starting up
the Mongo db server right here.
I'm going to navigate to the root of my machine using CD forward slash and then we can start navigating
to that path CD program files forward slash Mongo DB where DBM capitalized forward slash server capital
S board slash three point two this is the directory where Mongo DB was installed.
I can use Der. to print out the contents of this directory and what we care about is this been and directory
we can navigate into Been using CD bin and print its contents out using d'O and this directory contains
a whole bunch of executables that we're going to use to do things like start up our server and connect
to it.
The first one we're going to run is this Mongo.
File.
This is going to start our local Mongo D-B database before we can go ahead and run in this taxi see
there is one more thing we need to do over in the generic file explorer.
We need to create a directory where all of our data can get stored to do that.
I'm going to put mine in my user directory by going to the C-Drive users Andrew and right here I'm going
to make a new directory and I'm going to call this directory Mongo hyphen in data.
Now the Mongo data directory is where all of our data is actually going to get stored.
This is the path that we need to specify when we run the Mongo D-Conn. Ex-Sea command.
We need to tell Mongo where to store the data over in the terminal we can now start this command.
I'm going to run Mongo D.
X-C passing in as the D-B path argument.
The path to that folder we just created.
In my case it's forward slash users forward slash upper case.
Andrew forward slash Mongo hyphen data.
Now if your user name is different which it obviously is or you put the folder in a different directory
you're going to need to specify the absolute path to the Mongo data folder right here.
Once you have that though you can go ahead and start up the server by running the command.
You're going to get a long list of output.
The only thing you care about is that at the very bottom you see waiting for connections on port 27
0 1 7 if you see that then you are good to go.
And now that the server is up let's connect to it and issue some commands to create and read some data
to do that.
Well we're going to do is open up a second command prompt and navigate into that same bin directory
from the second command prompt we're going to navigate into that same bin directory using CD forward
slash program files Burrard slash Mongo D-B board slash server forward slash 3.2 for Slash Ben from
here.
We're going to run a mongo dot X..
Notice we're not running the Mongo D command.
We're running Mongo dot X-C.
This is going to connect to our local Mongo DB database and it's going to put us in sort of a command
prompt view of our database.
We'll be able to issue various Mongo commands to manipulate the data.
Kind of like we can run node from the terminal to run various javascript statements right inside of
the council when we run this.
We're going to connect it to the database over in the left tab.
You can see that connection excepted shows up.
We do have a new connection in the right hand side now we can run some commands to create and read data.
Now I don't expect you to take away anything from these commands.
We're not going to talk about the ins and outs of Mongo DB just yet.
All I want to do is make sure that when you run them it works as expected to get started.
Let's create a new to do from the council.
This is going to get done via D.B and dot to do's and on this to do's collection.
We're going to call the method.
Insert dot insert and we're going to call insert with one argument and object and that object can have
any properties we want to add to the record.
For example I want to go ahead and set a text property.
This is the thing I actually need to do inside of quotes.
I can go ahead and pick something I'm going to go with create new node of course.
Now when I run this command it's going to actually make the insert into our database and we should get
a right result back with an and inserted property set to one.
This means that one record was inserted.
Now that we have one to do in our database we can go ahead and try to fetch it using DBI dot to do's.
Once again this time instead of calling insert to add a record we're going to call find with no arguments
provided this is going to return every single to do inside of our database.
When I run this command what do we get.
We get an object looking thing where we had a text property set to create new node.
Course we also have an underscore ID property underscore ID as Mongo DB is unique identifier.
And this is the property they use to give your document.
In this case the to do a unique identifier we'll be talking more about underscore ID and about all of
the commands we just ran a little later.
For now we can go ahead and close this down using control-C.
We have successfully disconnected from Mongo and now we can close the second command prompt window.
Before we go there is one more thing I want to do.
We're going to be installing a program called robo Mongo Robo.
Mango is a gooey for Mongo D-B.
It's going to let you connect to your local database as well as real databases which we'll be talking
about later and it'll let you view all the data manipulate it and do anything you could do inside of
a database.
It's really useful.
Sometimes you just need to dive into a database to see exactly what the data looks like in order to
get this started.
Well we're going to do is head over to a new tab and go to robo Mongo dot org.
Here we can grab the installer by going to download.
We're going to download the latest version and I'm on Windows.
I want the installer not the portable version.
So a click that first link this is going to start a really small download just 17 megabytes and we can
click Next a few times through this one to get robo Mongo installed on our machines.
My installers all done.
I'm going to go ahead and start the process confirming installation and clicking next to just a couple
of times.
There's no need to do anything custom inside of the settings.
We're going to run the installer with all of the default settings applied.
Now we can go ahead and actually run the program by finishing the installer.
When you run robo Mongo you're going to be greeted with a connection's screen.
This screen lets you configure all the connections for robo Lango you might have a local connection
for your local database.
You might have a connection to a real you R-AL where your actual production data is stored.
We'll get into all of that later for now.
We're going to go ahead and click Create and by default your address of localhost and Port of 2 7 0
1 7 and do not need to be changed.
All I'm going to do is change the name.
So it's a little easier to identify.
I'll go with local Mongo database
perfect.
Now that we have this in place we can save our new connection and actually connect to the database by
simply double clicking it.
When we do that we get a little tree view of our database.
We have this test database.
This is the one that's created by default.
We can go ahead and expand it then we can expand our collections.
And right here we see the dues collection.
This is the collection we created over inside of the council.
I'm going to go ahead and right click that and go to view documents when I view the documents.
I actually get to view the individual records.
Here I see my underscore id property and my text property that has create new node course sitting right
here.
If you are seeing this then you are done.
It means that you have a local Mango's server running and that also means that you've successfully inserted
data into it.
We were able to use Roboam ongo to view the database.
We were able to use the Mongo DDX executable to start the server up.
Now that we have this in place we can actually create a node application that takes advantage of Mongo
D-B as its database that is all coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time