In this video we're going to go over some notes vocabulary that's going to set us up for the rest of
the course.
And if you are familiar with Escuela databases we'll be doing a little comparing and contrasting comparing
which term best maps up to a term in the other database.
Now it's not a perfect one to one map but as you'll see the general principles are the same.
It's really just the details that are different.
To get started the term database is used in both and Eskew allein might have a database for my to do
app and the same would be true in no as well both of those databases are going to contain various sets
of information.
If it's a weather app I might have a set of users a set of locations and a set of temperatures.
Now that data is stored inside of your database.
This is a little different inside of su l we have a table like structure instead of notes.
Well we have more of an array like structure.
Now the table is called a table and the horæ like structure is called a collection.
So if I have a weather app I might have a table of users and a table of temperatures inside of notes
that would be a collection of users and a collection of temperatures.
Now let's take that table of users.
What do you call an individual user and asks Who else you could call that user a row or a record.
That's what I have highlighted in red right here in no S Q L an individual user in the users collection
would be called a document that's going to start right here at that curly brace and it's going to end
at the end of my Jasen like object.
Here we have various properties just like we have various columns over here name Andrew name Andrew.
Now let's talk about those individual properties inside of su l you might have called this a column.
We have an e-mail column A Name column and so on and so forth.
And this is because su l is schema based.
So the Name column is going to exist for all records.
It's going to be of a specific type and it can pretty much be guaranteed to be there for anything in
this table instead of No.
Q Well it's not the same.
Your documents in a collection they don't all need to have the same properties.
The properties could be completely different although there's not usually a lot of value in that unless
you're doing some data mining or they could be the same which is what we're going to be doing.
We want to store some data like users and users are going to have the same properties those are going
to be called the fields inside of no as.
Well here we have a name field email field.
I might also call them properties since it's an object like syntax.
Either way though these are pretty much the big differences between STOVL and Nolst Well in terms of
vocabulary.
So we're going to create a database for the to do app we're going to have a collection of users will
have individual user documents and those documents will have fields.
Enough of this vocab.
Let's go ahead and actually start using Mongo D-B