In this video you're going to learn how to connect your node applications to the Mongo DB database that
you have running on your local machine.
This means that we'll be able to issue database commands right inside of our node apps to do stuff like
insert update delete or read a data.
This is going to be critical if we're ever going to make that to do arrest API when someone hits one
of our API endpoints.
We want to manipulate the database whether it's reading all of the to do's or adding a new one before
we can do any of that though we have to learn the basics to connect to our Mongo DB database from inside
of Node.
J.S. we're going to be using an NPM module created by the Mongo DB team.
It's called node Mongo D-B native and it includes all of the features you'll need to connect to it interact
with your database to get to it.
We're going to google node Mongo D-B native it a good hub repo which should be the first link is the
one we want the node Mongo D-B native repository.
And if we scroll down we can take a look at a few important links.
First up we have documentation and we also have our API docs.
These are going to be critical as we start exploring the features that we have inside of this library.
Double-O there's a ton of examples on how to get started.
We'll be going through a lot of this stuff in this course.
But I do want to make you aware where you can find other resources because the Mongo D-B native library
has a ton of features.
There are entire courses dedicated just to Mongo D.B and they don't even begin to cover everything that's
built in to this library.
We're going to be focusing on the important and common subset of Mongo D-B that we need for node J.S.
apps to get started.
Let's go ahead and open up the box.
When you go to the docs page you do have to pick your version will be using version 2.0 to have the
driver and there's two important links here.
We have a reference link.
This includes guide like articles things to get you started and other various references.
If you go back and you go to the API link and this includes the details of every single method available
to you when you're working with a library and we'll be exploring some of the methods in here as we get
started creating our node to do API.
For now though we can get started by creating a new directory for this project and then we're going
to go ahead and install the Mongo DB library and connect to the database we have running.
Now I am going to assume that you have your database running for all the videos in this section.
I have that running in a separate tab in my terminal.
It's sitting right here.
If you're on Windows refer to the instructions in the Windows install video to start your database if
you forget if you're on the Linux or OS X operating systems use those instructions and don't forget
to also include that DBI path argument that is essential for booting up your Mangold db server to kick
things off.
I'm going to make a new folder on the desktop for the node API.
I'll use M-K Diyar to create a new directory called node hyphen to do an API and then I can go ahead
and UCD to go into that directory C-D node to do API.
And from here we're going to run NPM in it which creates our package.
Jason File and lets us install this Mongo DB library NPM in it once again like we've done throughout
the course we're going to be using enter to skip through all of the options using the defaults for each.
Once we get to the end we can confirm and now our package Jason file is created.
The next thing we're going to do is open up this directory inside of Adam.
I'm going to go ahead and pop that open real quick.
It's on the desktop.
And here it is node to do API.
Next up inside of the root of the project we're going to create a new folder and I'm going to call this
folder a playground inside of here will store various scripts.
They're not going to be scripts related to the to do API.
There'll be scripts related to Mongo DB.
So I do want to keep them in the folder but I don't necessarily want them to be part of the app.
We'll use the playground folder for that like we have in the past in the playground folder.
Let's go ahead and make a new file and we'll call this file.
Mongo D-B connect and Dot J.S. inside of this file We're going to get started by loading in the library
and connecting to the database.
Now in order to do that we do have to install the library from the terminal.
We can run NPM install to get that done.
NPM install the library name is Mongo D-B.
All lower case no hyphens.
Then we're going to go ahead and specify the version to make sure we're all using the same functionality
at two point 2.5.
And this is the most recent version as of the filming after the version number I am going to use the
save flag.
This is going to save it as a regular dependency which it is we're going to need this to run the to
do API application with Mongo D-B now installed.
We can move in it to our Mongo DB connect file and start connecting to the database.
The first thing we need to do is pull something out of the library that we just install that Mongo DB
library.
What we're looking for is what's called the Mongo client the Mongo client lets you connect to a mango
server and issue commands to manipulate the database.
Let's go ahead and kick things off by creating a constant called uppercase m a mongo client.
And we're going to set that equal to require and we are going to require the library we just installed
a mango D-B and from that library we're going to pull off Mongo client just like this.
Excellent.
With a mongo client now in place we can call Mongul client and connect to connect to the database Mongo
client ADOT connect.
And this is a method that takes two arguments.
The first argument is a string and this is going to be you R-AL where your database lives now in a production
example.
This might be an Amazon Web services you are out or Heroku you are Al.
For our case it's going to be that local host you are l.
We'll talk about that in just a second.
The second argument that is going to be a callback function the callback function will fire after the
connection has either succeeded or failed.
And then we can go ahead and handle things appropriately.
If the connection failed we'll print a message and stop the program.
If it succeeded we can start manipulating the database.
That first argument in our case is going to look something like this.
We're going to start it off with Mongo D-B colon of forward slash forward slash.
When we connect it to a mongo DB database we want to use the Mongo D-B protocol like this.
Next up it's going to be at local host since we're running it on our local machine and we have the port
which we already explored 2 7 0 1 7 after the port.
We need to use forward slash to specify which database we want to connect to.
Now in the last video we used that test database.
This is the default database that Mongo DB gives you but we can go ahead and create a new one after
the slash.
I'm going to call the database to do app just like this.
Next up we can go ahead and provide that callback function.
I'm going to use and yes 6 arrow function and we're going to get past two arguments the first one is
going to be an error argument.
This may or may not exist just like we've seen in the past.
It will exist if an error actually happened otherwise it won't.
The second argument is going to be the db object.
This is what we can use to issue commands to read and write data.
Now before we write any data I'm going to go ahead and handle any potential errors that come about.
I'll do that using an if statement if error if there is an error we're going to print a message to the
console letting whoever is looking at the logs know that we were unable to connect to the database server
console a dialog that inside of quotes something like unable to connect to Mongo DB server.
Excellent.
After the if statement we can go ahead and log out a success message something like Konsole that log
and then inside of quotes we'll use connected to Mongo DB server.
Now when you're handling errors like this the success code is going to run even if the error block runs
what we want to do instead is add a return statement right here.
This return statement isn't doing anything fancy.
All we're doing is using it to prevent the rest of the function from executing as soon as you return
from a function.
The program stops.
Which means if an error does occur the message will get logged.
The function will stop and we'll never see this connected to Mongo db server message.
The alternative from the return keyword would be to add an else clause like this and put our success
code in here.
But it's unnecessary we can just use this syntax which I prefer.
Now before we run this file there is one more thing I want to do.
At the very bottom of our callback function we're going to call a method on NDB it's D.B ADOT close.
This closes the connection with the Mongo DB server.
Now that we have this in place we can actually save the Mongo DB connect file and run it over inside
of the terminal.
It doesn't do much yet but it is indeed going to work over in the terminal we can run it using node
playground as the directory and the file itself as Mongo D-B hyphen connect dot J ass.
When we run this file what do we get.
We get connected to Mongo db server printing it to the screen and if we head over into the tab where
we have the Mongo db server we can see we got a new connection connection accepted and then that connection
was closed down below.
And this is fantastic.
Using the Mongo library we were able to connect print a message and disconnect from the server.
Now you might have noticed that we changed the database name right here and we never actually did anything
to create it in Mongo D-B unlike other database programs.
You don't need to create a database before you start using it.
If I want to kick up a new database I simply give it a name something like.
Users.
Now I have a users database I can connect to it and I can manipulate it.
There is no need to create that database.
First I'm going to go ahead and change this back to do app and if we head into the robo Mongo program
and connect it to our local database you'll also see that the only database we have here is test indeed
to do app database was never even created even though we connected to it.
Mongo is not going to create the database until we start adding and data into it and we can go ahead
and do that right now.
Inside of atom what we're going to do right before our call to DVD-Rs close is insert a new record into
a collection.
Now this is going to be the to do application.
We're going to have two collections in this app A to do's collection and a user's collection right here.
We can go ahead and start adding some data to the collection by calling NDB dot collection DVD collection
takes as its only argument in the string name for the collection.
You want to insert into now like the actual database itself.
You don't need to create this collection first.
You can simply give it a name like uppercase t to do's and you can start inserting into it.
There is no need to run any command to create it.
Right here we're going to use a method available on our collection called insert one insert one lets
you insert a new document into your collection.
It takes two arguments and the first one is going to be an object.
This is going to store the various key value pairs.
We want to have on our document.
And the second one is going to be a callback function.
This callback function will get fired when things either fail or go well.
You're going to get an error argument which may or may not exist.
And you'll also get the result argument which is going to be provided if things went well inside of
the arrow callback function itself.
We can add some code to handle the error and then we'll add some code to print the object to the screen
if that was added successfully.
First up let's add that air handler much like we do above.
We're going to check if the error argument exists.
If it does then we'll simply print a message using the return keyword to stop the function execution.
Here we can use cancel dialog to print unable to insert to do excellent.
The second argument Ahman a past to console dialog is going to be the actual air object itself.
So if someone's looking at the logs they can see exactly what went wrong.
Down below our IF statement we can add our success code in this case all we're going to do is pretty
print something to the screen console dialog.
Then I'm going to call Jason and Dot string if I and then we're going to go ahead and pass in result.
Dot ops the OPs attribute is going to store all of the docs that were inserted in this case we used
insert one.
So it's just going to be our one document.
Then I can add my other two arguments undefined for the filter function and the indentation will be
to do with this in place.
We can now go ahead and execute our file and see what happens.
Hey it's Andrew from the future with a quick update.
This course was filmed using Mongo DBI module to and the code for that is the code that we just wrote
out in the video.
I put it over here.
Just for comparison's sake.
This code right here is the exact code that you have in your file.
Now if you're using Mongo DBI module V-2 you can stick with this code.
The code is going to work as expected.
You can figure out what version of Mongo DBI you installed by looking for it in package.
Jason.
Now some students have upgraded to V3 and you can't just make the upgrade with the same code because
there are a few API changes that we're going to need to address.
So on the left hand side we have the current code on the right hand side we have the updated code.
There are three things we're going to talk about.
We're going to talk about a change and arguments we're going to talk about a new line and we're going
to talk about a change in where we access the Close method.
So first up the arguments no longer do we get error and D-B we now get error and client in v3.
So we have to use this client argument instead.
Now we do still need access to a database reference.
We get that with this new line.
Here we use client Scott D-B calling it passing in the database reference we're looking for.
In this case we're trying to get a reference for the to do app database.
Then we have this D.B and we can actually do something meaningful with it like call dbd collection.
So all of the code here hasn't changed at all.
It's the exact same code over here.
All that changes is that we now need to do a bit of work to get that database reference.
So that's the argument change and the new line change.
The last thing to talk about is that there is no longer a DB close method.
It is now client datt close.
So you're gonna want to make sure to change that as well.
If you looked in package that Jason and you're using V-2 of mango D-B you don't have to make a single
change.
If you do see yourself using v3 you're going to have to make those three changes before running the
script.
Right that is it for this update.
Everything else is exactly the same.
Let's jump right back into the video over inside of the terminal I'm going to run node playground board
slash a mongo D-B hyphen connect dot and J.S. when I execute the command.
We get our success message connected to Mongo db server and then we get an array of documents that were
inserted.
Now as I mentioned in this case we just inserted one document and that shows up right here.
We have the text property the text property gets created by us.
We have the completed property that gets created by us and we have the underscore ID property which
gets automatically added by Mongo.
Now the underscore ID property is going to be the topic of the next video we're going to talk in-depth
about what it is why it exists and why it's awesome.
For now we're going to go ahead and just know that it's a unique identifier.
It's an idea given to just this document.
And there we go and that is all it takes to insert a document into your Mongo DB database using node.
J.S. we can view this doc over inside of a robo mango up here.
I'm going to click the connection using right click and click refresh.
This reveals our brand new to do app database if we open that up.
We get our collections list.
We can then go into the collections view the documents and what do we get.
We get our one to do item.
If we expand it we can see we have our ID.
We have our text property and we have our completed boolean.
In this case the to do is not completed.
So the completed value is false.
Now that we have this in place what I want you to do is add a new record into a collection.
This is going to be your challenge for the video over inside of Adam.
What I'd like you to do is take the code all the way from D-B dot collection down to the bottom of our
callback and comment it out and then we're going to go ahead and add something.
And down below right here you're going to insert new doc into the users collection uppercase you a users
and this doc is going to have a few properties I want you to give it a name property set that equal
to your name.
Then we're going to give it an age property.
And last but not least we can give it a location string.
I want you to insert that doc using Insert one.
You're going to need to pass in the new collection name into the collection method then down below you're
going to add some error handling code and you're going to print the ops to the screen once you rerun
the file.
You should be able to view your record in the terminal and you should be able to refresh things over
in robo Mongo.
You should see the new users collection and you should see your user with the name age and location
you specified right here.
So take a moment to pause the video create that new record check that it works by viewing it in the
terminal and in roba Mongo.
And when you're done go ahead and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to insert a new document into that user's collection which you needed to do
in order to get this done is call D-B Dom collection so we can access the collection we want to insert
into which in this case is users.
Next up we have to call a method to manipulate that user's collection.
We want to insert a new document.
So we're going to use Insert one just like we did up above.
We're going to pass into insert one or two arguments the first one is the document to insert.
We're going to give it a name property.
I'll set that equal to Andrew and then we can go ahead and set the age equal to something like 25.
And lastly we'll set location equal to my current location.
Philadelphia excellent.
The next argument we wanted to pass in is our callback function which is going to get called with the
error object as well as of the result inside of the callback function itself.
We're going to first handle the error if there was an error.
We're going to go ahead and log it to the screen.
I'm going to return console log.
And then we can put a message right here unable to insert user.
And then I'll add at the error argument as the second argument to console that lock.
Next up down below we can add our success case code.
If things do go well all I'm going to do is use console a log to print result dot ops to the screen.
This is going to show us all of the records that were inserted with this in place.
We can now go ahead and rerun the file over inside of the terminal using the up arrow key and the Enter
key.
When we do it what do we get.
We get our array of inserted documents and we just have one the name age and location all come from
us.
And the id property comes from a mango D-B.
Next up I wanted you to verify that it was indeed inserted by viewing it over in Roboam Mongo.
In general when you add a new collection or a new database you can just right click the connection itself
click refresh and then you should be able to see everything that was added.
Right here we have our users collection.
I can view the documents for users.
And what do we get.
We get our one document with name set to Andrew age set to 25 and location set to Philadelphia.
With this in place we are now done.
We've been able to connect to our Mongo DB database using node J.S. and we've also learned how to insert
documents using this Mongo native library.
With this in place we're not ready to move on to the next video where we're going to take an in-depth
look at object IDs exploring exactly what they are and why they're useful.
Stay tuned.
I will see you next time.