And now that you have inserted some documents into your Mongo DB collections I want to take a moment
to talk about that.
Underscore id property in the context of a mongo DB because its a little different than the ideas that
you're probably used to if you've used other database systems like post graphs or my ask you Al to kick
off our discussion of the id property.
Let's go ahead and rerun the Mongo DB connect file.
This is going to insert a new document into the user's collection like we have defined right here.
I'm going to go ahead and do that by running the file through node.
It's in the playground folder and the file itself is called Mongo D-B heighth and connect Dot.
Yes I'm going to run the command and we're going to print out the document that got inserted.
And as we've seen in the past we get our three attributes as well as the one added by Mongo.
Now the first thing you'll notice about this is that it is not an auto incrementing integer kind of
like it is for post-crash or my Eskew minuscule where the first record has an idea of 1 and the second
one has an idea of two.
Mongo does not use this approach.
Mongo was designed to scale out really easily scaling out means that you add on more database servers
to handle that extra load.
Imagine you have a web app that gets about 200 users a day and your current servers are ready for that
traffic.
Then you get picked up by some news outlet and 10000 people flood your site with Mongo DB.
It is really easy to kick up new database servers to handle that extra load when we use a randomly generated
Id like this one.
We don't need to constantly communicate with the other database servers to check what the highest incrementing
value is.
Is it 7 is it 17.
Doesn't really matter.
We're simply going to generate a new random object id and use that for the documents unique identifier.
Now the object idea itself is made up of a few different things.
It's a 12 by value the first four bytes are a time stamp.
We'll talk about that in just a second.
That means that built into the data right here we have a time stamp that refers to the moment in time
the ID was created.
This means in our documents we don't need to have a created field it's already encoded in the ID.
The next three bytes those are a machine identifier.
That means if two computers generate object IDs their machine ID is going to be different.
This is going to ensure that the ID is unique.
Next up we have two bytes the process id just another way to create a unique identifier.
Last up we have a three byte counter.
This is similar to what my Eskew Ellwood do.
This is only three bytes of the ID.
As we talked about we have a time stamp which is going to be unique a machine identifier a process ID.
And lastly just a random value.
That is what makes up the object id you see right here.
Well the object id is the default value for underscore ID if nothing is provided you can indeed do whatever
you like with that property.
For example over inside of the Mongo DB connect file I can specify an ID property right here.
I'm going to give it a value let's go with one two three and a comma at the end and that is perfectly
legal.
We can save the file a rerun the script using the up arrow key and the enter key and what do we get.
We get our record where the underscore ID property is 123 and the object id is the default way.
Mongo D-B creates IDs but you can do anything you like for ID creation over inside of robo Mongo we
can give our users collection a refresh.
And what do we get.
We get our documents.
We have the one we created in the last video and the two we just made.
Now all with a unique identifier.
And this is why unique IDs are really important.
And this example we have three properties in name age and location and theyre the same for all the records
and that's a reasonable thing to do.
Imagine two people need to do the same thing like buy groceries and that string alone is not going to
be enough to uniquely identify to do object IDs on the other hand are going to be unique and that is
what we're going to use to associate things like to do with things like users.
Next up I want to take a look at some things we can do with the ID inside of our code.
As I mentioned earlier a time stamp is embedded inside of here and we can actually pull that out over
inside of atom.
What were going to do is remove the ID property right here the time stamp is only going to be available
when you're using object IDs.
Then down below inside of our callback we can go ahead and print the time stamp to the screen.
If you remember result dot ops is an array of all the documents that got inserted.
We're only inserting one here so I'm going to access the first item in the array and then we're going
to access the ID property.
This is going to do exactly what you might think if we save the file and rerun the script over from
the terminal all we get is the object id printing to the screen.
Now though we can call a method on the underscore ID property but we're going to call is dot get time
stamp and get time stamp is a function but it doesn't take any arguments it simply returns the time
stamp that the object idea was created at.
Now if we go ahead and rerun our program what do we get.
We get a time stamp right here I can see that the object idea was created on August 11th 2016 at 15
0 3 in GMT which would be 11 0 0 3 on the East Coast where I am.
So this time stamp is indeed correct.
This is a fantastic way to figure out exactly when a document was created.
Now we don't have to rely on Mongo DB to create our object IDs inside of the Mongo DB library.
They actually give us a function we can run to make an object ID whenever we like for the moment let's
go ahead and comment out our call to insert one right here.
Up above at the very top of the file We're going to change our inport statement to Loden something new
off of Mongo D.B and we're going to do this using an S 6 feature known as object destructuring.
Let's take a quick second to talk about that before we actually go ahead and use it.
Object restructuring lets you pull out properties from an object creating variables.
This means if we have an object called user and it set equal to an object with a name property set to
Andrew and then age property set to 25.
We can easily pull out one of these into a variable.
Let's say for example we want to grab name and create a name a variable to do that using object destructuring
in ESX.
We're going to make a variable and then we're going to wrap it inside of curly braces.
We're going to provide the name we want to pull out.
This is also going to be the variable name.
Then we're going to set it equal to whatever object we want to do structure.
In this case that is the user object and there we go.
We have successfully restructured the user object pulling off the name property creating a new name
variable and setting it equal to whatever the value is.
This means right below I can use console dialog to print name to the screen.
I'm in a rerun the script and we get angry right here which is exactly what you'd expect because that
is the value of the name property.
E6 destructuring is a fantastic way to make new variables from an object's properties.
I'm going to go ahead and delete this example and up above.
We're going to change our require statement to use a destructuring before we add anything new.
Let's go ahead and take this statement and switch it to destructuring and then we'll worry about grabbing
that new thing that's going to let us make object IDs.
I'm going to copy and paste this line down below and comment out the old one so we have it for reference.
Well we're going to do is remove our DOT Mongo client call after require there's no need to pull off
that attribute like we do here because we're going to be using destructuring instead.
And that means over here we can use destructuring which requires us to add our curly braces and we can
pull off any property from the Mongo DB library.
In this case the only property we had was a mongo client.
This creates a variable called Mongo client like we do here setting it equal to the Mongul client property
of require Mongo D-B which is exactly what we did here.
This code is identical to the code up above.
Now that we have some destructuring in place we can easily pull more things off of Mongo DB.
We can Atacama right here and specify something else we want to pull off.
In this case we're going to pull off upper case o object upper case I.
A D.
And this object id constructor function lets us make new object IDs on the fly.
We can do anything we like with them even if we're not using Mongo DB as our database.
There is some value in creating and using object IDs to uniquely identify things down below.
We can make a new object id by first creating a variable I'll call it LBJ and we'll set it equal to
New object id calling it as a function just like this using the new keyword we create a new instance
of Object ID.
Next up we can go ahead and log that to the screen using console dialog.
Oh just like we did earlier and this is a regular object ID if we rerun the file over from the terminal
we get exactly what you'd expect.
We get an object id a looking thing.
If I rerun it again what do we get.
We get a new one.
They are both unique.
Using this technique we can incorporate object IDs anywhere we like.
We could even generate our own setting them as the underscore ID property for our documents.
And though I find it much easier to Mongo DB handle that heavy lifting for us I'm going to go ahead
and remove the two lines right here since he won't actually be using this code in the script down below.
And with this in place we are now done.
We have learned a bit about object IDs what they are and why they're useful in the next couple of videos
we're going to be taking a look at other ways we can work with Mongo D-B will learn how to read remove
and update our documents.
That's all coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you next time.