It now that you know how to insert data into your database.
Let's go ahead and talk about how we can fetch data out of it and we're going to be using this technique
to do API.
People are going to want to populate a list of all the to do items they need to do.
And they might want to fetch the details about an individual to do item.
All of this is going to require that we can query the Mongo IDB database not to kick things off.
We're going to create a new file based off of Mongo DB connect.
In this new file instead of inserting records like we do here we'll fetch records from the database.
I'm going to created duplicate calling this new file.
Mongo D-B hyphen find Because find is the method we're going to use to query that database down below.
We can go ahead and remove all of the commented out code that currently inserts records Well let's get
started by trying to fetch all of the dues out of our dues collection.
Now if I had over to robo Mongo and open up the to dues collection we have just one record in order
to make this queering a little more interesting.
We're going to go ahead and add a second one right here.
I can click to insert a new document Rogow Mongo can delete insert update and read all of your documents
and this makes it a fantastic tool for debugging.
Right here we can add a new document on the fly with a text property equal to walk with the dog and
we can also tack on a completed value.
I'm going to set completed equal to false no by default we're not going to provide an underscore ID
Propp.
This is going to let Mongo DB automatically generate that object id and right here we have our two days
with this in place.
Let's go ahead and run our first query over inside of atom in atom what we're going to do is access
the collection just like we did over inside of the connect file using DBD collection D-B dot collection
passing in the collection name as the string.
This collection is going to be the to do's upper case t collection.
Now we're going to go ahead and use a method available on collections called Find ADOT find by default.
We can call find with no arguments.
This means we're not providing a query so we're not saying we want to fetch all to do's that are completed
or not completed.
We're just saying we want to patch all to do everything regardless of its values.
We want every document from the to do's collection no calling fine is only the first step.
Find returns a mongo DB cursor this cursor is not the actual documents themselves.
There could be a couple of thousand and that would be really inefficient it's actually a pointer to
those documents and the cursor has a ton of methods we can use those methods to get our documents.
One of the most common cursor methods we're going to be using is dot to uppercase a array to Array.
It does exactly what you might think it does.
Instead of having a cursor we have an array of the documents.
This means we have an array of objects they have ID properties text properties and completed properties.
This two array method gets us exactly what we want back we want back the documents now to array the
returns a promise.
That means we can tack on a then call.
We can add our call back and when things go right we can do something like.
Print those documents to the screen.
We're going to get the documents as the first and only argument here and we can also add an air handler
down below we'll get past an heir argument and we can simply print something to the screen like Konsole
dialogue.
Unable to fetch to do's.
And there's the second argument we'll pass in the air object.
Now up above for the success case what we're going to do is print the documents to the screen.
I'm going to go ahead and use Konsole dialogue to print a little message to do's and then I'll call
Konsole dialogue again.
This time we'll be using our Jason and docstring ify technique.
I'll be passing in the documents undefined for our filter function and to for our spacing.
With this in place we now have a script that is capable of fetching the documents converting them into
an array and printing them to the screen.
Now for the time being I'm going to comment out the D-B a dock close method currently that would interfere
with the code we have above.
So let's go ahead and comment that out save the file and run it from the terminal inside of the terminal.
I'm going to go ahead and run our script obviously since we connected to the database with robo Mongo
it is running somewhere it's running in this other tab over here.
I can run the script.
We're going to run it through node.
It is in the playground folder and the file itself is called Mongo D-B hyphen find.
Dot.
Yes.
When I execute this file We're going to get our results and what do we have.
We have our two do's array with our two documents.
We have our IDs are text properties and are completed boolean values.
And this is fantastic.
We now have a way to query our data right inside of a node.
Yes.
Now this is a very basic query.
We set everything in the to do array regardless of whether or not it has certain values in order to
query based on certain values.
Let's go ahead and switch up our to do's currently.
Both of them have completed a value equal to false.
Let's go ahead and change the walk the dogs completed value to true so we can try to query just items
that aren't complete.
Over in Roboam Ango we can go ahead and do just that.
I'm going to write click the document and click Edit document and right here we can go ahead and edit
the values.
I'm going to change the completed value from false to true and then I can save the record and over inside
of the terminal I can rerun the script to prove that it changed.
I'm going to shut down the script by running Control-C and then I can rerun it and right here we have
our two to choose one with a completed value of false and one with a completed value of true.
Now by default a to do app is probably only going to show you that to Dewes you haven't completed the
ones you have completed.
Like walk the dog will probably be hidden although they could be accessible if you clicked about unlike
Shelta news.
Let's go ahead and write a query that just fetches the dues.
They have a completed status set to false to get this done over inside of atom and we're going to make
a change to how we call find instead of passing in zero arguments we're going to pass in one.
This is what's known as our query inside of here.
We can start specifying how we want to query that to dues collection.
For example maybe we want to query only two Doo's that have a completed value equal to false.
All we have to do to query by value is set up the key value pairs right here.
If I rerun our script over in the terminal after shutting it down what do we get we get just our one
to do item.
We have our item with the text equal to something to do it as a completed status of false show it shows
up our other to do with a text of walk the dog that is not showing up down below because that one has
been completed.
It doesn't match the query.
So Mongo D-B does not return it.
This is going to come in handy as we start querying our documents based off of completed values text
properties or IDs.
Let's take a quick moment to look at how we can query one of our two do's by ID.
The first thing we need to do is remove everything from our query object.
We no longer want to query by the completed value instead we're going to query by that underscore ID
property.
Now in order to illustrate this I'm going to grab the ID from the terminal of the do with the completed
value of false.
I'm going to copy it using a command.
See if you're on a Windows or Linux you might need to right click after highlighting the ID and click
copy text.
And now that I have the text inside of the clipboard though I can head over to the query itself.
Now if we tried to add the ID like this it is not going to work as expected because what we have inside
of the ID property is not a string it's an object id which means that we need to use this object id
constructor function that we imported previously in order to create an object id for the query to illustrate
how that's going to happen.
I'm going to go ahead and indent our object.
This is going to make it a little easier to read and add it.
Now that we have this in place I'm going to remove the string and call new object id just like we imported
it up above.
Now new object idea as we saw in the previous video it does take an argument and the ID in this case
we have it stored as a string.
This is going to work as expected.
What we're doing here is we're querying and need to do is collection looking for any records that have
an underscore ID property equal to the ID we have right here.
Now I can go ahead and save this file.
You give things a refreshed by running the script again and we get the same exact to do.
I can go ahead and change it for the walk the dog to do by copying the string value pasting that inside
of the object id constructor function and rerunning the script.
When I do this I get the walk the dog to do return because that was the object ID.
I queried no queering in this fashion is one of the ways we'll be using find but there are other methods
other than to array that are available on our cursors.
We can explore other ones by heading over to the docks for the native driver over inside of chrome and
the Mongo DB docks pulled up.
These are the docks I showed you how to access earlier in the section and on the left hand side we have
the cursor section.
If you click that we can view a list of all the methods available to us on that cursor.
This is what comes back from.
Find down below at the very bottom of the list we have our two array method one that we're going to
look at right now is called Count up above.
You can go ahead and click count.
It's going to bring you to the documentation and the documentation for the native driver is actually
really good.
There is a complete list of all the arguments that you can provide some of them are optional some of
them are required.
And there is usually a real world example down below.
We can figure out exactly how to use count.
Now we're going to go ahead and implement count over inside of atom.
What I'm going to do is take the current queery copy it to the clipboard and then comment it out.
And down below I'm going to go ahead and replace our call to 2 array with a call to count.
Let's go ahead and remove the query that we pass in to find what we're going to do here is count up
all of the dues in the dues collection instead of having a call to array.
We're going to have a call to count instead.
Now as you saw inside of the examples for count they call count like this calling count passing in a
callback function that gets called with an error or the actual count.
You can also have a promise as the way to access that data which is exactly what we did with two array.
In our case instead of passing a callback function like this we're going to use the promise.
Instead we already have the promise set up.
We need to do to fix this is change docs to count and then we're going to remove the console log call
where we print the docs to the screen and right after we print to do's we're going to print to Dewes
count with a colon passing in the value.
Now this is not a template string but I am going to go ahead and swap it out with one replacing the
quotes with the ticks right here.
I can pass in the count awesome now that we have this in place we have a way to count up all of the
to do's in the two do's collection over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to go ahead and shut down our previous script or rerun it.
And what do we get.
We get to do is count two which is exactly correct.
The cursor that we have here a call to find returns everything in the deduced collection if you count
all of that up you're going to get those two to do items.
Now once again count end to array.
There are just a subset of all of the awesome methods you have available to you.
There are entire courses on Mongo D.B and a mongo DB for node.
We're not going to be using most of these methods but by now you should have a good idea about how you
can implement them.
Go ahead and scan the list for something that you think might be useful.
Check out the examples and try to implement it in your code.
Now we will be using other methods whether we use the Mongo D-B native driver or as you'll see later
the library mongoose.
But for now let's go ahead and do a challenge.
Given what you know to get started let's head into robo Mongo.
Open up the users collection and take a look at all of the documents we have inside of there.
We currently have five if you don't have the exact same number or yours are a little different.
That is fine.
I'm going to highlight them right click them and click expand recursively.
This is going to show me all of the key value pairs for each document currently.
Aside from the ID they're all identical names Andrew age 25 and location is Philadelphia.
I'm going to tweak the name property for two.
I'm going to right click the first document and change the name to something like.
John that I'll go ahead and do the same thing for the second document.
I'm going to edit that document and change the name from Andrew to Mike.
Now I have one document with the name of John one with Mike and three with Andrew.
The challenge for you in this video is going to be to queries your users looking for all of the users
with the name equal to the name you provided in the script.
In this case I'm going to try to query for all documents in the users collection where name is Andrew.
Then I'm going to print them into the screen and I would expect to get three back the two up above with
the name of Jan and with a name of Mike should not show up.
Now in order to do this all you need to do is go over to Adam comment out our previous query and add
a new one down below.
Take a moment to write this query.
Run it from the terminal and make sure the correct number of documents returns.
Remember if you didn't have 5 you might not get three.
Just make sure that the data you view in Roboam mango is the data that comes back.
Take a moment to knock this out test it.
Pause the video and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to write that query and get the data back.
If you were that is fantastic if you weren't that's also great.
We're going to go ahead and do it together right now.
The first thing we need to do is patch from that collection.
This is going to be the user's collection as opposed to the to do's collection we've used in this video
D-B Dom collection and we're looking for the users collection with an upper case you.
And now we're going to go ahead and call find passing in our queery remember querying was a part of
this challenge.
We want to queery fetching all documents where the name lowercase N is equal to the string.
Andrew upper case A.
Now this is going to return the cursor in order to actually get the documents.
We have to call to array just like this.
We now have a promise we can attach a then call on to two array to do something with the docs.
If the documents are going to come back as the first argument in our success handler and right inside
of the function itself we can print the docs to the screen.
I'm going to go ahead and use console dialog.
Jason docstring ify passing in our three classic arguments.
The object itself undefined and two for formatting were this in place.
We are now done the challenge we have a query and it should work.
We can test it by running it from the terminal over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to go ahead and shut down the previous connection and rerun the script when I do this.
What do I get.
I get my three documents back.
All of them have a name equal to Andrew and that is correct because of the query we set up.
Notice the documents with a name equal to Mike or gen are nowhere to be found.
With this in place we now know how to insert and query data from the database.
Up next we're going to take a look at how we can remove and update documents.
It's all coming up soon so stay tuned.
I will see you next time.