Before we go any further I do want to add a version control to this project.
In this video we're going to create a new repo locally.
We'll make a new get hub repository and we'll push our code to that get how that repository.
If you're already familiar with get or get hub you can go ahead and do that on your own you don't need
to watch this video if you're just getting started and you want to treat this video as a challenge.
That's great too.
I highly recommend taking this video as a challenge.
If you're new to get and it doesn't make sense just yet that's fine.
Also simply follow along and we'll go through the whole process.
This one is going to be really simple nothing.
Mongo DB related here to get started.
I am going to go ahead and initialize a new get repository from the terminal using get in it which we
explored in the previous section.
This is going to initialize a new repository and I can always run and get status like this to take a
look at the files that are on tracked right here we have our playground folder which we do want to add
under version control and we have packaged up Jason.
We also have node modules we do not want to track this directory.
This contains all of our NPM libraries to ignore node modules over inside of atom.
We're going to make that get ignore or file in the root of our project.
If you remember this lets you specify files and folders that you want to leave out of your version control
right here.
I'm going to create a new file.
Don't get ignore in order to ignore the node modules directory all we have to do is type it exactly
as it shown here.
Node.
Underscore modules a forward slash.
I'm going to save the file rerun and get status from the terminal and what do we get.
We get the get.
Ignore folder showing up any node modules folder is nowhere in sight.
The next thing we're going to do is make our first commit using two commands.
First up I'm going to use GET add a dot to add everything to the next commit.
Then I can make that commit using a get commit with the M flag.
A good message for this commit would be and it commit.
Excellent.
Now before we go I do want to make a good home repository and get this code up there.
That is going to require me to open up the browser and go to get hub dot com.
Once you're logged in we can make a new repo just like we did in the previous section.
I'm going to make a new repo and give it a name.
I'm going to go with a node course hyphen to to do API.
Excellent.
You can name your something else I'm going to go with this one to keep the course files organized.
Now I can go ahead and create this repository.
And as you remember you get how it actually gives us a few helpful commands in this case we're pushing
an existing repository from the command line.
We already went through the steps of initializing the repository outing our files and making our first
commit.
That means I can take these two lines copy them head over to the terminal and paste them in.
Now you might need to do these one at a time depending on your operating system.
On the Mac when I try to paste in multiple commands it's going to run all but the last and I just hit
enter to run the last one.
Take a moment to knock that out for your operating system you might need to run it as one command or
you may be able to paste it all in and hit enter.
Either way what we have here is our code pushed up to get hub.
I can prove that it's pushed up by refreshing the repository page and right here we have all of our
source code they get in your filed package.
Jason and we have our playground directory with our Mongo DB scripts.
That is it for this one.
As promised this one is simple Sure and unrelated to Mongo D-B itself.
I'll see you next time.
As we explore how to delete data from a mongo IDB collection