In this video you're going to learn how to delete documents from your Mongo DB collections before we
get into that exploring the methods that let us delete multiple documents or just one.
We want to create a few more to do.
Currently the dues collection only has two items and we're going to need a few more in order to play
around with all these methods involving deletion.
Now I do have to I'm going to go ahead and create a third by right clicking down below.
We'll make a new document with a text property equal to something like eat lunch.
Not sure why that's going on my To Do list but it is and will set completed equal to false.
Since I haven't eaten lunch today.
Now before we save this I am going to copy it to the clipboard.
We're going to create a few duplicate to do's so we can see how we can delete items based off of a specific
criteria for this case.
We're going to be deleting multiple to do's with the same text value.
I'm going to copy that to the clipboard.
Click save and then I'll create two more with the exact same structure.
Is the first one and here is the second.
Awesome.
Now we have three to do's that are identical except for the ID and we have two that have unique text
properties.
With this in place let's go ahead and move into Adam and start writing some code.
I'm going to duplicate the Find File creating a brand new file called a mongo D-B hyphen and delete
Dot.
Yes and here we'll explore the methods for deleting data.
I'm also going to remove all of the queries that we set up in the last video.
I am going to keep the DB close method commented out as once again we don't want to close the connection
just yet.
It's going to interfere with the statements we're about to write.
Now there are three methods that we'll be using in order to remove data.
The first one is going to be delete many delete many will let us target many documents and remove them
will be using delete one which targets one document and removes it.
And finally my favorite will be using Find one and delete find one end delete lets you remove an individual
item and it also returns those values.
Imagine I want to delete a to do I deleted to do but I also get that to do object back so I can tell
the user exactly which one got deleted.
This is a really useful method.
Now we're going to start off with delete many and we're going to target those duplicates we just created.
The goal here is to delete every single to do inside of the to do's collection that has a text property
equal to eat lunch.
Currently there are three out of five that fit that criteria over inside of Adam.
We can go ahead and kick things off by doing D-B duck collection.
We've used this before.
This is going to let us target our dues collection.
Now we can go ahead and use the collection method.
Delete many passing in the arguments in this case the only argument we need is our object and this object
is just like the object we passed to find we can target r to Dewes.
In this case we're going to delete every to do where the text equals uppercase.
Eat Eat lunch.
We didn't use any punctuation over here so we're also going to avoid punctuation over an atom and needs
to show up exactly the same.
Now that we have this in place we could go ahead and tack on a then call to do something when an either
succeeds or fails.
For now we'll just add a success case.
We are going to get a result argument passed back to the callback and we can print that to the screen
Council a dialogue result and we'll take a look at exactly what is in and this result object in just
a moment with this in place.
We now have a script that deletes all to do's where the text value is eat lunch.
Let's go ahead and run it and see exactly what happens over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to run this file.
It's in the playground folder and we just called it Mongo D-B hyphen.
Delete that.
Yes.
Now when I run it we get a lot of output.
The really important piece of output.
The only important piece actually is up at the very top.
If you scroll to the top where you're going to see this result object we get.
OK set to 1 which means things that did go as expected and we get and set to three.
And is the number of records that were deleted in this case we had three to do's that matched that criteria.
So three to do's were deleted.
This is how you can target and delete many to do.
Now aside from delete many we have delete one and delete one.
Works exactly the same as delete many.
Only it deletes the first item it sees that matches the criteria and then it stops.
To illustrate exactly how this works we're going to create two items inside of our collection.
If I give things a refresh you see now we only have those two documents.
These are the ones we started with.
I'm going to insert documents again using the same data that's already in my clipboard.
This time will just make to two that are identical.
The goal here is to use delete one to delete the document where the text equals eat lunch.
But since we're using delete one and not delete many one of these should stay around and one of them
should go away.
Back inside an atom we can go ahead and get started by calling debug collection with the collection
name we want to target.
In this case it's to Dewes again and we're going to use delete one delete one takes that same criteria.
We're going to target documents where text equals eat lunch.
This time though instead of deleting multiple documents we're just going to delete the one and we are
still going to get that same exact result.
To prove it I'll just print to the screen like we did up above.
Console dialog result excellent.
With this in place we can now rerun our script and see what happens over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to shut down our current connection.
Rerun it.
And what do we get.
We get an A similar looking object a bunch of junk we don't really care about but once again if we scroll
to the top we have our results object.
We're OK as one and the number of deleted documents is also one.
Even though multiple documents did pass this criteria it only deleted the first one and we can prove
that by going over to Rodel Mongo right clicking up above and viewing the documents again and this time
around we have three to do's.
We do still have one of the do's with the eat lunch text and now that we know how to use these two methods
I want to take a look at my favorite.
This is find one and delete most of the time when I'm deleting a document.
I only have the ID.
This means that I don't exactly know what the text is or the completed status and it can be really useful
depending on your user interface.
For example if I delete a to do maybe I want to show that down below saying you deleted the to do that
says eat lunch with a little undo button in case they didn't mean to take that action.
Getting the data back as well as deleting it can be a really useful thing in order to explore find one
and delete we're going to once again target to do where the text equals eat lunch.
I'm going to go ahead and comment out delete one and down below we can get started by accessing the
appropriate collection.
The method is called Find one and delete find one and delete.
Takes a very similar set of arguments.
The only thing we need to pass in is the query.
This is going to be identical to the ones we have above this time though let's go ahead and target to
do's that have a completed value set to false.
Now there are two to do's that fit this query but once again we're using a find one method which means
it's only going to target the first one it sees the one with a text of something to do back inside of
out and we can get this done by targeting to Doo's where completed equals false.
Now instead of getting back a result object with an ok property and an end property defined one end.
The method actually gets that document back.
This means we can tack on a then call.
We can get our result and we can print it to the screen.
Once again console dialog result awesome.
Now that we have this in place let's test things out over in the terminal over in the terminal.
I'm going to shut down the script and started up again this time around.
What do we get.
We get a few different things in our result object.
We do get an ok set to 1 letting us know things went as planned.
We have a last error object.
We'll talk about that in just a second.
And we have are a value object.
This is the actual document we deleted.
This is why the Find want to delete method is just super handy.
It gets that document back as well as deleting it know in this particular case the last air object once
again just has our end property and we can see the number of dues that were deleted.
There is other information that could potentially be in the last air object but that's only going to
happen when we use other methods so we'll look at that when the time comes.
For now when you delete a to do we just get the number back.
With this in place we have three different ways we can target our Mongo DB documents and remove them.
As I mentioned I think three times already find one and delete is my personal favorite.
With this in place we're going to go ahead and go over a quick challenge to test your skills inside
of Roboam Monga.
We can look at the data we have in that user's collection.
I'm going to open it up.
Highlight all the data and expand it recursively so we can view it.
We have the name Jan. We have Mike we have Andrew Andrew and Andrew.
This is perfect data.
Now yours might look a little different but the goal is to use two methods.
First up look for any duplicates anything that has a name set to the name of another document in this
case I have three documents where name is Andrew.
What I want to do is use delete many to target all of these documents and remove them.
I also want to use find a one and delete to delete a no other document doesn't matter which one.
And I want you to delete it by deed.
You can break this up into two parts.
You can write both commands then you can comment one out run the script make sure it works and then
swap it commenting out the one you read on an on commenting.
The other one in the end both statements should show their effect over inside of Roboam Mongo.
When I'm done I'm hoping to see these three documents deleted.
They all have the name Andrew and I'm hoping to see this document deleted where the name is Mike because
I'm going to target this one by ID in my find one and delete method call.
Take a moment to knock this out.
Write these scripts.
Test them.
And when you're done go ahead and click play.
How do you do.
Hopefully you were able to get this done without too much trouble.
First up I'm going to write my scripts one for deleting users where the name is Andrew and one for deleting
the document with this ID in order to grab the idea I am going to go ahead and edit it and simply grab
the text inside of quotes right here and then I can cancel the update and move into Adam.
First up we're going to go ahead and tried to remove the duplicate users and I'm going to do this using
DBI dot collection.
We're going to target that users collection.
And in this particular case we're going to be using the delete the many method and Dot delete many just
like we did above here.
We're going to try to delete all of the users where the name property equals Andrew.
Now I could tack on a then call to check for success or errors or I could just leave it like this which
is what I'm going to do.
If you used a callback or you used the promise then method that is perfectly fine as long as the deletion
happens you're good to go.
Next up I'm going to write the other statement we're going to target the users collection once again.
This should be users and not user.
This statement would not have worked how to use the user collection.
Now we're going to go ahead and use the Find one and delete method.
Now in this particular case I am going to be deleting the to do where the ID equals the object id I
have copied to the clipboard which means I need to create a new object ID and I also need to go ahead
and pass in the value from the clipboard inside of quotes either single or double work.
Make sure the capitalization of object id here is identical to what you have up above.
Otherwise this creation will not happen.
Now that we have the ID created and passed in as the underscore ID property we can go ahead and tack
on a then callback.
Since I'm using find one end Doley I am going to print that document to the screen right here and I'll
get my argument results and I'm going to print to the screen using our pretty printing method Council
dialogue Jason docstring ify passing in those three arguments the results undefined and the spacing
which I'm going to use as to with this in place we are now ready to go.
Let's go ahead and comment out you find one and delete first.
We'll run the delete many statement over in the terminal I can shut down the current connection started
up again and if we go over to robo Mongo we should see that those three documents were deleted.
I'm going to right click up above to view the documents and what do we get.
We just get the two documents back anything.
Her name was Andrew is now removed which means our statement did work as expected.
And this is fantastic.
Next up we can run our find one and delete statement in this case we're expecting that that one document
the one where name equals Mike gets removed.
I'm going to go ahead and make sure I save the file.
Once I did I can move into the terminal and rerun the script.
This time around we get the document back where name is Mike.
We did target the correct one and it does appear that one item was deleted.
I can always go ahead and verify this by refreshing the collection over inside of Roboam Mongo.
And what do I get.
I get my collection with just one document inside of it with this in place we are now done.
We know how to delete documents from our Mongo DB collections.
We can delete multiple documents we can target just one or we can target one and get its value back
before we go let's go ahead and make a commit pushing it up to get her over in the terminal.
I can shut down the script and I can run get status to see what files we have on tracked.
Here we have our Mongo DB delete file.
I can add it using get add dot and then I can commit using get commit with the flag.
Here I can go ahead and provide a commit message add delete script.
Excellent.
I'm going to make that comment and I am going to push it up to get it using and get push which will
default to the Orjan remote.
Now when you only have one remote the first one is Orjan.
This is the default name just like Master is the default branch.
With this in place we are now done our code is up on get hub.
I'll see you next time as we continue looking at Mongo DB methods.
Next up is updating you're going to learn how to update documents inside of a collection.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then